泰坦尼克号——人类历史上最出名的船，多半没有之一！
The RMS Titanic is probably the most famous ship in human history.
其名声大噪，主要是因为大伙都知道它寄得多惨
That popularity only steamrolled by how many people know that it went out sad,
堪称史上最惨烈单船沉没事故的No.1
with its demise being the deadliest single ship wreck of all time.
如今它成了海底标本
It is a relic now,
但当年刚下水时，可是水灵灵的20世纪工程奇迹
but that beauty was an early 20th century marvel when it first hit the waves.
泰坦尼克号是艘大英帝国缔造，用于客运的巨轮
The Titanic was built in the United Kingdom as a passenger ship,
这个庞然大物创下了当时体积之最
the biggest ship there ever was at the time
也给现实讽刺文学的留下了浓重一笔
and is the leading example of real-life irony.
当年它大肆吹嘘的就是
One of the main things it was known for in its time
它“现代最强”的顶配安全性能
was the vessel's then state-of-the-art safety features,
宣传说使上了最潮最新的科技
with the latest technology available
来预防和应对海上意外
to prevent and respond to an emergency at sea.
泰坦尼克与其姐妹船奥林匹克的官方宣传册上
In promotional material for the Titanic and its sister ship, the Olympia,
直接立下了flag，声称
they were described by saying,
“如果这真有可能的话”
As far as it is possible to do so,
“这两首船是按着永不沉没设计的（会沉吗？不会的）”
these two wonderful vessels are designed to be unsinkable.
结果呢？泰坦尼克，在它的首航
Where the Titanic, of course, on its first ever voyage
直接表演了个史诗级翻车
would go on to shit the bed spectacularly
和冰山来了场激烈亲密接触后当场去世
by having violent intercourse with an iceberg and die.
不管你看没看过泰坦尼克号主题的小黄片
Whether you watch X-rated Titanic parodies or not
1912年4月15日晚11:40，它开始咕嘟咕嘟沉
the ship went under on April 15th, 1912 at 11.40pm,
耗时2小时40分钟彻底扑街
and took roughly 2 hrs and 40 mins before the boat was fully claimed by the seas.
船上载满了2200多人
There were some 2,200 people aboard that ship,
救生艇却只够装个零头
and there were only enough lifeboats to save a fraction of those passengers,
1500往上乘客直接在冰海里冻成冰棍
leaving over 1,500 people to perish in the frigid sea.
几天后，事故曝光在公众视野
A few days later, when the scope of the tragedy reached the general public,
全民炸锅，愤怒于怎么能有等惨剧发生
it caused outrage over how something like this could even happen.
直接催生了海运安全新规
It led to major changes in safety regulations at sea,
比如'船必须配够全员的救生艇'
like a requirement to carry enough lifeboats for all people on board a vessel.
哇哦，真是个天才规定
What a brilliant idea.
提出这主意的人真是个小机灵鬼！
Whoever made that happen's a genius.
至于它的文化影响力？不用我多说了吧
Beyond that, I don't need to tell you about the Titanic's cultural impact.
你活在处处被它影响的时代里
You literally live in its wake.
没有它，你可能至今不知道小李子叫啥
It's the reason to know Leonardo DiCaprio's name.
而对我来说，泰坦尼克算是初恋般的存在
As for me, the Titanic was my first love, you might say.
我第一次的“过度专注”
My first hyperfixation.
“过度专注”指对特定对象或活动表现出极度投入的心理状态,常见于自闭症等人群
这里画面是表达管主早该意识到自己有自闭症
是我幼儿园时期的终极精神鸦片
It was all I thought about for the entire school year as a kindergartner,
除了中间短暂爬墙某些鲨鱼话题之外
with a brief break where I got really into sharks.
我读遍了所有能找的泰坦尼克童书
I read every book on the Titanic I could.
还用蜡笔自创了魔改版
I wrote my own terrible versions with crayon and colored pencil.
不算抄袭！
It's not plagiarism,
毕竟我连抄的字都认不全
because I didn't know half the words I was reading to copy them.
但我清楚地记得它有四个烟囱！
And I knew that the Titanic had four smokestacks exactly.
毕竟...俺会数数！
Because yeah, I can count.
但话说回来，谁关心过事故的另一位主角？
With all that said, though, what about the other side of the coin?
我痴迷于那艘沉船一辈子
All my life, I've been obsessed over the ship that sank,
从未停下来思考究竟是什么导致了沉没
but I never stopped to think about what did the sinking.
把泰坦尼克送进海底坟场的那位，又是咋样？
What about the thing that sent the Titanic to its watery grave?
我说的那座冰山
The iceberg.
呃...它也就还行吧？
I mean, yeah, it's all right, I guess.
宝贝们！欢迎来到《走进冰山—冰山之冰山图》！
Hi again, guys, and welcome to the Iceberg Iceberg Explained.
我老早想自己搞张冰山图了
I wanted to make my own iceberg chart for a while,
但本人实在做不到单纯享受爱好
but I'm not capable of just letting myself enjoy stuff,
所以先叠个自黑buff，万一做砸了就当搞笑视频了
so I made a joke of the concept as a defensive layer of irony if this goes badly.
我看了一堆关于“冰山图”的冰山图
I saw a whole lot of iceberg charts about iceberg charts,
但真·冰山的内容毛都没有！
but barely anything about the real ones.
属于让检索资料冰上加冰了
It made researching this video harder,
现在搜啥+ “冰山” 跳出来的全是“冰山图”！
because looking up anything plus iceberg just gives you a chart now.
我最初觉得死都不可能爱上冰山
Still, I didn't think I'd end up liking actual icebergs
不过研究完真·冰山后
as much as I do now after researching.
老子直接叛变革命了
I've completely switched teams.
啥泰坦尼克就沉他丫的吧！
The Titanic had it coming.
眼前这张图是我东拼西凑的
The chart you see here, I put together myself.
借鉴了几张现有图表
I pulled from a few existing charts,
但对于我想完成的这个视频，都不太合意
but none were quite what I wanted from this video,
干脆自己撸袖子整活
so I made my own.
致敬那些前人栽树
Shout out to the folks who did the hard work before me
让我能后人美美蹭流量（口动狗头）
so I could profit off it on a YouTube video, /j.
叠甲声明：有些内容不算严格意义上的冰山相关
Up front, some of these aren't directly iceberg related.
我的标准是，要么和冰山直接有关
My general criteria was including stuff that at least has to do with them,
要么是冰山常出没的场景
or where icebergs usually show up,
或者...纯粹就是我想讲
but also if I just wanted to talk about it.
这种大杂烩视频难免有纰漏
Any video I make this big is bound to have some slip-ups,
如果有漏了啥你觉得该加的
and if there's anything I missed that you think should be in here,
或者你捉了什么虫
or that you caught and want to correct,
请评论区斧正！
please do so in the comments.
另外，手动空格——
I'm gonna give a blanket.
我会疯狂读错词！提前声明！
I will mispronounce things warning now,
我就不用接下来一直道歉
so I'm not stopping to say sorry
当我搞错了我不会的语言的发音时
every time I butcher a language I don't speak.
嗯，我会说错些东西
So yeah, I'm gonna say things wrong.
我的错，那咋了！
Uh, my bad.
继续前，最后的重点
Last thing before we dive in,
这是我鸽了很久的复更视频，经过一些...
this is my first video back after my
额，不可抗力
unplanned hiatus,
然而只有20%老铁点了关注
and still somehow only 20% of y'all are subscribed with notifications on.
想蹲我后续瞎扯淡的
If you want to see what I've got coming down my asshole in the future,
订阅+一键三连搞起，兄弟伙些！
it'd mean a lot if you subscribe and hit the bell icon.
嫌我烦了随时取关，买卖不成仁义在！
Plus, you can always undo it later if you decide you hate me.
嘿嘿嘿嘿，等等！先别划走！
Hey, hey, hey, hey, hey, but first, just chill out for a second, let's relax,
让我感谢下本视频的金主爸爸
and let me tell you about this video's sponsor,
让这一切成为可能的神人们（后面是叶子广告）
the nutjobs who made it all possible,
总之 说回冰山吧
Anyways, back to the icebergs
啊 看看这只可爱的小狗狗 放松一下
Aw, look at this cute doggy and relax a little
毕竟 这只是第一层：你这冰山怎么尖尖的
After all, it's only layer one. Just the tip
“冰山一角”这个词本身
The tip of the iceberg
（当然 泰坦尼克号不算在内）恰好就是我们的第一个条目
is fittingly our first entry, if you ignore Titanic
这个说法的来源是 冰山只有10%的体积露在水面上
It's saying that comes from an iceberg only having 10% of its mass visible above water,
而它的大部分都在水下 我们是看不见的
where most of the thing is submerged underwater where we can't see it
这也是冰山图这个东西的起源
It's origin of every iceberg chart
废话 这不就是重点嘛
No shit, that's like the whole point
冰山图指的是把某个特定话题的常识比作一捏捏
And it compares how common knowledge of a given topic is only the tip of the ice,
就像冰山一样
and that like an iceberg
而你能学到的关于一个主题的大部分信息 都得你潜到深水里才能看见
most of what you can learn about a subject is information that you gotta dive deep into the water to see
很多人相信 这个说法是在20世纪初开始流行的
Lots of people believe the saying was popularized in the early 1900s,
很大程度上是因为泰坦尼克号的沉没才开始流行起来的
in large part a result of the Titanic hitting a new low,
那件事让冰山在当时火了一把
as that rocketed icebergs into public awareness at the time
在写作上 “冰山理论” 也叫“省略理论” 是由欧内斯特·海明威创造的
Now, in writing, iceberg theory, also called theory of omission, is coined by Ernest Hemingway
它本质上和这个俗语的意思一样 只是变成了（写作remix）
and essentially it means the same thing as the saying, but applied to writing
海明威在回忆录《午后之死》中 就把这种写法比作冰山
In Hemingway's memoirs, specifically in Death in the Afternoon, he compares this theory of writing to an iceberg
这位作家说 他会有意省略故事的部分内容
The author said he omitted parts of a story on purpose
并以一种能让读者察觉到信息被刻意隐去的方式写作
in a way where the reader is made aware that information in the story is being withheld from them
即便读者永远都无法确切知道那些信息是什么
That even though a person will never get to know exactly what that info is,
但这种有意的省略却能通过制造悬念 从而增强故事的张力
leaving out that information on purpose strengthened the story by creating intrigue
汉斯·赫托夫特号
The MS Hans Hedtoft
这是一艘丹麦的客货两用船 它在1959年1月沉没了
was a Danish cargo passenger liner that sank in January 1959
而其沉没的方式很经典 就是撞上了冰山
via the classical crash into an iceberg
这艘船是以丹麦第14任首相的名字命名的
The ship was named after the 14th prime minister of Denmark
而他的名字是——汉斯·赫托夫特
named get this, Hans Hedtoft
在我看来 他算是个明事理的人 因为他并不怎么喜欢纳粹
He seemed like a decent opinion haver to me in that he was not a huge fan of Nazis
我觉得这非常勇敢
I personally agree, it's very brave, I know
截至撰写本文时
As of writing this,
汉斯·赫托夫特号是目前已知最后一艘因撞上冰山而沉没、并造成人员伤亡的船只
the Hedtoft is currently the last ship known to be sunk by an iceberg that resulted in casualties
该船沉没时 还带走了船上全部的95人以及其宝贵的冷冻鱼货
The ship lost all 95 people aboard, plus its precious cargo of frozen fish when it sank
讽刺的是 其唯一被发现了的残骸是一个救生圈
Ironically, the only piece of wreckage ever discovered was a lifebelt
如果你能暂时忘了海托夫特号最终失败的结局
If you forget for a second that the Hedtoft ended up being a failure,
它本身其实是一艘相当不错的小船
it was actually a pretty neat little boat on its own
它从哥本哈根前往格陵兰的首航前半程快得打破了纪录
The first half of its maiden voyage from Copenhagen to Greenland was made in record time,
结果却在返航途中遇上了极其恶劣的天气 于是它就这么完蛋了
before some uniquely terrible weather conditions did them in on the way back around
2005年 一座纪念遇难者的纪念碑在哥本哈根的北大西洋码头揭幕
A monument to those who died was unveiled in 2005 at the North Atlantic wharf in Copenhagen
《企鹅俱乐部》里的冰山
The iceberg from Club Penguin
这是漂浮在企鹅俱乐部岛东北方向虚拟水域上的一块冰
was a chunk of ice floating on the digital water northeast of Club Penguin Island
大多数时候 它就是一块白色的空地
Most days, it was just an open white floor
大家会在上面跳着杀马特舞蹈
that people would bust out the mid-2000s versions of Fortnite emotes on
但这些年来它也经历了一些变化
but it saw changes over the years,
比如增加了游戏 还有几次活动中的派对改变了冰山的布局
like the additions of games, as well as several event parties which would alter the iceberg's layout
当然了 这东西最出名的还是那个流传已久的都市传说
Of course, this thing is best known for its long-standing urban legend
即据说只要有足够多的企鹅站在上面 就能把冰山给掀翻
where if enough penguins stood on the thing, it was said you could flip the iceberg to its other side
这事儿让玩家们激动得不行 大家都在讨论到底要怎样才能把那块冰给掀翻
It had people foaming at the mouth, discussing what it took to flip that ice,
有的人是真正在研究 有的人则纯粹是在瞎搞
either genuinely theorizing or just making shit the fuck up
最典的谣言之一是 只要有足够多的企鹅使用安全帽道具附带的“手提钻3000”表情
One of the biggest rumors was that if enough penguins used the Jackhammer 3000 emote
就能让那块冰整个翻过来 让它屁股朝天
you could convince the ice to go ass up, face down
在一段时间里 这都纯属扯淡  （消息来源  我瞎编的）
For a while, that was all total horseshit. (Source: I lied)
但官方半开玩笑地回应了这个谣言
but the rumor would get tongue-in-cheek nods from the developers,
比如在游戏后期 他们把一幅翻过来的冰山画作成了一个彩蛋
like a painting of a tipped over iceberg being an Easter egg in other parts of the game later on
但当原始服务器准备关闭时
But when the original servers were getting ready to shut down,
《企鹅俱乐部》的最后一场派对
the Waddle On party, the final party on Club Penguin,
“继续前行”派对 终于让掀翻冰山成为了可能
made it possible to finally flip the iceberg
要做到这点 需要几个蓝色企鹅 或者带了蓝色拉姆的企鹅 再一起使用手提钻表情
To do it, you needed either a few blue penguins or penguins with blue puffles equipped, and to use the Jackhammer emote together
根据你所在大厅里蓝色成员的数量 会发生不同的事
Different things would happen depending on how many blue members were in your lobby
两到四个人会让冰山摇晃 而如果有至少五名玩家 你就能终于...
Two to four people would cause the iceberg to shake, and with at least five players, you'd finally...
...终于能把这块冰掀翻了
...finally be able to flip the ice
冰山的另一面相当有情怀
The other side of the iceberg was quite sentimental
在冰山底部有一块牌匾 上面写着
There was a plaque on the underside that read,
“我们在一起 可以建立一座岛屿
"Together we can build an island,
创造一个社区 改变世界 甚至掀翻一座冰山  继续前行吧”
create a community, change the world, and even tip an iceberg. Waddle on."
泪目了
That made me cry as a grown man half a decade on
我都不知道我能泪目
I didn't know I could still do that
冰川
A glacier
就是指那种存在了很久很久、拜登似的、
is any long-running, old-as-sin body of dense ice
还会靠着自己的重量不停移动的巨大冰块
that continuously moves under its own weight
冰川是在特定条件下形成的
Glaciers form when in the right conditions,
需要积雪经过好几年 有时候是几百年 甚至更久的时间不断堆积才行
enough snow has built up over the course of years and sometimes centuries, if not longer
这些家伙不仅是所有冰山的源起
These things aren't just the birthplace of every iceberg,
它们还遍布世界各地 在除了大洋洲以外的每个大洲都有
they exist all over the world and on every continent except Australia
因为那地方热得跟地狱差不多
It is hotter than hell there
它们会把自己的触角 硬塞进任何能找到的缝隙里
They have their tendrils shoved into wherever they can find a suitable hole
还有一种叫冰盖的东西 其实就是一块特别大的冰川
There's this thing called an ice sheet, which is actually just a really big glacier
它也被称为大陆冰川
It's also called a continental glacier
这个词被用来形容覆盖面积超过50000平方公里的冰川
It's a glacial ice that takes up over 19,000 square miles of space
它只有在南极洲和格陵兰岛才能找到
and they're only found in Antarctica and Greenland
冰川也是气候变化的重要指标
Glaciers are also important indicators of climate change
而它们融化的速度 就是气候变化程度的一个标志
The speed they are melting is a sign of how aggressively the climate is changing
说到这个 首先 气候变化是真的
Speaking of, climate change is, for one, real
从这儿开始聊感觉挺合适的
That seems like a good place to start
你们肯定知道要讲这个了
You had to know this one was coming
它和其他条目也相关 毕竟要聊天然冰就绕不开它 所以这里我就简单说几句
It's relevant in other entries because it's hard not to talk about natural ice without it, so I'll be brief with this one
如今 “气候变化”一词主要指全球变暖
Climate change is mostly used today to mean global warming,
即地球年均温度持续异常攀升的现象
where average Earth temperatures have been rising more than usual year after year,
但它也更宽泛地指地球整个历史进程中的气候变迁
but it also refers more broadly to how Earth's climate has changed over its entire history
地球目前的变暖趋势 正因温室气体进入大气层而加速
The current warming of the Earth is being accelerated by greenhouse gases getting in the atmosphere
而这些气体来自化石燃料产生的排放 还有牛放屁之类的
from things like fossil fuel emissions and cows farting
气候变化导致了沙漠扩大、野火、热浪
Climate change has led to deserts growing larger, wildfires, heat waves,
以及其他的自然灾害变得比以前更剧烈、更常见
and other natural disasters becoming more intense and commonplace than before
但对我们来说最重要的是 它加快了冰川、永久冻土和海冰的融化速度
But most importantly to us, it's sped up the rate that glaciers, permafrost, and sea ice are melting
气温升高会导致更多冰块从冰川上脱落
The warming temperatures cause more ice to break off from glaciers,
也意味着我这个视频的背景里能有更多道具了
meaning I have more props in the background of this video
但这些冰山最终都会融化成液态水
But these same icebergs will ultimately melt into liquid water,
而脱落的冰越多 北极生物的栖息地就越少
and the more that breaks off, the less habitats for Arctic life there are
而生活在这些冰面上的动物 就成了你生物课本里讲的“濒危物种”
Putting many animals who live on these ice heaps in the "endangered" column of your biology textbook
冰川融化正在推高全球海平面 而人类居住的沿海地区也已经开始受到威胁
The ice melting into the ocean is causing sea levels to gradually rise, and it's already begun to encroach on the shores of where people live
预计随着更多冰的融化 海水会占据更多陆地
Areas closer to the sea are expected to have their shores pushed back as more ice melts
从而导致近海地区的海岸线向内陆后退
and the water takes up more land
冰川崩解 指的是巨大的冰块从更大的冰体上断裂脱落的现象
Ice calving is when huge chunks of ice break off from bigger pieces of ice
无论其主体是冰川、冰架 还是一个大冰山分裂成小冰山
Be that a glacier, an ice shelf, or even just a big iceberg breaking into smaller ones
冰山最初就来源于南极和格陵兰等地的崩解事件
Icebergs originally come from calving events in places like Antarctica and Greenland,
在这些地方 冰川的末端与水体相接 而断裂的冰块便落入开阔的海域
where glaciers terminate at bodies of water and the ice breaking off falls into open seas
当冰山崩解发生时 声音会非常大
When a calving comes around, it gets loud
你会听到冰块从其母体结构上断裂时发出的清脆裂声或巨大轰鸣
You'll hear the physical crack or boom of the ice breaking off from its parent structure
接着 巨大的冰块会落入水中 激起滔天巨浪
And then large chunks of ice will fall into the water, causing massive waves
如果你不够小心 这些巨浪能把船整个掀翻
that can judo flip the shit out of ships if you aren't careful
有些冰川崩解的威力堪称我一小腿过去(笑点解析:calves/calving)
Calving events at some glaciers are almost as strong as my calves,
因此人们必须远距离观望 确保安全
to the point where you have to view it from a proper distance
例如约翰斯·霍普金斯冰川崩解时
Like at Johns Hopkins Glacier, when it calves,
冰块砸入水中激起的浪大到船只必须在超过一英里半以外的地方观看
waves from ice hitting the water get so big that boats have to view the event from over a mile and a half away
那想象一下 亲眼看到那玩意儿该有多震撼
Now imagine how crazy that shit looks in person
你想了吗？
Did you do it?
你这辈子就没点自己的想法吗？
You have not had an original thought in your life
白痴 无数人都想到了 而且这主意确实不错
Tons of people already thought of that, idiot, and they were right, too
所以 像这里——伊卢利萨特和阿拉斯加等地 早就成了旅游热点
So, there are major tourism spots in places like here in Ilulissat, as well as in Alaska,
全世界的人都跑去那里 就为了亲眼看一次冰川崩解
where people come from all over the world just to see ice calve off in person
冰山翻转 就是指冰山因为质量变化等原因在水里整个翻了个个儿
Icebergs flipping is when an iceberg changes and rotates its position floating in the water based on changes, like a loss of mass or other influences
根据冰山的不同 这可能引发一系列重大后果
Depending on the ice, this can have a range of major consequences
你要知道 冰山的尺寸能大得离谱 长宽绵延好几英里
For context, icebergs can get like unbelievably large, we're talking miles and miles in both length and width
有些冰山比一些州甚至国家还大
Some have been bigger than states and the size of countries
这些巨大的冰山通常因其尺寸而非常稳定
and these big ones are generally very stable because of their size
因为它们绝大部分体积都在水下 从而使其保持正向朝上
and therefore, how much of the iceberg is under the water, keeping it right side up
但问题是 一座冰山不需要那么大 也能掀起滔天巨浪
The thing is, a berg doesn't need to be that big to make a big splash
而当一座足够大的冰山翻转时 其释放的能量能堪比核弹
And when a big enough iceberg does flip, the energy release can reach the levels of a nuclear bomb
虽然能量不是像炸弹那样瞬间爆发的
The energy isn't let out all at once like a bomb,
但我想说的是 这玩意儿他妈的太危险了
but what I'm trying to get across is that shit is dangerous
川崩解和冰山翻转都能引发海啸 把靠得太近的船只直接掀翻
Ice calving and icebergs flipping can cause tsunamis that capsize ships if they get too close
总而言之 能拍到不止一座那种尺寸的冰山翻个底朝天也太牛逼了
In general, it's nuts that there has been more than one iceberg that size caught on camera while rolling over
但即便不是巨型冰山翻转
But even if it's not a large iceberg flipping,
只要你离得够近 它也照样能轻而易举地要了你的命
if you're close enough to it, it does not take a lot to turn one over, and it'll kill you, no problem
看看这个视频就知道了
Just look at this video
这段视频显然是关于两个法国佬的
That video was apparently of two French dudes
据报道他们自己也认为爬冰山很蠢 不是个好主意
who reportedly also think climbing the ice was dumb and not a great move
你可以看到 尽管冰山看起来很大 但它们的形状依旧混乱 稳定性也毫无保障
You can see that despite how large icebergs can seem, even relative to people, they are still shaped like a mess and their stability is not guaranteed
众所周知 这玩意儿经常因为一点点小事就翻身 这简直就是我
These things are known to get rotated a lot based on very little, which is just like me for real
而这俩哥们儿一爬 正好把力用对了地方 光凭他们自己就把它给弄翻了
And these dudes climbing, putting force in just the right places, was enough on its own to tip one over
再说 他们反正也爬不到顶
Plus, it's not like they were gonna reach the top of it anyways
就好像这两个家伙没玩过《现代战争2》（那部老的）一样
It's like these guys didn't play Modern Warfare 2 (the first one)
你的冰镐和德莫尼亚牌冰鞋呢 小伙子？
Where are your ice picks and Demonia ice boots, young man?
冰架就是冰川伸到海里的那一大片浮冰 冰山就是从它上面掉下来的
An ice shelf is the part of a glacier that an iceberg will actually break off from
它是冰川流入海洋的部分形成的冰
It's ice that forms at the part of a glacier that flows into the ocean
就和冰盖一样 它们仅存在于南极洲和格陵兰 以及北极俄罗斯和加拿大北部
Like ice sheets, they are only found in Antarctica and Greenland, as well as Arctic Russia and northern Canada as well
不过最近 冰架一直在大幅度缩小
Recently though, ice shelves have been shrinking big time
通常 冰架因为崩解和融化失去的冰会被新的冰雪补充 从而达到一种平衡
Usually the ice that a shelf would lose from things like calving events and melting is replenished by new ice and snow coming through, creating a sort of equilibrium
但近来 冰架的冰损失速度和补充速度之间已经完全失衡了
But as of late, the pace of ice lost in ice shelves is out of whack with the amount that can be replaced
这导致一些冰架几乎完全消失了
And it's led some ice shelves to almost completely disappear
例如埃尔斯米尔冰架在20世纪期间 其发际线后退了90%
For instance, the Ellesmere ice shelf, which had its hairline pushed back by 90% during the 20th century
成为冰山的标准
Criteria to be an iceberg
有意思的是 讲了这么多 我等到现在才告诉你们真正的冰山到底是什么
It's funny that this many entries in, I'm only now telling you what a real iceberg even is
基本上 一块漂浮的淡水冰要想被视为冰山 必须满足一些既定标准
Basically, for a chunk of floating freshwater ice to be considered a berg, it has to meet some set standards
根据美国国家海洋局的规定
According to the US National Ocean Service,
想要获得“冰山”的尊贵头衔
for the prestigious title of "iceberg",
一块给定的冰体必须高出海平面超过5米
a given chunk of ice has to be over 16 feet (5m) above sea level,
厚度在30到50米之间 且覆盖面积至少为约500平方米
98 to 164 feet (30-50m) thick, and it has to cover an area of at least 5,382 square feet (500 sqm)
你能想象自己就是那块就差一米就能成为冰山的冰吗？
Can you imagine being the iceberg under the requirements by one foot?
在我剩下这不断融化的人生里 我每晚都会哭吧
I'd cry every night of what's left of my life that's literally melting away
我已经 拼尽了全力... 却还是太小了...
Like my best chance... was still too small...
这是个(CENSORED)笑话 说的是我的(CENSORED)
It's a [CENSORED] joke. About my [CENSORED].
那如果它们太小成不了冰山
But if they're too small to be icebergs,
那这些更蠢、更小、更可怜的废物冰块该叫什么呢？
what are those dumber, tinier, more pathetic bits of loser ice called?
呃 叫“小冰山”和“碎浮冰”
Uh, "bergy bits" and "growlers"
这俩都是比冰山还小的冰块的分类名
Both of those are classifications for the ice chunks smaller than an iceberg
“小冰山”是中到大型的 高出海平面至少1米但不足5米
A "bergy bit" is medium to large sized with a height of at least 3 but less than 16 feet above sea level
面积在100到大约300平方米之间的
and an area of 1,100 to something like 3,200 square feet
这些家伙能长到那么大 结果连学名都还叫“碎块”
Those dudes can get so big and still get called "bits" for their scientific name
这也太冷(酷)了吧 老兄
That's cold, man
再说尺寸 “碎浮（咆哮）冰”这名字听着挺唬人
Then, shrinking down in size, "growlers" are named like they sound intimidating,
但实际上比它们小多了 就是些小冰渣
They're actually much smaller, just little fragments of ice,
大概一架三角钢琴那么大 或者把几个Xbox 360摆成三角钢琴那么大
around the size of a grand piano or several Xbox 360s arranged in the shape of a grand piano
这么算的话 我有一个坏消息
And with that said, I have some bad news
如果一个企鹅俱乐部角色的身高是三英尺半(1.07米)
If the height of a Club Penguin avatar is three and a half feet,
以此为参照 我们来量一下企鹅俱乐部那个冰山的尺寸 结果可不太妙
using that as reference, if we measure the dimensions of the Club Penguin iceberg, it's not good
它的尺寸是9x16.5个企鹅身长 换算下来是9.6米乘17.6米
Coming in at 9 by 16.5 penguins, converted to 31.5 by 57.75 feet,
就算我们往大了算 把它当成一个完整的长方形
giving this 'berg the most generous calculation we can by treating it as a full rectangle,
其面积撑死也只有169平方米
it is still only a max of 1,819 square feet
它根本不是一个真正的冰山
It is not an actual iceberg
它只能算作他妈的“小冰山（渣）”
It's a fucking bergy bit
这玩意儿听起来也太软趴趴了吧 老兄
That shit sounds so limp, man
真不敢相信 我们居然为了一个假的冰山兴奋了那么久
I can't believe we got so excited for so long over an iceberg that lied about being one
桌状冰山 也叫“冰岛”
Tabular icebergs, also called "ice islands"
如果你看过NASA拍的那些看起来像巨大铁锭的冰板照片
If you've ever seen the photo NASA took of the big iron ingot looking ice slabs,
边缘比你花500块在理发店剪的头还齐的东西就是桌状冰山
the ones with straighter edges than you'd get from a $500 haircut, those are tabular icebergs
桌状实际上只是冰山六种形状分类中的一种 而这一种基本上就是一个平坦的长方形
Tabular is actually just one of six shape classifications an iceberg can have, and this one is essentially just a flat rectangle
它们的长高比大于五比一 并且是那种因其形状而能长得他妈的巨大的冰山
They have a length to height ratio greater than five to one and are the kind of iceberg that can get big as fuck because of their shape
它们大多来自南极洲
They mostly come from Antarctica
之所以被称为冰岛 是因为它们的表面最终会变得又大又平坦
and are called ice islands because of how large and flat their surfaces can end up being
由于其形状 桌状冰山相对稳定
Because of its shape, tabular icebergs are relatively stable,
这也使它们在历史中成为供政府使用的感兴趣之地
which has made them places of interest for government use throughout history
而其他的五种形状跟它根本没法比
It's a losing game for all five of the other shapes
就像我说的 总共有六种 而它们被分为两大类
Like I said, there are six total, and they are split into two categories
一种是桌状冰山 然后其他所有都属于另一类
There's tabular icebergs, and then all the other ones in a separate category
非桌状冰山
Non-tabular icebergs
穹顶状冰山就是顶部呈圆形的冰山
A dome is an iceberg with a rounded top
尖塔状冰山就是有一个或多个尖顶的冰山
A pinnacle is an iceberg with one or more spires
楔形冰山就是一侧陡峭 另一侧是斜坡的冰山
Wedges are icebergs with a steep edge on one side, and a slope on the other
干船坞状冰山是被侵蚀后 内部形成了一个凹槽或通道的冰山
A dry-dock is an iceberg that has eroded to have a slot or channel inside it
而块状冰山则是侧面垂直陡峭、顶部平坦的冰山
while blocky icebergs are steep with vertical sides while having a flat top
块状冰山和桌状冰山的主要区别在于
The main difference between blocky bergs and tabular ones is that
它看起来更像《我的世界》里角色的头 而不是阿尔宙斯的冰冻石板
it looks more like the head of a Minecraft character than it does the Icicle Plate for Arceus
冰山的颜色
Iceberg colors
冰山就像美国人 大多数是白色的 但也可以是其他几种颜色
Icebergs are like Americans, in that they are majority white, but can also be a few other colors
这个比喻到此为止
This is the end of that analogy
有些冰山是绿色、黑色、黄色、蓝色的
Some icebergs are green, black, yellow, blue,
有些甚至带有彩虹或条纹图案
and some even have rainbow or striped patterns,
而每一种独特外观的背后都有着不同的成因
with each having a variety of reasons behind their unique looks
蓝冰山通常在冰山水上部分融化 而此前未被雪覆盖的底部暴露出来时出现
Blue icebergs usually pop up when the part of an iceberg that was above water is melting and the underside that's been untouched by snow is exposed
所以 当它的形状改变到足以让冰山在水中重新定位时
so when its shape changes enough that an iceberg has to reposition itself floating in the water,
那种特殊的亮蓝色就会出现在水面
that striking bright blue is what pops up on the surface
在我看来 这是自然界能真实产生的最疯狂的颜色之一
In my opinion, it's one of the craziest colors you can see authentically produced in nature
颜色较深的冰山 其天然色调通常来自冰体中随时间积累的沉积物
Icebergs with a darker color usually get their natural hue from sediment picked up in the ice over time
人们曾认为绿色冰山是由溶解的有机物在已经是蓝色的冰山上变黄所致
People used to think green icebergs were caused by dissolved organic matter turning yellow on an already blue iceberg,
而两者结合便会使其变绿
which together would make it green
废话
Duh
毕竟 有机物质过去也曾以类似方式使其他东西变黄
And organic material has also made other stuff turn yellow in a similar way before
但后来发现 这是氧化铁呈现出黄色色调的结果
But it was later found to be a result of the yellow hue that iron oxides take on
它们在南极洲的地质中很常见
They're common in Antarctica's geology,
而人们发现翡翠色或绿色的冰山富含这种物质
and jade or green colored icebergs were found chock full of them
颜色也可以是冰山年龄的标志
Color can also be an indication of an iceberg's age,
年代更久远的冰山更有可能呈现出那些鲜艳的蓝色和绿色
where older ones are more likely to have those vivid blues and greens
浮冰是另一种非冰山类型的冰 你可能会在冰山出没的同样地方看到它们
Ice floes are another non-berg type of ice you might see floating around the same places that icebergs do
它们是大片的浮冰 通常比我的鼙鼓还平 但比它们宽得多
They're large sheets of floating ice that are typically flatter than my cheeks, but much wider than them
其最宽处至少有20米 有时甚至超过10公里
being at least 20 meters across at its biggest point, sometimes getting to be over 10 kilometers across
这些东西麻烦透顶 有人就曾因为站在上面时浮冰与海岸断开而被困
These things are so inconvenient, people have gotten stuck on them because they broke off the shore while they were standing on it
浮冰会将船只困在其冰原中 让探险家们进退维谷 最终丧命
Ice floes trap ships in their ice fields, stranding explorers and getting them killed
然后就是那些它们把人们的生活搞成一坨狗屎的故事了
Then there are the stories about how they've managed to make people's lives absolutely dogshit
不过 与浮冰形影不离的是流冰 它是由多个浮冰组成的海洋冰原
Hand in hand with ice floes, though, is drift ice, which is a field of sea ice that is made up of multiple ice floes
这些冰块会在河流中造成冰塞 基本上就是把河道堵住 也能损坏船体
These can cause ice jams in rivers, basically just clogging them up, and can also damage a ship's hull
在特定季节 或是冰块聚集得恰到好处地碍事时 航道会因此彻底瘫痪
During certain seasons, or if the ice has just clumped up in an annoying enough way, drift ice can make shipping routes completely inaccessible
格陵兰的伊卢利萨特镇 人口约4700 却也是这个国家最具吸引力的旅游胜地
Ilulissat, Greenland, is a town of around 4,700-ish people that's also the country's biggest tourist attraction
而我现在就在此地
It's also where I am right now
这里的雪橇犬和人一样多
They have as many sled dogs as they do people here
这个小镇的名字在西格陵兰语里的字面意思就是“冰山”
The town's name literally just means "icebergs" in West Greenlandic
我念不对它原来的名字 你知道为什么
I can't say its original name right, you know that already
但这里之所以如此受欢迎 是因为小镇离伊卢利萨特冰峡湾非常近
But it's such a popular spot because of how close the town is to the Ilulissat Icefjord,
那是北半球最高产的冰川 猛得一塌糊涂
the most productive glacier in the northern hemisphere
那家伙可是会经常吐出一些巨无霸冰山的
That thing spits out some big ass icebergs
小镇的经济主要就靠旅游业 因为它实在太吸引人了
The town's economy is mainly centered around all the tourism because of how big of a draw it is
但从个人经验来说 我可以讲这里相当不错 除非你是蚊子
But from personal experience, I can say it is quite nice, except for the mosquitoes
冰山巷 你敢信吗 也是一个观赏冰山的热点
Iceberg Alley is also a spot of interest for iceberg viewings, if you can believe it
它位于加拿大纽芬兰和拉布拉多的海岸 是人们能看到冰山的最南端地点
It's the coast of Newfoundland and Labrador in Canada and also the furthest south that you can view icebergs
这里大多数巨大的白色冰山仍然来自格陵兰 但也有一些来自加拿大北部
Most of the big white icebergs here still come from Greenland, but some originate from northern Canada
而冰山巷之所以出名 是因为它正是泰坦尼克号沉没的地方
Iceberg Alley is famous as being the place where the Titanic sank
也是世界上最具标志性的冰山观赏地之一
and as one of the most iconic places for iceberg viewing out there
那里的冰大约有1万年的历史 而且无论在陆地还是海上都能看到冰山
The ice there is about 10,000 years old and icebergs are viewable from both land and sea
你可以在海岸线上的多个地点观赏它们 也可以选择乘船游览
You can look at them from multiple points along the coastline with boat tours being an option as well
“冰山管理”是一个统称 指的是管理冰山的相关工作
Iceberg management is the general field of managing icebergs
抱歉 这些条目听起来并不是都一样刺激
Sorry they're not all exciting
不过这个我真喜欢 我超爱后勤管理（nerd）
This one is though, I love logistics
从事这类工作的团体五花八门   从监控冰山动向的联邦机构
Groups who do this kind of work include everything from federal agencies who monitor iceberg movement
到担心这些冰巨人会摧毁他们在冰山巷等地的昂贵基础设施的公司
to corporations who are worried about these ice giants destroying expensive infrastructure they have in places like Iceberg Alley
知道冰山在哪儿 以及它们接下来可能去哪儿
Knowing where icebergs are and where they will probably go next
对于保证世界上某些地区的航运和国际贸易畅通无阻至关重要
is important for shipping and international trade to not get clogged up in certain parts of the world
这有助于评估哪些社区或行业可能受到冰山移动的影响
It helps to gauge what communities or industries could be affected by iceberg movement,
比如北大西洋的船只就非常需要知道它们将面临什么样的危险
like ships in the North Atlantic needing to know what they're heading into
负责这些事的人写了些很详细的文件 老实说我并不能完全看懂
The people running this stuff write some detailed documents that I honestly can't fully understand
但我找到了一份将近一百页的报告
but I found an almost hundred-page report
专门讲如何管理大浅滩的冰山的 所以起码写这份报告的人跟我是一路人
on managing icebergs in the Grand Banks alone, so whoever wrote it is just like me for real
如果这页数还不够说明问题的话 那只能说这项工作内容非常繁杂
If the page count didn't make it obvious, there's a lot to this work,
所以我们会在后面的条目中再次讨论这类事情 讲一些更具体的冰山管理内容
so we'll revisit this kind of thing in later entries covering more specific iceberg management stuff
“史上最大的冰山们”之所以是复数
The largest icebergs ever is plural
是因为最大冰山的头衔会随着时间推移而易主
because the title of the big one changes hands over time
我干脆把几个放一起讲 免得我自己都搞混了
I might as well group a few together here instead of getting all my wires crossed
有记录以来最大的冰山是在1956年被发现的
The biggest iceberg ever reported was in 1956
当时美国海军“冰川号”舰艇 这名字肯定是故意的
when the ship the USS Glacier, these names have to be on purpose,
报告称发现了一座超过12000平方英里的冰山
reported an iceberg over 12,000 square miles wide
据测量 它长208英里 宽60英里 比比利时还大
It was measured at 208 by 60 miles long, making it bigger than Belgium
我说的是那个有华夫饼的国家 免得你不知道
The country with waffles, in case you weren't aware
不幸的是 当时还没有卫星 所以我们没有照片 也因此尺寸只能靠估算
Unfortunately satellites weren't around yet, so we don't have pictures, and the size has to be estimated
也就是说我们没法确切知道那座冰山到底有多大
meaning we can't know for sure how big the iceberg actually was
B15号冰山则是被卫星数据可靠记录下来的、面积最大的冰山
Iceberg B15 is the biggest that was reliably recorded with satellite data and by recorded area
我们能确定这家伙的大小  长159海里 宽20海里 面积3200平方海里
We are sure this thing was this big: 159 by 20 nautical miles wide, with an area of 3,200 square nautical miles
这差不多有牙买加那么大了
That's close to the size of Jamaica
就连从那个巨无霸身上分裂出来的小块 现在都还在海上漂着呢
Even pieces that split off from that big-ass dude are still out there floating around
A76号冰山曾是近年以来最大的冰山
Iceberg A76 was the largest iceberg in recent memory
直到2021年5月 它分裂成了三块
until May 2021 where it broke into three different pieces
小更正一下  A76号冰山其实最早是在2021年5月脱落的
Small correction: Iceberg A76 actually originally broke off in May 2021
但一直到2022年10月才分裂成了几块
and didn't break into several pieces until October 2022
说实话 这战绩也还可以了
Still a pretty unimpressive reign, not gonna lie to ya
最大的那一块A76A至今也还在海上 不过肯定是在融化了
The largest piece, A76A, is also still out there to this day, though it is definitely melting
最后 目前最大的是A23A
Finally, the current biggest is A23A
有趣的是   它也曾是前任最大冰山
What's interesting is that it was also the former biggest iceberg
因为在2021年5月 当A76从南极的娘胎里爬出来抢走了头衔时 它就跌下了神坛
as it lost its crown in May 2021 when A76 first climbed out of Antarctica's womb to snatch the title
但A76只卫冕了不到两年 就以闪电般的速度解体
But A76 only held the belt for under two years, breaking up at lightning speed
堪称UFC重量级历史上最令人失望的冠军之一
in one of the most disappointing title runs in UFC heavyweight history
A23A号冰山之所以能保持这么大这么久
Iceberg A23A managed to stay so big for so long
是因为它磕了胆固醇 而且它几乎没离开过它在南极的出生地
because it's on cholesterol and because it barely traveled away from its birthplace in Antarctica
它好像有点卡在海底了 这让它不太容易碎裂
It got kind of stuck on the seafloor, making it less likely to break apart
洋流也没怎么影响它 所以它一直待在较冷的水域
Ocean current didn't affect it as much so it stayed in colder waters,
让它成了冰山尺寸比拼史上唯一重登神坛的
making it the only comeback king in iceberg dick measuring history
冰山的年龄 这个可以指好几件事
An iceberg's age can refer to multiple things
主要指的是一座冰山从冰川或更大的冰山上脱落后能存活多久
The main one is how long an iceberg will live after first calving off a glacier or a bigger iceberg
有记录以来寿命最长的冰山是B09
The oldest iceberg we can be sure of was B-09,
它最早于1987年在B-15后来脱落的同一个地方断裂
which first broke off in 1987 in the same place that B-15 later would
这家伙晃悠了将近33年才精疲力竭
And this dude chugged along for almost 33 years before he gassed out
它也是有记录以来寿命最长的冰山之一
It was also one of the longest icebergs ever recorded
完蛋的时候还带走了一个叫“小美国五号”的研究站
and carried away a research station named "Little America V" when it died
我去 它是有多讨厌美国啊
Damn, he hates America that much?
真庆幸它在发现大美国之前就挂了
I'm glad he perished before he found out about Big America
B-09的尺寸是它能活那么久的一个因素
B-09's size factored into how long it lasted
因为它的质量让它在较冷的水域里卡了更长时间 为它抵达温暖海域前争取了些时间
as its mass caused it to get stuck in colder waters for longer, buying it some time before reaching warmer seas
寿命第二长的冰山A23也是同样道理 它活了将近30年
The same can be said for the next oldest iceberg, A23, that lived for almost 30 years
你可能还记得它 上个世纪它也曾是现存最大的冰山
And you might remember it from the last entry where it was also the biggest iceberg currently around
此处应有个关于A24的梗
There's an A24 joke in here somewhere
除此之外 普通冰山的寿命就全看天意了
Outside of that, the average iceberg's lifespan is at God's hands
来自冰山巷的一座冰山平均可以存活两到三年
One from Iceberg Alley may live for two to three years on average,
而那些离开冰山巷向南漂流的冰山则很少能持续超过一年
while those that head south out of the alley rarely last more than a year
就会融化到不再符合冰山标准的大小
before they melt to a size no longer considered an iceberg
冰山年龄的另一个意思则是指冰本身有多古老
The other meaning of an iceberg's age refers to how old the ice itself is,
这可以追溯到远早于有记录的历史之前
which can go back to well before recorded history
还记得冰川可以随着时间缓慢移动吗？
Remember how glaciers move slowly over time?
嗯 我说的可是真的慢
Well, I meant really slow
一般来说 冰川里的冰要移动几千年 才能断裂下来变成一座冰山
Generally, it takes thousands of years before the ice in a glacier has moved enough to break off and become a berg
举个例子 一座北大西洋冰山的生命周期大概是这样的
Just for an example, an iceberg in the North Atlantic might have a life cycle something like this
公元前1000年 它还只是一堆雪
In 1000 BC, it's all just snow
直到公元前950年 这些雪才被压实 成为冰川的一部分
That's all there is until 950 BC, where the snow has been able to harden into part of a glacier
快进几千年 比如到了90年代
Fast forward a few thousand years to like the 90s,
含有那片公元前1000年的雪的冰川 可能终于移动了足够远的距离
and the glacier may have finally moved enough for the snow from 1000 BC
断裂成了一座冰山
to break off as an iceberg,
然后在几个月或几年后最终融化掉
and finally melt away a few months or years after
这些家伙是沉默的潜伏者 存在的时间比我们长得多
These things are silent lurkers who have been around way longer than us
然后在死前还会去环游世界度个假
and go on vacation to see the world before they die
总比被困在养老院里好吧 我猜
It's better than being trapped in a retirement home, I guess
北大西洋冰山基本上就是指所有顺着北大西洋漂流下来的冰山
North Atlantic icebergs are basically any iceberg that comes down the North Atlantic Ocean
每年大概有15000到30000座冰山从那里被吐出来
Something from 15,000 to 30,000 of them get spit out of there every year,
这里可能是你能找到冰山的最著名的地方了
and it's probably the most well-known place you can find icebergs
因为这个地区的很多旅游业都是以观赏冰山为基础的
as lots of tourism in the area is based on iceberg viewing,
而且来这里玩比去南极要容易得多
and it's way easier to visit here than going to Antarctica
北大西洋的冰山季大概是从2月15日到6月1日
Iceberg season in the North Atlantic runs from about February 15th to June 1st,
这意味着我选择在7月份写这个视频的大部分稿子 简直是个天大的疏忽
meaning that writing most of this video in July was a massive fucking oversight
有记录以来 北大西洋的冰山在融化前向南漂得最远的一次
The farthest south a North Atlantic iceberg has been known to travel before melting away
是到了百慕大东北约150海里处
was about 150 nautical miles northeast of Bermuda
关于用冰山作饮用水 是这么一回事
Icebergs as drinking water, here's the deal.
冰是由淡水构成的 尽管地球上只有不到2%的水被冰封着
Ice is made of fresh water, and even though less than 2% of all Earth's water is locked in ice,
但70%的淡水 就是我们能喝下去不吐的那种 都锁在冰里
70% of fresh water, the kind we can swallow without puking, is locked in ice
如果我们能从冰山中获取水源 理论上就能帮助最需要水的地方解渴
If we could harvest the water from an iceberg, then it could theoretically help quench thirst in places that need it the most
这事儿还从没真正大规模地搞过
It's never been done at scale for real,
但把冰山拖到缺水的地区
but the idea of towing icebergs to places without enough water
让他们用上融化的冰山水 这个想法至少从70年代就有了
so they can use the melting water has been around since at least the 1970s
就算拖拽过程中会有很多冰融化
Even with how much of the ice would melt while being towed,
但据估计   剩下的部分
they say what's predicted to still be left
也足以给像南非开普敦这样的地方带来很大帮助
could do a lot for places like Cape Town in South Africa
兰德公司为国家科学基金会写了一份83页的报告 专门讨论把冰山作为全球淡水资源的话题
The Rand Corporation wrote an 83-page report for the National Science Foundation dedicated to the topic of using icebergs as a global freshwater resource
报告基本上就是说 这个想法理论上一直很酷 但实现它的技术还不存在
And it basically says that the idea has always been neat in theory, but the technology for it just doesn't exist yet
即使到现在 我也没找到任何成功实现这项技术的案例
Even up till now, I couldn't find anything on successful uses of that type of tech that could pull it off
有没有可能...？
Or have I?
空想性错视基本上就是你的大脑的一种习惯
Pareidolia is basically your brain's habit
它会让你在你看到、听到 或者说任何感知到的随机事物中 找出特定的模式或意义
of projecting patterns or meaning onto random things you see, hear, or perceive
比如 看到云的形状觉得像个动物 或者经典的烤焦吐司上的耶稣像
For example, seeing a cloud shape and thinking it looks like an animal, or the good old Jesus in the burnt toast
你的大脑基本上就是在告诉自己
Your brain essentially tells itself,
“嘿 这玩意儿看起来像另一个不是这玩意儿的玩意儿”
"hey, this thing looks like a different thing that isn't this thing"
人们经常拍那些长得像别的东西的冰山照片 而且还挺容易火的
And people take pictures of icebergs that look like other stuff a lot, and they go viral pretty often
15年前 有座冰山大家觉得长得像蝙蝠侠
There was this iceberg that people thought looked like Batman 15 years ago
还有一张超酷的素材图 是一座冰川侧面在流水 看起来像一张哭泣的脸
There's also this really cool stock photo of a glacier pouring water out its side that looks like a crying face
最后 这是一张贴吧网友一看到就立刻想跟它上床的冰山
And finally, here's one Reddit saw before immediately wanting to have sex with it
南极条约体系包括主要的《南极条约》 还有几个独立但相关的协议
The Antarctic Treaty System includes the main Antarctic Treaty as well as several separate but related agreements
用来规范各个国家在南极洲的活动
that regulate how countries are allowed to operate in Antarctica
它最早是在1959年签署的
It was first signed in 1959
当时像美国和苏联这样的主要国家都同意了 还有日本、英国、法国等国
with major players like both the US and the Soviet Union both agreeing, as well as Japan, the United Kingdom, France, and others
截至2023年 总共有56个成员国签署了这项条约
As of 2023, a total of 56 member nations have signed this treaty
它的基本想法就是让南极洲成为一个我们不会在上面打仗的地方
Its basic idea was to keep Antarctica as a place that we do not have wars on
这块大陆上禁止一切军事活动 这使其成为了冷战时期的第一个军备控制协议
Military activity was banned on the continent, making it the first arms control agreement of the Cold War
而且它的用途就是将南极专门保留给科学考察和研究
and it was meant to be used only as a preserve for scientific investigation and research,
一个可以为了创新而自由进行科学研究的地方
a place to freely practice science stuff for the sake of innovation
大家并不总是遵守规定 而且这个条约体系内容庞杂 但它好歹是存在的
Everybody didn't always follow through on that, and there is a lot to the treaty system, but it's still a pretty big deal
它涵盖了一些更具体的话题 比如各国在签约前提出的领土主张之类的
It covers several more specific topics like claims of land made by countries prior to signing and other stuff like that,
所以我们会在相关的地方再回头聊这个条约
so we'll circle back to the treaty where relevant
Fellas, watch your step and put your hammers down, because now it's Layer 2.
兄弟们，小心脚下、放下锤子，第二层来了
We're breaking the ice.
冰山迪哥不再低调
The International Ice Patrol is an organization founded in 1914
国际冰情巡逻队，成立于1914年
that has been tracking iceberg activity for over the last 100 years now.
截止到目前，已经追踪冰山活动一百多年了
This thing was born five months before Franz Ferdinand got shot.
比斐迪南大公挨枪子儿还早五个月
It was formed in January of that year at the first Safety of Life at Sea convention.
是在1914年，第一次《海上人命安全公约》会议上搞出来的
The patrol was first formed in direct response to the Titanic sinking,
主要就是为了应对泰坦尼克号这样的沉船事件
and they mainly monitored danger bergs in the North Atlantic.
主要负责盯着北大西洋那些有事故风险的冰山
Funding comes from a bunch of different countries like Canada, the United Kingdom, Japan,
经费是大家一起凑的，比如加拿大、英国、日本
and others who rely on iceberg movement data
还有一些需要冰山移动数据的国家
either because they're close by
他们要么是靠得太近
or have trade that relies on not running into them.
要么就是航运路线必须经过冰山区
Listen, do not fuck with shipping lanes.
记住，别几把碰航运航道
World powers let a lot slide.
大国对很多事情都是睁一只眼闭一只眼
Kill civilians, sell drugs to kids, whatever.
纱人、给小孩卖冰，随便
But do not mess with the money.
但是赚钱的行当，不行
That's the only thing these motherfuckers will work together on.
byd们唯一能齐心协力的事，就是护住钱路
The Ice Patrol is somehow a part of and run by the U.S. Coast Guard,
奇异搞笑的是，冰情巡逻队听令于「美国海岸警卫队」
and they operate out of U.S. federal buildings in Maryland.
办公地点设在马里兰的联邦大楼里
So it is international, but, like,
所以说，它是个国际组织，但问题是
whose ice patrol is it, really?
这到底算谁的巡逻队呢？
A lot of countries still have iceberg-monitoring operations of their own,
很多国家其实也有自己独立的冰山监控
separate from the IIP.
跟国际巡逻队（IIP）完全两码事
I.P.
爱屁
This includes the United States for some reason,
美国自己也奇怪
who, despite running the patrols day-to-day,
明明日常巡逻是他们在干
also have the U.S. National Ice Center,
结果美国搞了个「美国国家冰情中心」
which was formed in 1995.
这玩意儿1995年才成立
They make global sea ice charts as well as name icebergs
他们专门做全球海冰图，顺便给冰山起名字
that, at their biggest point, are over 10 nautical miles long.
最大长度超过10海里的冰山，都给编上号
I was gonna make a joke about how they're redundant
我本来想吐槽，说这俩机构重复了
and we literally got other governments to pay for something that we control,
等于我们忽悠别的政府出钱，结果项目还是我们说了算
but it sounds like the ice center does different stuff,
但冰情中心的业务还真不一样
so, actually, I'm the idiot.
所以是我傻比了
They post a lot of the information they collect publicly on their official .gov page,
他们在官网公开了很多数据
and there's some neat stuff there.
里面有不少好东西
So if you're into this shit as much as I've tricked myself into being,
所以如果你跟我一样，不知为何迪成了冰山迷
then there may be exciting cutting-edge information for you on there.
那里可能会有一些让你眼前一亮的前沿资讯
Outside the U.S., if you're a country with waters that have icebergs in them
在美国之外，如果你的国家海域里有冰山
or you rely on shipping routes with icebergs in them,
或者航线要经过冰山区
chances are you've got a local ice-watching enthusiast club.
十有八九也有自个儿的“冰山爱好者俱乐部”
There's the Canadian Ice Service, for one,
比如说「加拿大极冰署」
and it's made up of roughly 60 personnel.
大概有60号人吧
That is technically a big operation when you consider it's, like,
规模相当于，怎么说呢
two very full high school classrooms all working on the same thing,
相当于在两个高中教室里，坐满了研究冰的人
but they really sound like the iceberg equivalent of a bird-watching society.
但听起来就像冰山界的“观鸟协会”
They all know each other and hang out on weekends.
都老熟人了，周末出来耍
I just really want to know what their in-jokes are.
我很好奇，他们有什么内部梗
I'm trying to find people who like this stuff, too.
小哥小哥，有没有冰山同好呀
Operation Deep Freeze is the codename for multiple American missions to Antarctica.
「深冻行动」是美国多次南极考察任务的代号
It's a general label these days,
现在大家都这么叫了
but individual operations were first labeled as Operation Deep Freeze I,
但最初每次行动都有编号，比如「深冻行动1号」
then Deep Freeze II, and so on.
「深冻行动2号」...
Eventually, operations were named by the year they took place,
后来干脆用年份命名
and over time, Operation Deep Freeze became the general term for United States-ian activity in the South Pole.
久而久之，「深冻行动」就成了美国在南极活动的统称
Deep Freeze I started around when the Antarctic Treaty System first went into effect,
深冻一号在《南极条约》刚生效那会儿启动
and as part of the 1957-1958 International Geophysical Year.
也是57-58「国际地球物理年」活动的一部分
That was a joint scientific initiative
这是个联合科研行动
with many of the same member nations as the Antarctic Treaty,
参与国与《南极条约》的成员国大体相同
who all agreed to collaboratively conduct studies in both of the Earth's poles.
大家统一意见，南北两极都要科学研究，不逾矩
The IGY. marked the end of a period in the Cold War
“国地物年”标志着冷战期间
where scientific exchange between the East and West was majorly stunted.
东西方科学交流冰封期终于结束
It was big news.
是件大事
Beginning in 1955, backed by the U.S. Navy and Task Force 43,
活动从1955年开始，背靠美国海军和“第43特遣队”
which consisted of several U.S. icebreaker and freighter ships,
这个特遣队就是几艘美国破冰船和货船
Operation Deep Freeze I established a permanent base of operations in Antarctica.
深冻一号在南极建了永久基地，正式落地
Both the Navy and, interestingly, Disney Studios documented the expedition,
有趣的是，海军和迪士尼都记录了这次探险
which got Walt Disney listed as an honorary member.
所以迪士尼是本次活动的名誉成员
The leadership for the operation switched hands several times over the decades,
几十年来，行动指挥多次换手
being run by several different military and government subgroups,
由不同的军方和政府小组轮流管理
where today it's headed by the U.S. Antarctic Program and the U.S. National Science Foundation.
现在归「美国南极计划」，和「美国国家科学基金会」管理
The grotto in an iceberg is a photo that goes hard as shit,
冰山里的冰窟照片，这个牛逼
screenshot at your own risk.
不怕被震到 就截图
It was taken during the British Antarctic Terra Nova expedition on January 5th, 1911.
照片拍摄于1911年1月5日，英方南极“新地”探险队拍的
Herbert George Ponting snapped it,
摄影师是赫伯特·乔治·庞廷
and it depicts the scientists Griffith Taylor and Charles S. Wright
照片是科学家格里菲斯·泰勒和查尔斯·S·赖特
at the entrance of the ice,
站在冰川入口
with the Terra Nova, the ship used for the expedition, visible in the distance.
远处还能看到他们探险用的船——“新地号”
One of these dudes brought a fucking cane to the South Pole.
这哥们儿去南极探险居然带着拐杖
By all accounts, this guy is a scientist,
按说他就是个科学家
meaning a massive nerd,
超级书呆子
and he's out here looking cool even from a distance?
怎么他的照片就这么帅呢
How did nerds being lame and weak ever become the stereotype?
我就不明白，书呆子低质男的刻板印象是怎么流行的？
That guy definitely fucks and is probably decent at math on the side.
这个人绝对不缺异性缘，数学肯定也很牛逼
Bringing it full circle, the RMS Titanic iceberg
大的来了，泰坦尼克号撞的冰山
is the specific iceberg that struck the Titanic, causing it to sink.
让泰坦尼克沉下去的罪魁祸冰
The pictures I'm showing here are some of the only known photos ever taken of the iceberg
我展示的这些照片，是仅有的几张冰山照片之一
that people THINK suck the shit.
而且大家觉得这幅图帅炸了
One was taken by the chief steward of the SS Prinz Adalbert.
其中一张是「阿尔伯特王子号」总管拍摄的
On the night after the Titanic sank,
泰坦尼克号沉没的那个晚上
his ship sailed near the disaster site without even knowing that it had even happened.
他的船路过事发海域，却不知道悲剧已经发生了
M. Linoenwald, who I cannot say his name, that's what they said he was,
M.利诺恩瓦尔德拍下了这张照片，这名字咋这么难念
but he said he took the photo because he saw a red streak along this iceberg,
他拍这张照片的原因，是因为他看到冰山上有条红色条纹
which indicated there may have been a recent collision with the ship,
可能是因为这里最近发生过事故
but he didn't know what ship it would have been, much less the Titanic.
可他压根不知道是哪艘船，更别提泰坦尼克号了
On a different boat, Captain De Carteret took another photo,
另一艘船上，船长德卡特里特 拍了另一张照片
and also identified the iceberg by the streak of red paint on its side
可以看出，冰山上的红色条纹可能不是油漆画的
that made it look like something had, I don't know,
而是有什么东西...
hit it with a big boat or something.
可能是被一艘大船撞到了
Except all of that's baloney because we've got a real police lineup here.
但这些全是胡扯，因为我们这儿有一份真正的“列队认人”
There are other pictures of icebergs that allegedly sank the Titanic,
还有别的冰山照片，据称是造成泰坦尼克号沉没的冰山
and we're not certain which one is the real culprit.
不过谁是真正的凶手已经无法考证
The problem with the Prince Adalbert photo
阿尔伯特王子号拍下来的照片
is the crash was described as a lot more violent,
问题在于，泰坦尼克号撞击的痕迹要比照片上猛的多
tearing chunks of the iceberg away from it when it hit the Titanic.
干碎了一大块冰山
A streak of red paint probably isn't enough to go off here,
所以仅凭一道红色痕迹恐怕不足以当证据
as there would probably be a lot more cartage,
因为现场应该会留下更多“屠杀”的痕迹
and the red streak might not have even come from paint.
那道红痕甚至可能不是油漆
It doesn't help that several icebergs in the area were said to have red streaks on their sides as well,
更糟糕的是，据说当时附近好几座冰山侧面都有红色条纹
and unless the Bergs were playing ping-pong just running train on the Titanic,
除非这些冰山在那儿打乒乓球，轮番上去撞泰坦尼克号
there is no way they all got a piece of ass.
否则不可能都撞一遍吧
We do have first-hand accounts though,
不过我们倒是有一手资料
as some folks are built different than those drown-pilled losers and lived through the sinking.
因为有些乘客身体异于常人，比淹死掉的倒霉蛋们更硬核
Survivor Joseph Scarrett made this neat little drawing of what the iceberg looked like from his memory,
幸存者约瑟夫·斯卡雷特，凭记忆画了一张详尽的冰山素描
where he apparently described it as being in the shape of the Rock of Gibraltar,
他说冰山的样子跟直布罗陀巨岩差不多
with gleaming icy sides and a dark patch of earthy matter.
两边是闪闪发亮的冰面，中间夹着一块暗色的泥土状物质
There's also this dude Colin Campbell Cooper,
还有这个叫科林·坎贝尔·库珀的
who's like an actual famous artist with his own wiki page,
是真·知名艺术家，维基百科有他的条目
who just happened to be on the Titanic.
刚好在泰坦尼克号上
He was rescued by the Carpathia,
卡帕西亚号将他救了下来
which was the first ship on the scene of the Titanic that saved some 700 passengers.
那艘船是最早赶到现场的救援船，救下了大约七百名乘客
And while aboard, he documented the rescue operation while it was going on
上船之后，把他看到的救援过程记录了下来
by drawing what happened as it happened.
用画笔直播
He doodles the Titanic on his math homework, just like me.
他是在数学作业本上画的，我也喜欢
One of the things he drew right after the wreck was a sketch of the iceberg that caused it.
事件结束后，他画了一张图，也就是冰山之谜的万恶之源
His drawing had two distinct peaks like Joseph's did,
与约瑟夫的照片如出一辙，画出了两个明显的冰峰
but also had a chunk near the bottom torn off where the ice had rammed into the ship.
不过他还补了一笔，在底部画上了一大块缺口
I'm sure these dudes' memories weren't perfect.
虽然这些人的记忆不可能完全准确
They did almost die during the whole thing.
他们差点死过你死过吗
I can understand it being a little hazy.
记忆模糊点也情有可原
But luckily, some of the icebergs photographed
不过幸好，当时拍下来的几座冰山里
look a whole lot more like what these fellas said than others.
有几座确实比其他的更符合他们的描述
There's one picture in particular that best fits these descriptions by a mile.
其中有一张照片能跟他们的描述对得上号
About a week after the Titanic sank,
在泰坦尼克沉没大约一周后
the SS Bremen, the one launched in 1896,
1896开始启用的「不莱梅号邮船」出事儿了
not to be confused with one of the four other naval or six passenger ships also named the SS Bremen,
别搞混了，不是另外四艘同名军舰或者六艘同名客轮
occasionally at the same time.
它们还在同一时期服役
Sorry, I got sidetracked,
抱歉，跑题了
but this SS Bremen passed through the Titanic wreck site on April 20th, 1912,
总之，这艘不莱梅号在1912年4月20日路过了泰坦尼克残骸
which is the same day Hitler turned 33.
也就是希特勒33岁生日那天
Why didn't they warn us?
卧槽不早说
A passenger named Stephen, unpronounceable last name,
有个乘客叫斯蒂芬，他的姓我不会念
took this picture of an iceberg that matched several eyewitness descriptions
他拍下了一张冰山的照片，跟不少目击者的描述都对得上
and also the sketches made of the alleged ship sinker.
还符合那些“肇事冰山”素描的描述
It's not for sure this iceberg,
不能百分百确定就是它
but all things considered,
但综合各种因素来看
I'm gonna say it's probably that one.
大概率就是它了
Can't go back in time and the magic tree has to check,
我们又回不到过去，不是《神奇树屋》
but it was in the right place at the right time,
但是地点、时间都对的上
and it looks how people said it looked.
外观也符合
It's dead now anyway,
虽然但是现在已经化了
so the chance for true justice to prevail has passed.
所以无法查证
The SS Kronprinz Wilhelm is the real reason the Titanic sank.
「威廉皇太子号」，泰坦尼克号沉没的真凶
And I'm only half-joking.
一半认真
The Wilhelm was a pre-World War I German ship,
威廉皇太子号是一艘一战前的德国船
and pretty big-looking as it is.
相当大
Seven-year-old me would have thought the Wilhelm was the Titanic.
七岁的我肯定会以为这就是泰坦尼克号了
If it had enough smokestacks, then it was directed by James Cameron.
只要烟囱够多，那就是卡梅隆导演的大片片段
And it turns out I actually can't count.
事实证明，我不会数数
But hey, in 1907, the Wilhelm DID also ram into an iceberg.
话说回来，1907 年，威廉皇太子号确实撞过冰山
But instead of being a massive pussy,
但威廉皇太子号是一艘猛男船
the Kronprinz still finished its voyage and then remained in use after.
它走完了自己的航程，还服役了一段时间
It even ended up switching teams to become an American ship.
后来还被美国收编，成了美国船
That guy got out of Germany before they were Nazis.
走得还真及时，那时德国甚至没有纳粹
Why didn't they warn us?
卧槽又不早说？
As far as how it made the Titanic sink,
至于说它是怎么导致泰坦尼克号沉没的
the Kronprinz iceberg crash happened around the time the Titanic was being constructed.
泰坦尼克号的诞生，正好和威廉皇太子号撞冰山处在一个时期
And because crashes like the Wilhelms,
因为威廉皇太子号
where the ship still made it to shore after suckin' face with a block of ice,
跟冰山来了个亲密接触以后还能安全上岸
were not too rare,
这种事并不算罕见
the developers of the Titanic kinda thought they were hot shit and went,
泰坦尼克号的设计师们就有点自以为是
I could do that too.
“我也行”
And they treated icebergs as less of a concern than they ended up being.
他们没把冰山当回事儿，事实证明冰山不跟你闹
Ernest Shackleton was an Irish explorer
爱尔兰探险家 欧内斯特·沙克尔顿
who, in his lifetime, led three British expeditions to Antarctica.
他这一生主导了三次英国南极探险
The first was the Discovery Expedition from 1901 to 1903,
第一次是1901到1903年的“发现号远征”
and the second was the Nimrod Expedition in 1907 to 1909.
第二次是1907年到1909年的“猎人号远征”
But his most well-known adventure,
但其中最出名的一次
with a Capcom re-release length name,
名字长的像是卡普空各种冷饭的后缀
is the Imperial Transantarctic Expedition.
叫“帝国跨南极探险”
Kratos from God of War was a guest character on the research team,
战神奎托斯好像是研究队的客串成员
but only on PlayStation.
但是PS独占
Lasting from 1914 to 1917,
这次探险从1914年持续到1917年
it was Shackleton's first trip to Antarctica
这是沙克尔顿的第一次南极之行
to get funding from not just private investors, but also from the government.
且土豪和政府都资助了这次探险
It was about as long as his other expeditions,
这次探险的时间跟前几次差不多
but this one was way more insane
但这一次玩的非常大
because they lost both their damn ships
因为他妈的两艘船都报废了
and got stranded in Antarctica for years.
被困在南极好几年
I'm getting ahead of myself.
讲快了，慢慢说
The two ships used on the expedition
这次远征用的两艘船
were the Endurance, led by Shackleton, heading to the Weddell Sea,
沙克尔顿带领“坚忍号”，目标是威德尔海
and the Aurora, led by Aeneas Mackintosh,
艾尼亚斯·麦金塔什带领“极光号”
en route to McMurdo Sound on the other side of Antarctica.
目标是南极另一侧的麦克默多湾
You see, this particular outing was also an attempt
是这样，这次探险还有个目标
to be the first guys to cross all of Antarctica on land.
就是成为史上首批横穿整个南极大陆的人
It did not work.
但是失败了
Ernest was apparently picking his crew
显然，沙克尔顿选船员的标准
based mainly on vibes instead of technical expertise or merit.
是看他们潮不潮，而不是技术能力或资历
He was asking people things like if they could sing,
他会问他们一些奇怪的问题，比如你会不会唱歌
and if he liked the person the second he saw them, he apparently gave some of them a job.
看顺眼了就发给他一个职位
Shackleton also maintained a less strict hierarchy on his ship.
沙克尔顿船上的等级也没那么森严
He chose to give chores to all crew members,
他把各种杂活平均分给所有船员
be them scientists, seamen, or officers more equally.
不管你是科学家、水手、军官，都一视同仁
*seamen是水手，semen是精子
He had a heavy emphasis on camaraderie,
他特别强调团队友谊
just socializing with his crew himself after dinners,
晚饭以后跟大家social一下
cracking jokes, and participating in games and sing-alongs.
开开玩笑，玩玩游戏，一起唱歌
The recruitment ended up totaling in a 56-person crew,
最终招了56名船员
with each ship getting 28 crewmen apiece,
每艘船28人
and within the first year of the voyage,
而在航程第一年里
the Endurance got caught in an ice floe
海上的浮冰将坚忍号团团围住
where it was frozen in place.
寸步难行
After a month of waiting and the ship not wiggling loose enough to leave,
经过一个月的等待，还是无法挣脱困境
Shackleton abandoned their usual routine
沙克尔顿放弃了常规安排
in favor of refitting the Endurance into a suitable winter station.
把坚忍号改装成可以过冬的临时基地
But over the next few months,
不过接下来的几个月里
the ship drifted north through the ice.
船随着浮冰一路向北
In November 1915, it finally became too much,
1915年11月，这回真没招了
and the ship went to bed forever, sinking.
坚忍号彻底报销，沉入海底
So for the next two months,
接下来的两个月
Shackleton and the fellas were left camping on drift ice,
沙克尔顿和伙伴们只能在浮冰上露营
hoping it would float all the way to Pollitt Island,
希望冰块能漂到保莱特岛
where they knew there would at least be supplies.
至少那里会有补给
Fingers crossed, knock on wood, guys.
双手合十，祈祷老天保佑吧
They would've just legged it there,
本来他们可以直接走过去
but walking wasn't possible on the ice,
但是浮冰之上无法走动
so Shackleton set up the Patience Camp,
于是沙克尔顿建了个“耐心营”
and he was manifesting all his built-up karma,
他简直把自己所有好运气都调动出来
hoping they got to the island via floating ice.
希望浮冰能把他们带到岛上
Oh, I almost forgot to mention,
哦，忘了说
during all of that, the Aurora pieced out and drifted into the sea as well.
极光号在这期间脱队，自己漂走了
Also, three of the crew, including the captain, died.
包括船长在内的三名船员也寄了
That sucks, but it's good for me,
太惨了，不过对我来说倒是好事
because I could not say that captain's name right
这样就不用念船长的名字了
even worse than usual.
现在更记不住了
Shackleton's guys, though, could just not stop getting fucked on a cosmic level.
沙克尔顿那批人好像受到了老天的诅咒
The ice flow they were living on split and was no longer safe to stay on,
浮冰裂开了，不能继续在上面生存
so they all had to cram into their leftover lifeboats
全员只好挤进剩下的救生艇里
and sail to wherever the hell nearest land was,
航向最近的陆地
die trying, or stay put and die for short.
要么死于冒险，要么死于躺平
After five straight days on the water,
在海上漂了五天五夜
the survivors ended up on Elephant Island,
幸存者终于登陆了海象岛
almost 350 miles from where the ship sank,
距离沉船地点将近350英里
and it fuckin' sucked there.
这地方烂的一比
They were so out of the way of any ships that might be looking for them
他们离过来搜救的船非常远
that they had to risk sailing on open ocean
以至于不得不冒着在公海上漂流的风险
in their rinky-dink wooden jokeboats to find help.
坐着破烂小木船去求救
They were aiming to reach the South Georgia whaling stations
他们的目标是南乔治亚捕鲸站
just a short 820-mile trip away.
也就是820英里“而已”
Shackleton was part of the crew that went out to sail,
沙克尔顿也亲自上阵
and he didn't pack for more than four weeks at sea,
他只带了四周的干粮
because he knew if it took any longer,
因为他知道，要是四周还没得救
he'd already be dead.
说明他已经死了
So Ernest and a few of his boys were sailing for 15 days,
于是沙克尔顿和船员就这么航行了15天
almost capsized all the time,
一直在翻船
and got caught in frequent storms.
频繁遇上风暴
Their luck was so bad
运气差到爆炸
that they managed to get in the middle of an actual hurricane
他们居然直接进入了一个飓风中心
that they later found out had managed to sink a much bigger, much safer boat
后来才知道，这场飓风让更大、更结实的船都沉进了海里
than the plywood they were stewing in.
显得他们的胶合板小船脆弱不堪
Despite it all, they still somehow made it.
尽管如此，他们还是奇迹般的活了下来
I am not kidding.
这是真的
They were the first people to ever sail that route as well.
他们也是史上首批走这条航线的人
It was under duress, do or die for sure,
也算是拼了老命了
but these fellas sure do do.
兄弟们确实不赖
After finding help, Rescue took multiple attempts
找到救援后，营救过程也非常曲折
because of sea ice, trolling a little, and getting in the way.
因为海冰这捣蛋鬼挡住了他们，还有各种小意外
But eventually, the remaining 22 men on Elephant Island were all saved,
最终，海象岛上剩下的22名船员全部得救
the Aurora crew that was still left stranded was saved,
以及留在那儿的极光号船员
and the Aurora itself was found after drifting an open ocean for months
几个月后，救援队找到了漂流的极光号
and finally recovered.
打捞上岸
It kinda all worked out in the end,
算得上皆大欢喜
if you ignore all the ways that it didn't.
去掉一路上吃的苦
It wasn't a success as an expedition,
从探险的角度看，这算不上成功
but if you were making an argument for being one of the hardest motherfuckers of all time,
但如果要评谁是史上最硬核的人
this is a pretty good one.
这次探险绝对够格
Captain Sir John Franklin's last expedition—
约翰·富兰克林爵士的最后一次探险
and I'm gonna read this word-for-word because it's funny out of context—
我要逐字念出来，因为脱离上下文听起来很搞笑
was a failed British voyage.
“是一场失败的英国远征”
And yeah, it sounds like the Brits got a lot of those.
英国人翻车的次数有点多了
It was led by John Franklin—surprise—
由约翰·富兰克林带队，惊不惊喜
with two ships, the Erebus and the Terror.
带了两艘船，幽冥号和恐怖号
The goal was to gather magnetic data
目标是收集磁力数据
to see if having that type of information could aid in navigation.
看看这些信息能否帮助航行
Instead, both ships got locked in the ice
结果，两艘船都被冰封了
and a total of 129 people got stuck in the Victoria Strait near King William Island,
总共有129人被困在威廉王岛旁边的维多利亚海峡
which today is Canadian Nunavut.
现属于加拿大努纳武特
After a year of being isolated out there
面临着冰面融化的风险
and being edged by melting ice,
他们在那儿待了一年
both ships were abandoned in April 1848.
1848年4月，探险队放弃了这两艘船
By then, around 24 people, including Captain John Franklin,
包括富兰克林船长在内，约24人
had danced their last Fortnite emote and died.
跳完最后一个堡垒之夜舞蹈就安心去死了
Several rescue attempts were made and some people's remains were found,
后来进行了几次营救，还找到了部分遗骸
but tragically, none of the expedition crew were found alive.
遗憾的是，没有找到任何活着的探险船员
It wasn't a triumphant success against the odds like Ernest Shackleton's was.
跟前面沙克尔顿逆天改命不一样，这次输的特别干脆
Still, despite screwing the pooch— and ultimately failing—
即便如此，虽然这次探险彻底翻车
the expedition did manage to explore
但他们的探险是有成果的
and be the first to sail through a series of unknown Northwest passages that went on to be rediscovered later.
但他们确实摸出了一些没人走过的西北航道
There's also been recent developments to the story,
而且这部老番在最近还更新了
where the wrecks of both ships, the Erebus and the Terror,
2014年和2016年
were found in 2014 and 2016 respectively.
分别找到了幽冥号和恐怖号的残骸
They've both been named as Canadian National Historic Sites
两艘船都被列为加拿大国家历史遗址
and sit near King William Island today.
现在就静静地躺在威廉王岛附近
Ice piers, or ice wharfs,
冰墩，也叫冰码头
are structures built to help unload ships in Antarctica,
是用冰建成的码头，用来在南极给船卸货
primarily at McMurdo Station.
主要在麦克默多站用
Actually, only McMurdo Station, from what I've read.
其实也就麦克默多站用了
I thought there'd be more.
我还以为有更多
To make one, you basically hose seawater into a controlled area
建一个冰墩，其实就是把海水往一个指定区域猛喷
and just let it freeze,
等它结冰
which it will always do because it's always cold.
反正南极够冷 肯定会结冰
When you repeated that a few times and as the layers built up,
重复几次、叠加成层后
it got to be several meters thick and strong enough to support shipping crates and supply trucks
冰墩就能厚到几米，足以承受货箱和补给卡车的重量
that can move shit around more efficiently than dudes dragging crates behind them.
比人力搬货快多了，工人 淘汰...
The first one ever constructed was also a part of Operation Deep Freeze in 1973,
第一个冰墩建于1973年的“深冻行动”
where folks in that job built the first ice pier at McMurdo Station.
由麦克默多站的工作人员完成
This freeze-iced-and-freeze-more-on-top-lol method
这种“先冻一层，再冻一层”的叠叠乐
sounds like something I would do for fun in third grade if I had the means.
听着就像我三年级有钱有空也会干的实验
And because of that, I'm not surprised that shit went sideways with them more than once.
所以我一点都不惊讶，冰墩会折腾多次出幺蛾子
Wind, as well as forces like sea swells,
风、海浪之类的力量
can fuck an ice pier till its tummy's bulging.
能把冰墩的肚子耍成曲面
In 1993, those exact things became an issue.
1993年，大的来了
Not the tummy bulge.
不是说肚子大了
And they caused some scary, probably-do-not-ignore cracks in the ice pier.
冰墩出现了几条吓人的裂缝，这真得特别关注了
The one with the funniest picture associated with it was in 1983,
最搞笑的一次是1983年
when an ice pier was pushed to its limits
冰墩已经没法用了
because people were unloading way more than normal for that season.
因为那季卸的货比平常多太多
And the ice broke under the pressure, making a cargo truck fall through it.
结果冰裂开了，掉进去一辆货车
Kind of fucking everyone's day up.
真是煞风景
Oil companies and ice is a broad topic.
说到石油公司和冰，能聊的很多
Oil execs like drilling icy areas all the time.
高管们喜欢去冰天雪地里钻油井
But burning fossil fuels contributes to ice melt, which is not so good for us.
但燃烧化石燃料会加速冰面融化，对人类不利
So some folks want oil to be used less.
所以有人希望减少石油的使用
But that means oil execs would make less money, so they aren't happy to let that happen.
但这意味着高管们会赚少点钱，他们当然不乐意
For me, though, the first thing that comes to mind
我一开始想到的是
is an ad that Humble Oil, a company owned today by Exxon,
汉伯尔石油公司，现在是埃克森美孚的子公司
aired in 1962.
1962的一则广告
In it, they were dick-measuring their oil output
广告里，他们在比谁的产♂量更大
based on how much glacier they could melt with the energy their oil had produced.
用自己的石油能融化多少冰川来秀肌肉
I'm not gonna read the text straight to you a whole lot in this video,
我不会一字不漏念出来
but you gotta hear the shit as it was written.
但是广告词很狂
Each day, Humble supplies enough energy to melt 7 million tons of glacier.
“汉伯尔的石油能量，足以每天融化七百万吨冰川！
This giant glacier has remained unmelted for centuries,
这座巨型冰川几个世纪以来都没有融化
yet the petroleum energy Humble supplies,
但汉伯尔的石油能量换成热量的话
if converted into heat, could melt it at a rate of 80 tons a second.
每秒就能融掉80吨
To meet the nation's growing needs for energy,
为了满足国家不断增长的能源需求
Humble has applied science to nature's resources
汉伯尔利用科学和自然资源
to become America's leading energy company.
一跃成为美国头号能源公司”
Now, this wasn't a straight-up, we-are-going-to-melt-the-poles-suck-it losers
当然，他们不是直白地说“俺要把极地融化”
and climate change wasn't talked about in public back then like it is today,
当时大众对气候变化的认知没有现在这么高
but it sure has aged.
以现在的眼光看有点神
Exxon also hired internal scientists, as in literally working for Exxon,
埃克森还养了内部科学家，只给他们工作
that ran tests predicting global warming pretty damn accurately,
他们做的测试对全球变暖预测得相当准
decades ahead of the danger becoming well-publicized knowledge.
几十年以前就发现了全球变暖的危害
And then they spent those decades ignoring the research they paid for on purpose,
然后呢，他们故意忽视自己花钱做的研究
because acting on it meant they'd have to pump less oil and make less money in the short term.
因为如果真去管这事儿，短期内就得少开几口油井，少赚钱
I'm sure it was for good, injustifiable reasons.
他们肯定有“有理有据”的理由来掩饰
Darren Woods, I know you're just the CEO of Exxon and not the shareholders,
伍德伦，我知道你只是美孚的CEO，不是股东
*1999年埃克森和美孚合并，才有了埃克森美孚，严谨
but you're the easiest public face I could find.
但你是最好找的形象
I just want to assure you that you should feel absolutely safe in your home, away from people.
你放心，待在家里非常安全，没有人会拿你怎么样
*截止到2021年，伍德伦的年薪超过2000万美元
No one is meant to be able to get you there,
没有人知道你住哪儿
and you've got nothing to worry about, pal.
千万不要担心啊
This entry could go on a lot longer, but it's pretty straightforward.
这段还能讲很多东西，但意思很简单
Oil companies know the consequences of their actions and they don't give a shit,
石油公司知道自己干的事会导致全球变暖，但他们不在乎
which, like, no shit.
吊都不吊
Drifting ice stations were temporary facilities built on Ice floes during the Cold War.
「浮冰站」是冷战期间建在浮冰上的临时设施
Ice floes were not always stable,
因为浮冰并不稳定
so there was a good chance the ground you built that doohickey on would crack open sooner
所以在上面建的东西随时都有可能散架
instead of whenever later is.
而不是到未来的某一天才出问题
But both the Soviets and the United States
苏联和美国
established and maintained several stations in the Arctic Ocean for both research and espionage purposes.
在北冰洋建了好几个站，用来做科研和间谍活动
Though they probably wouldn't have told you about the latter when they were still in the middle of it.
当然，这些国家不会承认间谍这一块
The stations themselves were usually not that impressive as buildings.
一般来说，浮冰站都很简陋
Like, if a station was just for spying,
如果只是间谍任务的话
they were usually just putting up shacks and spots of interest.
就随便搭几个小棚子，标个重点区域就完事
While this might sound like some shit that could only be thought of
听起来像是冷战时期的专属活动
in the Cold War era of poison cigar assassinations,
就“毒雪茄暗杀事件”这样的
↓卡斯特罗
the idea for a station set up on drift ice actually came in the late 1800s,
但在19世纪末，就有人想出在浮冰上建考察站的点子
where one hell of an interesting brain was already doing this type of stuff.
而且这个人脑洞非常大，都实践上了
A dude named Fridtjof Nansen came up with the original drift station concept,
此人名叫弗里乔夫·南森，提出了最早的浮冰站
and he was operating his own outpost from 1893 till 1896.
他从1893到1896年自己造了一个哨所
Fun fact, he also has a Nobel Peace Prize. Good for him.
小知识，他是诺贝尔和平奖得主，恭喜恭喜
The Soviets established North Pole 1 in May 1937
苏联在1937年5月建了北极一号
and definitely had a head start by the time the Americans were building their own.
比美国自己的考察站早大截
The last drifting ice station the USSR built was shuttered in 1991.
苏联建的最后一座浮冰站在1991年关停
Post-Soviet Union, Russian activities in the Arctic have really scaled back.
苏联解体后，俄罗斯在北极的活动大幅缩减
They didn't do much at all in the North Pole for over a decade until eventually re-entering in 2003.
有十多年都没怎么去北极，直到2003年
But guess what?
您猜怎么着？
Global warming since the mid-2000s
自00年代中期起，全球变暖
has made ice floes that you can actually camp on really rare,
导致能够用来搭建考察站的浮冰少之又少
and some stations have had to evacuate way ahead of schedule because of thawing ice.
有些站甚至因为浮冰融化提前撤离
Subglacial lakes are lakes found under glaciers.
冰下湖，就是位于冰川下的湖泊
You're welcome. What would you do without me?
告诉你点小众潮酷知识，不用谢
First discovered under Antarctica, there are over 400 subglacial lakes around the world,
冰下湖是在南极考察出来的，全球有超过400个冰下湖
but almost all 400 of them have been found in Antarctica,
但几乎全部在南极
and I imagine they look something like Crystal Cavern from PMD Explorers.
应该和《宝可梦不可思议迷宫》里的结晶洞窟类似
They're notable because all this water that we can't see
地下湖很重要，因为这些肉眼看不到的水
is roughly 15% of the liquid freshwater on Earth.
大约占地球液态淡水的15%
And what's really interesting is that in these isolated underground lakes that have never seen the light of day,
最有趣的是，这些从未见过阳光的封闭地下湖里
there is previously undiscovered life living in them.
居然藏着未知生物
It's exciting because these places have been super isolated with uniquely cold and harsh conditions,
牛娃，这些地方长期封闭，环境极端寒冷恶劣
so the way evolution developed in those lakes
地下湖的进化路径，能让我们猜测
could give us an idea of how life might form in similar conditions on other planets and shit.
在类似条件下，其他星球可能会出现什么样的生命
We'll get into this life under the ice topic deeper in the chart,
后面会细说冰层底下的生物
but it's even more exciting to me considering subglacial lakes have already been found on Mars.
但更爽的是，火星上也发现了冰下湖
Maybe there are some plankton-sized friends waiting for us there.
万一冰下的世界有痞老板呢
The Ross Ice Shelf is the largest ice shelf in Antarctica.
罗斯冰架是南极最大的冰架
It was discovered in 1841 by Sir James Clark Ross,
是詹姆斯·克拉克·罗斯爵士于1840年发现的
who it was later named after,
就用他的名字命名了
and for decades in early Antarctic exploration
在南极探险的早期阶段
was considered an almost mythical, untraversable obstacle.
探险家们认为罗斯冰架是一个无法跨越的传说
It was originally just called the Barrier
一开始这东西叫“障”
because it stopped Ross's expedition in its tracks
因为它挡住罗斯的探险队了
with any number of extra adjectives like the Great Ice Barrier added
后来人们给它加上了不少形容词，比如叫“大冰障”
because it stopped explorers from being able to sail any further south beyond it.
就因为它挡住了探险家继续往南
But Ernest Shackleton, our favorite little guy,
但我们最喜欢的沙克尔顿
and a team of his were the first people to ever cross the ice shelf in 1908
和他的团队在1908年首次成功穿越了罗斯冰架
on the Nimrod Expedition while trying to reach the South Pole,
也就是尼姆罗德探险期间，他们要抵达南极点
years before the trip that got them stranded there.
比前面提到的“帝国跨南极探险”早好几年
Quite fittingly, after the Great Ice Barrier was finally conquered,
有意思的是，“大冰障”开源以后
it went on to become a sort of staging ground for later explorers.
反倒成了后来探险家们的一个天然大本营
As it was big as hell and flat on top.
属于是开了超平坦模式
It's almost poetic that what once stopped us dead in our tracks is our new starting point,
把我们挡在原地的冰架，竟成了新的起跑线，真是诗情画意
and the first man it stopped is now memorialized in its name.
而第一个被它拦住的人，成了冰架的名字
The Thwaites Glacier, nicknamed the Doomsday Glacier,
思韦茨冰川，也叫“末日冰川”
is similar to the Doomsday Clock
有点像末日时钟的概念
in that when time's up, when it's all gone,
时钟一响，万物归尘
it means that it's too late and we're probably all dead by then.
那时候我们差不多都完蛋了，就太晚了
So, uh, maybe let's get ahead of that one.
呃，还是在末日降临之前想办法吧
Thwaites is an abnormally big glacier in Antarctica that is monitored closely
思韦茨冰川是南极里一个特别大的冰川，重点关注对象
because it could potentially send the sea levels up to your ankles during the dry season
因为它可能在枯水季，就让海平面涨到脚踝这么高
and is relatively vulnerable to disappearing.
而且消失的可能性极大
It's concerning enough that people more powerful than me
严重到上面的大人物
made a group of people smarter than me hang out for five years in 2018.
在2018年就安排了一群比我聪明的人，忙活五年
Their job was to develop plans for possible futures involving the glacier.
他们的任务是为思韦茨冰川的未来做各种规划
Or, to put it more dramatically, they were doomsday planning.
说的更惊悚一些，他们在做末日演习
Those guys put together an estimated timeline for potential collapse
这些人整理出了冰川崩塌的时间表
and found that ocean water was eroding the glacier quicker than they originally thought,
发现海水侵蚀冰川的速度，比他们最初预想的要快得多
and that the water itself was already two degrees above its freezing point.
而且水温已经比冰点高出两度
Not great.
不妙啊
This one glacier alone contributes 4% of global sea level rise
光这一个冰川就贡献了全球海平面上升的4%
and its full collapse would raise sea levels by over two feet.
它的崩塌，会导致海平面上涨两英尺以上
At this point, the only chance to preserve Thwaites, according to simulations,
根据模拟，现在保住思韦茨冰川的唯一机会
is if we achieve the lowest level of warming possible.
就是把全球变暖控制在最低水平
If we don't, the glacier will eventually collapse within the next 200 to 1,000 years,
如果没有采取措施，思韦茨冰川会在200到1000年内崩塌
probably making a mess of things for us along the way.
给人类造成大麻烦
The Halloween crack,
万圣节裂缝
as recently as 2022, is a big-ass iceberg just waiting to happen.
截至2022年，这个裂缝很有可能会造出一座巨型冰山
It's been on the cusp of breaking off its ice shell for ages
它已经悬在那儿很久了，随时可能从母体冰层脱落
and has been hanging on by a thread for that long as well,
而且一直是摇摇欲坠
only hooked on to Antarctica by one-third of a mile of ice.
和南极大陆之间只剩下三分之一英里的冰桥
It was named the Halloween crack because it was first discovered on October 31st, 2016,
因为是在2016年万圣节找到的，故得名“万圣节裂缝”
which is kinda cute,
可爱捏
and it's located in a zone called the McDonald Ice Rumples for some reason.
而且它奇怪地坐落在一个叫“麦当劳冰褶”的地方
Historic explorers had fun when naming shit down south,
早期南极探险家起名字也太会整活了
so I'm glad to see the tradition's been kept alive and iceberg-loving circles up today.
看到今天的冰山爱好者延续了这种精神，我很开心
But when Halloween finally cracks and moves out of its parent house,
但“万圣节裂缝”断开，离开母体冰层时
it's expected to be about 675 square miles,
预计面积大约675平方英里
around half the size of Rhode Island and five times the size of Malta.
差不多是罗德岛的一半，马耳他的五倍大
The likelihood of icebergs like this forming is only going up,
而且这样的冰川只会越来越多
and the warmer it gets from cows farting straight methane,
牛放屁释放的甲烷让气温升高
the more likely an iceberg this size will show up.
也导致了巨型冰山越来越多
An ice shove, also known as, and apologies for the long list,
冰壅，接下来我要念他的n个别称 忍一下
an ice surge, ice push, ice heave, shoreline ice pile-up,
冰潮、冰堆、冰抬、沿岸冰堆
ice piling, ice thrust, ice tsunami, or ice ride-up,
冰堆积、冰冲、冰啸、冰抬升
is a big surge of ice from either large lakes or an ocean onto the shoreline
这是一种自然现象，指大量的冰从湖泊或海洋涌上岸边
and can be caused by temperature changes, ocean currents,
其成因包括温度变化、洋流
or strong, shad-like winds pushing ice onto shore.
或者被一些捉摸不透的怪风吹到岸上
These ice piles can get up to 40 feet high
这些冰堆最高可达40英尺
and are devastating to Arctic communities like in Alaska along its coastline
对阿拉斯加沿岸的北极社区，以及楚科奇海
and in the Chukchi Sea, the body of water that makes up most of the space between Russia and Alaska.
俄罗斯和阿拉斯加之间的一大片海域，造成了毁灭性影响
The creation and amount of ice shoves caused is affected by climate change,
冰壅的形成和数量，受气候变化的影响
and like pretty much every other ice-based natural disaster on this chart,
就像这个图表上几乎所有其他冰灾害一样
rising temperatures are setting the stage for even more of these to happen in the future.
气候变暖让未来出现更多类似的灾害成为了可能
Shelf ice is, first and foremost, not an ice shelf.
陆架冰，不要把它和冰架搞混
It occurs mostly in the Great Lakes,
主要出现在五大湖地区
and it's like if they tried to make a Las Vegas Eiffel Tower type of copy of real icebergs.
有点像是在拉斯维加斯建一个微缩冰山
Shelf ice forms when part of a lake freezes over and it later washes up onto shore.
陆架冰是在湖面部分结冰后漂到岸边形成的
The ice usually doesn't stay flat on top of the lake, though.
不过，这些冰通常不会在湖面上保持平整
Currents in the water and wind push these things around like a 6th grade bully,
因为水流和风会像恶霸鲁尼一样，把冰块干的东倒西歪
causing them to stack up in unappealing mounds of ice.
导致它们堆成一堆堆奇丑的冰堆
They've been, if I'm in a position to judge, rudely described as
我就这么说，用一个粗俗一点的形容
if you took a pile of rubble and pushed up against a wall.
就是“把一堆碎石堆起来顶在墙边的样子”
I guess we're running with that schoolyard bully metaphor.
还是很校霸
They're dangerous to walk on because of how textured its surface is,
陆架冰表面凹凸不平，走在上面非常危险
and there are potentially air pockets lurking under that shelf ice,
而且冰下面可能藏着气穴
so you can plummet a few feet through one into the water if the shelf ice breaks.
一旦陆架冰破裂，你就可能直接掉进几英尺高的水坑里
We all know by now that icebergs go very far down.
众所周知，冰山一定要深
That's, like, why we talk about them.
不然做冰山图干嘛
But they can go so deep that they straight-up cut out marks on the ocean floor.
但是冰山潜得够深时，甚至会在海底留下明显的划痕
This is called seabed gouging by ice.
这种现象叫做「冰凿海床」
Icebergs can scrape these long marks on the ocean floor if the water it's floating in is shallow enough.
如果浮冰所在的水域足够浅，冰山就能在海底刮出长长的痕迹
Most gouging doesn't really go deeper than a meter or three feet, if you're correct,
大多数刮痕不会超过1米/3英尺左右，如果你没记错的话
but in northern Canada, they can get as deep as 16 feet into the seabed.
但在加拿大北部，这种刮痕可以深达16英尺
Charles Darwin was apparently the first person to think of this idea being a possibility,
据说达尔文是第一个提出这种可能性的人
but it didn't get properly investigated until the 1970s.
但直到上世纪70年代，才得到正式研究
Since you can't tell jack shit from the surface,
因为你在海面上看不出什么端倪
you have to use sonar and other similar technology in order to research these things.
所以研究这些东西必须借助声呐之类的技术
Iceberg commercial products is an entry made up of a few things I've chosen to group together.
我把几类相关的事物归纳在一起，称之为「冰山商品」
But generally, I mean it as using icebergs as part of a product's branding,
一般来说，我指的是把冰山作为产品品牌的一部分
its production as a part of a gimmick,
在生产过程中利用冰山作为卖点
or places where icebergs are genuinely part of what's being sold,
或者，是把冰山本身作为商品的一部分销售
as well as a few other types of commerce.
当然，也包括其他几类商业行为
In places like Newfoundland and Labrador
在纽芬兰与拉布拉多
and Ololosaut where iceberg tourism is big,
以及奥洛洛索特这些冰山旅游盛行的地方
some businesses in the area offer you drinks
有些商家会提供饮料
where the ice cubes and water come from a millennium's old iceberg.
里面的冰块和水来自千年冰山
I got to try some while I was here.
我喝了几次
It's pretty good.
味道还不错
In an Atlantic article,
《大西洋月刊》一篇文章中
the author Matthew Barkhold went to Newfoundland and Labrador
作者马修·巴克霍尔德去了纽芬兰和拉布拉多
and gave some examples of the stuff he saw.
写下了一些见闻
The Quidi Vidi Brewery in St. John's
圣约翰的Quidi Vidi啤酒厂
uses 20,000-year-old iceberg water for its iceberg,
用两万年前的冰山水酿造了一款叫“冰山”的啤酒
a light lager that comes in a striking cobalt bottle.
这是一款浅色拉格啤酒，用夺目的钴蓝色瓶子装
Auk Island Winery blends iceberg water with wild berries to make specialty wines,
Auk Island酒庄把冰山水和野生浆果混合，酿制特色葡萄酒
*现在叫Great Auk Winery
and the Canadian Iceberg Vodka Corporation
加拿大“冰山伏特加公司”生产的
makes exactly what its name advertises.
就是名副其实的冰山伏特加
He was also told that his martini was the efforts of a cook
服务员告诉作者，他的马提尼酒是厨师的杰作
who plucked a piece of ice from the Labrador Sea while out on his jet ski,
他骑着水上摩托在拉布拉多海取了一块冰
and I think that guy is full of shit.
我觉得服务员在吹牛逼
This article is full of really fun examples of iceberg consumerism at all levels,
这篇文章里写了很多好玩的冰山消费主义例子
sometimes not even for profit.
有些例子甚至不是为了赚钱
Like, this random dude in the fishing town of Brigus
比如说，布里格斯的渔村里有个普通人
apparently keeps a growler in his freezer in his garage,
据说他把一个大冰块放在车库的冰箱里
so he can chip off ice cubes from it whenever he needs some for barbecues.
方便烤肉时随时取用，直接敲一块下来
The commercial aspect of icebergs is a rabbit hole all on its own,
用冰山搞钱的商业行为本身就是一个兔子洞
a lot of stuff in this video is,
本期视频里会涉及很多
and we'll be looking at some more specific examples later in the chart,
冰山图下面会有不少更具体的例子
but I'm gonna keep it moving for now.
不过我先继续讲
The North Pole landmass does not exist,
北极并不存在陆地块
in that the North Pole is not actually a chunk of land,
因为北极并非真正的大陆
it's literally all ice that is just floating on top of the ocean,
是纯纯漂在海上的冰
and is also called the Arctic Ice Pack.
也称作「北极冰盖」
I always wondered as a kid why there were only seven continents
小时候我总是很好奇，为什么世界上只有七大洲
when the North Pole was right there and somehow not one of them.
地图上白白嫩嫩的北极凭啥不算
It got talked about way more than the South Pole as well.
而且北极的讨论度远高于南极
Like, the amount of misinformation you heard about what Santa was getting up to was insane.
你听到关于圣诞老人活动的各种误传，全是扯淡的
It made it seem like the U.S. would view the North Pole as a threat to U.S. hegemony in the area.
搞得好像北极是美国在这片地区霸权的威胁一样
Actually, that's probably why they track where he goes.
呃，美国好像还真的因为这个原因追踪圣诞老人了
But it turns out that Antarctica is considered a continent
但事实是，南极是一个真正的大陆
because there's actually a landmass attached to the Earth's crust under all that ice.
因为在厚厚的冰层下，确实有一块附着在地壳上的陆地
From what I know, the North Pole is like the Pluto of continents,
据我所知，北极就像大陆界的冥王星一样
except it never even got to pretend it was a real boy.
只是它连参加派对的资格都没有
The Arctic is mostly just a sea,
北极主要是海洋
and land surrounds those bodies of water as opposed to the other way around.
陆地包围着这些水域，而不是水域包围陆地
That's why no permanent stations have been built on the North Pole  like they have in Antarctica,
这就是为什么，北极没有像南极那样建立永久科研站
and why stations with a built-in expiration date were used instead.
所以北极用的是带有“使用期限”的临时科研站
Operation IceBridge is a still-active NASA mission
「冰桥行动」是NASA仍在运行中的任务
to keep an eye on and document polar ice change.
用于监测和记录极地冰层变化
NASA used to have a satellite in the 2000s for looking at polar ice,
00年代，NASA曾发射过一颗用来观察极地冰层的卫星
but in 2008, due to a technical malfunction, it got shelved,
但2008年，由于技术故障，这颗卫星去玩太空生存了
and a next-gen satellite wasn't ready to launch until September 2018.
下一代卫星直到2018年9月才准备好发射
That was also the first month in America you might have ever known what TikTok was.
那个月还发生了一件事，洋抖入驻美国
Time Flies.
时光飞逝
Operation IceBridge was the stopgap used in between the two satellites,
冰桥行动充当了两颗卫星之间的过渡方案
where, while NASA spent the next ten years or so building a new space eye,
在NASA花十年左右建造新的“太空之眼”期间
they'd launch regular flights over both the Arctic and Antarctic
他们定期派飞机飞越北极和南极
to bridge the gap, so to speak, between satellite missions.
弥合卫星任务之间的空档
Hence its name.
这就是“冰桥”
During these flyovers, some neat stuff has been discovered,
这些飞机发现了一些有趣的东西
like these Coomer Brain holes in the ice that were all real close to each other.
比如冰层上这些紧挨在一起的不可言状之洞
Operation IceBridge has been keeping overwatch on places of interest,
冰桥行动一直在监测重要区域
like the Pine Island Glacier, where there's an ice tongue that, if it were to melt,
比如松岛冰川，那里的冰舌一旦融化
would let a big chunk of that glacier drop right into the sea.
就会有一大块冰川直接坠入海中
Using information gathered on flyovers,
利用飞行观测收集的数据
they've even discovered the longest canyon on Earth under Greenland's ice sheet.
NASA甚至发现了格陵兰冰盖下地球上最长的峡谷
It's literally called the Grand Canyon Greenland in parentheses,
后得名“格陵兰大峡谷”
despite it being bigger.
虽然这东西比大峡谷要大
Sometimes the dude who did it first matters than the dude who did it biggest.
有时候，谁先发现 比谁发现的大更重要
Antarctic "Countries" refers to multiple things.
南极的“国家”，指代多种情况
For one, real-world governments making territorial claims in Antarctica.
其一，是现实中各国对南极领土提出的主权声明
A lot of nations have claimed parts of the South Pole as their own,
许多国家会说南极的某块地是他们的
and they generally kept operations to the part of the continent they said finders keepers on.
通常，他们只在自己声明过的区域开展活动
But not always.
但也并非总是如此
Some countries with competing claims were friendlier with each other than others,
有些国家虽然主权声明重叠，但关系还挺好的
and some just do not care and will set up shop any place they feel like.
而有些国家根本不在乎，想在哪儿建就在哪儿建
There are several overlapping claims, but as of today, it's all a bit of hogwash.
现在虽然有几个重叠的主权声明，但说实话，都有点扯
As part of that Antarctic Treaty,
根据《南极条约》
it was agreed no nation could make new claims of land
各国同意不得再提出新的主权声明
or expand their current ones.
也不能扩展现有的领土
It didn't force anybody to give up their old claims,
条约并未强制任何国家放弃原有领土
but it essentially cast the status quo of the time in resin,
是把各国的领土固定了下来
and land claims have stayed the same in Antarctica ever since.
从此南极的领土一直保持不变
Still, half the nations who signed the treaty said that they
不过，签署条约的国家中有一半表示
still reserved the right to claim land if they felt like it.
有必要的话，他们仍保留未来提出领土主张的权利
And there's speculation on if a country like the US, Russia, or even Brazil
有人猜测，美国、俄罗斯，甚至巴西这样的国家
will make a new claim of land eventually, but none have so far.
未来会提出新的领土主张，但目前为止没有
It's kinda neat.
挺有意思的
Antarctica is the only continent with no native human population,
在有人类居住的大陆里，南极是唯一没有原住民的大陆
and it's managed to remain one of the only kinda-sorta-neutral places on Earth.
至今仍是地球上少数保持“某种程度中立”的地方之一
Now, the other type of Antarctic countries
而另一类所谓的“南极国家”
are a result of this almost no-man's-land status at the South Pole.
则是接近南极无人区状态的产物
Because parts of Antarctica are still officially unclaimed by any nation-state,
因为在明面上，有部分南极领土没有被任何国家认领
random folks who have never set foot on that ice
一些从未踏足冰原的人
have made unofficial claims of statehood
便对这些无人区提出了非官方的国家主权声明
on some of that unclaimed land called Micronations.
建立了所谓的“私人国家”
Micronation is basically a country not recognized by any real nation on Earth.
私人国家，基本上就是没有任何现实国家承认的国家
Shoutout Kekassia viewers.
向《给力西亚》的观众问好
West Arctica is the biggest as far as I'm aware,
据我所知，「西南极大公国」是最大的私人国家
and is the biggest area of claimed land not recognized by a single real country.
也是所有未被任何真实国家承认的土地中最大的一块
West Arctica has 2,000 citizens from across the world, none of which live there,
西南极有大约2000名“世界公民”，但是没有人居住
but these guys even have a national anthem, so they got somethin' goin' on.
他们甚至有自己的国歌，算是有点东西
The dude who started the country, Travis McHenry,
西南极大公国的创始人叫 特拉维斯·麦克亨利
calls himself Grand Duke Travis,
自称“特拉维斯大公”
which skirts on being very cool while brushing close to very bad and racist territory.
这个称号有点酷，但又差点就踩到种族歧视的雷区了
Either way, it's still very LARPy,
呃，有点像在玩剧本杀
so I'm docking points for not being ashamed of the things you enjoy.
众目睽睽之下玩剧本杀，感觉心理素质堪比露出
There are other Antarctic countries like the Grand Duchy of Flandrences,
还有其他南极国家，比如弗兰德伦西斯大公国
but they all have a relatively similar theme of being a marketing gimmick.
但这些国家都是名气大于实力，沾点炒作
These Micronations are more often than not used as branding for charity organizations
慈善组织就经常用私人国家给自己打广告
that try to raise awareness for climate change and its effect on the habitats of Antarctica.
旨在提高公众对气候变化，及其对南极生态影响的关注
The Dickburg was originally gonna be a humorous example of pareidolia,
“鸟山”，一开始可能是大脑错觉的幽默例子
but I found more than one iceberg that got famous for lookin' like a penis,
但我发现有不止一座冰山因外形像吊闻名
so now it's a recurring phenomenon.
这是一个周期性现象
Now I get to dedicate an entry to icebergs with ball sacks.
所以我得给“有蛋的冰山”开一个条目
The articles reporting on the two different Dickburgs
报道这两座不同“鸟山”的文章
are giving me the full range of reactions you could possibly have to one of these.
让我见识到了人们可能对此事做出的所有反应
From Livescience.com,
根据livescience.com的报道
加拿大假吊镇海湾惊现“巨型男根状”冰山
引众人惊讶
It's not a joke.
这可不是段子
Dildo Canada got a dick-shaped iceberg sent to them like an omen from the gods.
假吊镇收到男根状冰山，仿佛是上天赐予的征兆
I was gonna make a joke about a dick-worship-based religion,
本来想玩“生殖崇拜教”的梗
but that's just called being gay.
但是会很gay
Meanwhile, Metro put it a little more elegantly.
与此同时，《地铁报》的报道就含蓄一些
Penisberg, dead ahead!
看呐！鸟山！
I personally like it when you tell me information that way instead of how a credible source would.
我就喜欢这种报道方式，比正儿八经的新闻有意思多了
Is there, like, a male reproductive system under the ice?
难道冰下面真的藏着男性生殖器系统吗？
Apparently people called this iceberg the Hammer of the Gods,
据说有人把这座冰山称作“诸神之锤”
and I don't know what kind of gods these people are worshipping,
咱也不知道他们拜的是哪路神
because if that thing looks like a penis, then it's definitely a horse penis.
因为这座冰山长得跟吊一样，而且是马吊
I guess Poseidon was slangin' horse cock.
我猜是波塞冬在挥舞他的马吊了
*波塞冬的下半身是马
Look it up.
自己查吧
A-74 is an iceberg that was almost 20 times bigger than Manhattan
A-74是一座冰山，其体积几乎是曼哈顿的20倍
when it nearly crashed into the ice shelf that it came from.
当它差点撞上自己的母体冰架时
Watching the time lapse of the near-miss is like a Lego stop-motion movie
那个瞬间的延时录像就像乐高定格动画
right before a stormtrooper has to die
风暴兵阵亡的那个瞬间
and the red clay starts gushing out from all the holes it doesn't have.
然后红色黏土假血从不存在的伤口里喷涌而出
This near-miss happened in 2021,
这次差点撞上的事故发生在2021年
and up till then, A-74 had stayed close to its spawn point
在那之前，A-74一直徘徊在复活点附近
where conditions were cold enough for it to stay solid for a lot longer.
那里气温很低，让它能长时间保持坚固
But in August of that year, some strong eastern winds made that bitch a boomerang,
那年8月，一阵强劲的东风袭来，把A-74当回旋镖吹
just barely twirling around the ice shelf in a very close call.
在冰架周围打了个旋，差点撞上
If it hit, it probably would have caused an even bigger iceberg to pop out down the line.
如果撞上了，可能会导致后续出现更大的冰山
Is that like iceberg incest?
这算不算近亲繁殖？
One bird crashes into the ice shelf it came from, make it a bigger iceberg?
一座冰山撞上自己的母体冰架，就会生成更大的冰山？
We avoided it this time, but the brunt ice shelf where this happened
这次我们躲过了，但发生这事的主要冰架
is ironically not out of hot water just yet.
没有脱离苦海，好讽刺
Literally, too. The sea is getting warmer there.
字面意思也是如此，因为那片海域的海水正在变暖
Chasing Ice is a documentary from 2012
《逐冰之旅》是一部2012年的纪录片
that follows the exploits of photographer James Balog in the Extreme Ice Survey,
记录摄影师詹姆斯·巴洛格在极地冰川调查的工作
an organization who uses time lapses and photography, among other tools,
这个组织利用延时摄影和普通摄影等手段
to document the melting of glacial ice as a result of global warming.
记录全球变暖导致冰川融化的过程
It has an Oscar for Best Original Song,
这部片还获得了奥斯卡最佳原创歌曲奖
which Scarlett Johansson was one of the people singing it.
是斯嘉丽约翰逊唱的
I had no idea about any of this.
我还真不知道
What's cool that I wanted to mention here is that in this documentary,
我想特别提的一点是，这部纪录片
these guys managed to record the biggest ice-calving event ever caught on film.
记录下了有史以来最大的冰川崩裂事件
Even just on a flat screen, this stuff looks insane.
即使在屏幕上看，也非常震撼
It's like seeing the Forretress of Solitude sprout up on Viagra,
就像是吃了伟哥以后茁壮成长的「孤独堡垒」一样
except that is real and Viagra is not.
这可是真的，而伟哥只是个传说，，，
It's hard to conceptualize something that huge moving like that, or moving at all, really.
很难想象这么大的冰川能动起来，真挺难以置信的
The Iceberg Lounge is a personally motivated entry on this chart,
「冰山会所」出现在冰山图，是我的私货
and a fictional nightclub from Batman media
它是蝙蝠侠作品里虚构出来的一个夜总会
that serves as the base of operations for the iconic Batman villain, The Penguin.
是蝙蝠侠的经典反派——企鹅人的大本营
I swear, not everything with Iceberg in its name will have an entry.
我真的不是有意把所有带“冰”的东西都介绍一遍
Just a lot of them.
只是有点多罢了
And I like this one personally, so I get to put it in.
而且我很喜欢它，所以就塞进来了
If you don't like it, you should have made the video first.
不喜欢的话，就去自己做一个
In Batman Arkham City, the Iceberg Lounge is depicted as the building
在《阿卡姆之城》里，冰山会所是博物馆改造而来的
that has frozen water and ice platforms that you have to surf on inside of it,
里面的水全冻成冰了，蝙蝠侠能在平台上滑行
all while a shark that somehow lives there tries to eat you.
底下有一个吃人的鲨鱼
You then have to beat the living tar out of that thing to get the shark to leave you alone.
你要操控蝙蝠侠把鲨鱼打一顿，它才能安心滚回家
Shark repellent was never some shit Batman actually needed.
蝙蝠侠的战力本来就不需要用防鲨喷雾
It was just a marketing tactic to sell toys to idiot 1960s toddlers.
这只是66版蝙蝠侠卖儿童玩具的营销噱头
The Iceberg Lounge also appears in the 2022 film The Batman multiple times,
冰山会所也出现在了22年的《新蝙蝠侠》中
where Robert Pattinson uses it as a fun backdrop to beat people up on.
帕蝙在炫酷的冰山会所里激情打人
Iceberg Lettuce should probably not be on this chart,
「冰冻生菜」本不属于冰山的冰山图
but it has a funny name, sorry,
但是这个名字真的很好玩，织布机
my personal enjoyment will always come before quality control in this channel.
在这个频道里，我的个人喜好永远优先于质量
You should be used to it by now if you're this far into the video.
如果你能看到这里，说明你也习惯了
Still, Iceberg Lettuce was developed in 1894 by the Burpee Seed Company.
说回正题，冰冻生菜是Burpee种子公司在1894年培育出来的
It was one lettuce type of many, but easily one of the most well-known at the time.
它只是众多生菜品种之一，在当时迅速俘获了众多人的胃袋
It got its name from how lettuce used to be packed and shipped on crushed ice,
因为当时运输生菜会铺一层碎冰，故得名冰冻生菜
causing the lettuce heads to look like icebergs.
这样一来，生菜球看起来就像小冰山
It lost a lot of its popularity to much doper leaves like Romaine lettuce ,
后来，莴苣（罗马生菜）夺走了冰冻生菜的热度
which is darker, leafier, and generally more nutritious,
其叶子更绿、更大，营养价值也更高
but Iceberg Lettuce still has some diehard fans in modern times.
不过，冰冻生菜至今仍有一群死忠粉
It's a cult classic of the salad community,
在沙拉人里沾点cult
and if you like it, you're not alone if you look hard enough.
喜欢冰冻生菜并不孤独，同好是会相互吸引的
噢 我们真的要向下深入了 像爷们那样找死
Aw,we're really going under now,and we're gonna die like real men
因为这里是第三层 我们正随着这艘船一起沉入深海
cause it's layer 3 and we're sinking with this ship.
还记得早些时候提到的B-15冰山吗？
Remember Iceberg B-15 from earlier?
就是那座和牙买加差不多大 后来裂成几大块的南极洲冰山
The Antarctic one,roughly the size of Jamaica that later broke into massive chunks?
说实话 B-15A裂开一块而产下它的小冰山 更像是一次剖腹产
A chunk of B-15A busted open to birth its baby bergs was more of a C-section if I'm being honest.
而他们就像杀猪一样把那玩意切开了
They cut that dude open like a pig.
2005年10月 在远在地球的另一极的阿拉斯加湾外海 发生了一场超级风暴
In October 2005,off the Gulf of Alaska,all the way on the planet's other pole,there was one hell of a storm kicking up.
这场风暴威力非常哈人 在大约一周后
One so powerful that nearly a week later,
风暴把一股毁天灭地的几把巨浪一口气吹到南边 撞上了远在8300英里之外的B-15A 然后把它震碎成差不多六块
a terminator of an ocean swell made its way down to old Iceberg B-15A,8,300 fucking miles away, and cracked it open into like half a dozen pieces.
这真是我这辈子见过最操蛋的随机事件
That is some of the worst RNG I have ever seen in my life.
这下不管弹幕再怎么刷“运气不好”或“技术问题” 也不会让我继续破防了
No amount of unlucky or skill issue spam in chat could put more salt in that wound.
简直相当于输掉一把5v1的顺风残局，不过是大自然翻版
That's like the nature equivalent of losing a 5v1 S&D round.
冰川跃动是一种短期事件 冰川会猛踩油门 移速比平时快上100倍
Glacial surges are short-term events where glaciers slam the gas pedal and start moving up to 100 times faster than usual.
据悉 世界上只有1%的冰川会发生跃动 主要集中在北大西洋 也就是在这附近
Only 1% of world glaciers are thought to ever surge,concentrated mainly in the North Atlantic,around here.
跃动的周期约为10到200年 具体取决于冰川状况
Surges function on roughly 10 to 200 year cycles,depending on the glacier,
每年大概有15到超过100起跃动 但在许多情况下 它们仍是无法预测的
and there are 15 to over 100 surge events in a year,but they still remain unpredictable in many cases.
冰川漂砾是指被冰川搬运所沉积下来的岩石
Glacial erratics are rocks that get glacially deposited,
也就是冰川在山洪或跃动中把那些小玩意儿捡起来 然后把它们扔到些它们本不该出现的地方
like glacial ice in a flood or a surge,picks them bitches up,and then places them somewhere they are not meant to be.
我脑子不太好使 但我喜欢石头 它们在大小和构成上都与当地原生的截然不同
I'm not brain-dood,but I like rocks.They are distinctly different to native rocks in the area,both in their size and what the erratics are composed of.
在俄勒冈州麦克明维尔市的“漂砾岩州立自然保护区”里的岩石 就是这些巨石的样品
The stones at the Erratic Rock State Natural Site in McMinnville,Oregon, are an example of some of these big-ass rocks,
事实上那也是我们所知最大的一块
and the biggest we know of,in fact.
那里的冰川漂砾是最近一次冰期的最后遗迹之一
The glacial erratics there are some of the last remains of the most recent ice age,
数千年前 在美国太平洋西北地区 大型洪水时有发生
where thousands of years ago,major flooding was very common in the American Pacific Northwest.
洪水会携带着巨大的冰块 漂过今天的俄勒冈州和华盛顿州
They would carry massive glacier chunks sailing across modern-day Oregon and Washington,
当洪水退去后 那些从冰川上剥离下来的冰块就留在原地
and after the floodwaters ran their course,the iceberg chunks that got ripped off a glacier were left behind.
冰融化后 这些岩石就露了出来 散落在离它们来源地数百英里之外的地方
After the ice melted,these rocks were what was inside,and got left stranded hundreds of miles away from where they came from,
有的现在正安静地坐落在一些风景如画的美国农田里
now nestled to some photogenic American farmland.
冰下化石指的是发掘出的大量数百万年前已灭绝物种的遗骸
Fossils under the ice refers to the discovery of lots of remains from a number of extinct species from millions of years ago,
以及一些最近死亡 保存得非常完好的动物尸体
as well as some really well-preserved bodies of animals that died more recently.
近代能有更多的发现 是因为气候变化加剧 越来越多的冰层融化了
More finds have been made in recent history because of climate change heating up and melting more and more ice,
数百上千年甚至好几百万年前就埋在雪下的老资历因此重见天日
revealing stuff that got shoved under the snow hundreds to thousands to millions of years ago.
这方面的例子有很多
There are a lot of examples of this,
但我发现其中最有趣的 是南极远古物种的遗骸 那时南极还覆盖着树木之类的植被
but some of the ones I found most interesting are the remains of long-gone Antarctic species from when it was still covered in trees and stuff.
欧内斯特·沙克尔顿先前来南极探险 他们在四处走动时 发现了树叶和某些东西的印记
As early as Ernest Shackleton's expeditions,they were finding the imprints of leaves and things they found while walking around,
这表明南极以前可能要暖和得多
which indicated it probably used to be a lot warmer down south.
显然 像南极鳄这样的动物 曾与极地恐龙一道四处横行
Animals like Antarctic crocodiles were apparently stomping around with polar dinosaurs.
大约4000万到1亿年前 爬行动物主宰着南极
Reptiles used to be running the show in Antarctica some 40 million to 100 million years ago.
但在较近期的发现中 我就觉得 千万年前的老资历遗骸还能保存得这么完好 那可潮酷完了
But of the more recent finds,I think the well-preserved remains of animals from millennia ago are kinda neat.
古生物学家们非常喜欢像给宠物取名一样为这些东西命名
Paleontologists are really fond of naming these things like pets.
例如披毛犀 萨沙
For instance,Sasha the Woolly Rhino.
这是一只在西伯利亚发现的幼年披毛犀 它死的时候疑似是嗑嗨了
They found a baby woolly rhino in Siberia that died looking faded out of its mind.
那时候的老资历也给小登od是吧？
They gave drugs to kids back then too,huh?
行吧 从小od 终生od 不od不行的
Well, start them young and you got a customer for life.
尽管如此 听起来 这些人对一个32000年前就夭折的犀牛幼崽产生了深厚的感情
Still,it sounds like these dudes got really attached to a baby that hasn't been a baby for 32,000 years,
说实话还挺可爱的 我很高兴来冰川刨坟的是这些好人
and it's honestly kind of endearing.I'm glad it's the good people who get to grave rob glaciers.
萨莎是我们所知该物种唯一的幼体
Sasha is the only baby of its species we know of,
对于许多像它这样的标本而言 看看有没有DNA在冰中被保存下来是重中之重
and the goal with a lot of specimens like it is to see if any of its DNA was preserved while in ice,
正是因为它的状况良好 所以发现的可能性要大不少
as with its good condition,that's a lot more likely.
我找到了大量关于在世界上较冷的地区发现各种化石和木乃伊的例子
There are tons of examples I came across for all sorts of fossil and mummified corpse discoveries in the colder parts of the world.
如果你想知道都挖出了些什么东西 那这本身就是另一个可以深入发掘的兔子洞
It's another rabbit hole in its own if you want to know what kind of stuff's been dug up.
东方湖是南极最大的冰下湖 它就位于（前）寒极点的南方
Lake Vostok is the biggest subglacial lake in Antarctica,and is literally right at the southern pole of cold.
所谓寒极点 指的就是记录到全球已知最低温的地方
The poles of cold are the places in the northern and southern hemisphere where the lowest known temperatures were recorded.
在那里 你的魔丸会缩进体内 并因寒冷而瑟瑟发抖
Your nuts will roll up inside you there, just quivering in fear of the chill.
东方湖的水量比除了伊利湖以外的其它四大湖加起来还多 面积比除了苏必利尔湖以外的其它五大湖都大
Lake Vostok has more water in it than all the Great Lakes except Erie,and covers more area than all the Great Lakes except for Lake Superior.
为了让它更像BOSS战的背景设定 俄国人决定在地球上最冷的地方建立一座科考站
To make this even more like the lore for a boss encounter,the Russians decided to put a research station right on top of the coldest place on earth,
而此处恰好也位于有史以来最大、最神秘的湖泊之上
which is also on top of the biggest,most mysterious lake ever.
东方站和日本的某同名ip没有任何关联 因此它的名字并没有多么创
This Vostok station just translates to East Station,so that's not so creative.
但幸好 巧合的同名让我可以自己骗自己 让我相信它比实际上炫得多
But thankfully the language barrier lets me pretend it's much cooler than it is.
你也是老ACG雅士对吧 相信你懂我意思
It's the same way with anime, and you know I'm right.
湖中有微生物 它们最早是一群美国做题蛆发现并于1999年报道的
Microbe life in the lake was first discovered by some American nerds and reported in 1999,
但后来到了2020年 才初次有报道称那里生活着一种像鱼一样的生物
but later in 2020 came the first reports of a fish-like thing living down there.
有人质疑从湖中采集的样本是不是污染了的 但原本的读数似乎已有证实 并没有受到污染
Some folks have questioned if the samples taken from this lake were contaminated,but the original readings seem to have been confirmed as legit.
除此之外 俄罗斯政府一直在自行钻探东方湖
Outside of that,the Russian government has been doing their own drillings into Lake Vostok,
他们声称会好好对待这个湖 并尽量不干扰其自然的生态系统
saying that they'll take good care of the lake and try not to disrupt its natural ecosystem.
但他们的钻探方法显然把湖泊污染得一塌糊涂 因为他们做事风格向来狂野震撼宇宙
But their drilling methods have apparently been contaminating the shit out of the lakes,because of how dirty the way they do things has been.
俄佬用上了化学防冻剂 这样钻孔就不会再次冻住了
The Russians were using chemical antifreeze,so the hole wouldn't refreeze and close up again.
确实挺让人担心 他们使用那样简陋的钻探方法可能会污染湖泊
The concern was that they could contaminate the lake using crude drilling methods like that,
这样搞 不说会在人们发现那里有什么之前就把所有生物图干净了吧 至少也可能会严重扰乱那个封闭的生态系统
and if it doesn't just kill whatever's down there before we even get to find out what it is,it could severely disrupt that closed ecosystem in general.
一些科学家认为 会因为持续性钻探而遭到污染的 不仅仅是东方湖
Some scientists think that not just Lake Vostok will get screwed from continued drilling,
根据他们推测 南极所有的冰下湖都是相连的 如此行为可能会导致那里的一切受到波及
but some researchers speculate that all subglacial lakes in Antarctica are connected,and the consequences of this could just be fucking up everything down there.
每个人都告诉老毛子要使用热水钻探 因为那样更安全
Everybody was telling the Ruskies to use hot water drilling,because it was safer,
但俄罗斯就是不能发足够的电去进行热水钻探 所以他们坚持使用自己的方法
but Russia just didn't have the means to generate enough power to hot water drill,so they pushed ahead using their own methods.
这一切都是徒劳 因为他们拿到的样本被钻井油污染得太严重 无法确定其中是否有生命 而他们后来也承认了这一点
It was all for nothing anyways,because the samples they got,they later admitted were too contaminated from drilling oil to determine if there was any life in it.
要是有人能预见到这点并提醒他们放慢速度就好了
If only someone,anybody,could have seen this coming and warned them to slow down.
贝奇莫号 又被称为“永不沉没的幽灵船”
The SS Baychimo,also called the Unsinkable Ghost Ship,
这是关于一艘安分守己且与世无争的船的故事
is the story of a ship minding its own damn business and not bothering anyone.
贝奇莫号是一艘于1914年在瑞典为哈德逊湾公司建造的货运蒸汽船
The Baychimo was a cargo steamer built in 1914 Sweden for the Hudson Bay Company,who traded pelts with Inuit communities along Alaska's coastline.
该公司经营着与阿拉斯加沿岸因纽特部落的毛皮贸易
who traded pelts with Inuit communities along Alaska's coastline.
1931年 在一次贸易航行的末尾 刚刚载满毛皮的贝奇莫号被浮冰困住了
In 1931,at the end of a trading run,and having just stocked up on furs,the Baychimo got trapped in pack ice.
这是新手才会犯的错误 船员们选择弃船 在冰上走了半英里 去附近的巴罗镇暂住了几天
Rookie mistake.The crew chose to abandon ship and walk a half mile on the ice to the nearby town of Barrow in order to take shelter for a few days.
但天有不测风云 当他们回来时 贝奇莫号再一次挣脱
But too bad for them,the Baychimo broke free again by the time they got back,
不过幸运的是 一周后它又在别处被困住了
though it luckily got stuck again a week later somewhere else.
一些船员乘飞机离开巴罗 而其他人则留下等待冬天结束 并打算在冰消雪融后取回他们所有的东西
Some of the crew left Barrow via aircraft,while others stayed behind to wait out the winter and try to retrieve all their shit after the season had ended.
但上帝又一次打乱了他们的计划 贝奇莫号在一场暴风雪过后再次消失
But God stuck a wrench in their plans again when after a blizzard came through,the Baychimo disappeared once again,
留下的船员认为它当时已经沉没了
and the remaining crew thought it had just sank at that point.
然而他们得到消息 说有人在约45英里外目击到了它
However,they got a tip-off that it had been seen some 45 miles away,
船员们前去检查 结果不知怎地发现贝奇莫号仍浮在水面上
and the crew went to check it out and somehow found the Baychimo still above water.
他们认为这艘船很可能还会在冬天结束前沉没
The boys figured the ship was probably still gonna go under before winter ended,though,
所以他们把船上最贵的毛皮拿走 将贝奇莫号最后一次交由命运处理
so they took the most expensive furs off the boat and left the Baychimo to its fate for the last time.
事实证明 他们对它无法存活的判断大错特错
Turns out,they were very,very wrong about it not surviving.
简直错得离谱 以至于我都不好意思去讲这件事
Like,so wrong that I would be embarrassed to talk about it.
在那之后近40年里 这艘船一次又一次地被人目击
For nearly 40 years after that,the ship kept getting spotted.
且在接下来的几十年里 发生这种情况的次数多得搞笑
It happened a hilarious amount of times in the decades following.
甚至已经到了许多人实际上能够登船四处逛的地步
It was to the point where multiple people were actually able to board the ship and take a look around.
最后一次记录在案的目击是在1969年 此后就杳无音讯
The last reported sighting was in 1969, and it hasn't been seen since.
2006年 阿拉斯加政府启动了一个项目来寻找贝奇莫号 无论它是在水上抑或是水下
In 2006,Alaska's government launched a project to find the Baychimo,whether it's above or below the water.
无论如何 它至今尚未被找到 我宁愿相信它只是在外头悠哉悠哉地漂着
Either way, it hasn't been found yet,and I like to think that it's just still out there chilling.
虎鲸“冰山”是一头全白的成年虎鲸 它是最早被发现的之一
Iceberg the orca is an all-white adult killer whale,one of the first to ever be discovered.
它首次被发现于2010年的俄罗斯海岸 并在2016年最近一次被目击时仍活着
It was first recorded off the Russian coast in 2010,and was at least alive in 2016 when he was most recently spotted again.
“冰山”和一​​个由其它十几头虎鲸组成的鲸群一同生活 很高兴了解到他身边有一群亲友
Iceberg lives with a pod of a dozen other orcas,and it's nice to know that he's got a good group of friends around him.
如果鱼类之间的种族歧视和人类的一样 那日子肯定很难过
If fish racism is anything like human racism,shit's gotta be tough.
发现它的那支团队 我寻思是叫远东俄罗斯虎鲸计划（FIROP）吧
The group who spotted him,the Far East Russia Orca Project,or FIROP,I think,
他们也有着同样的担忧 但他们说“不 他看起来只是大伙中的一员”
they had the same concern too,but they said,nah,it seems like that he's just another one of the fellas.
没有看到任何歧视的迹象 也许虎鲸真的是色盲
No sign of discrimination that they've seen.Maybe orcas really are colorblind.
目前尚不清楚“冰山”是因白化病或白变而浑身雪白 但它引起了巨大轰动
It's unknown if Iceberg is all-white because of albinism or lucism,but he made a big splash,
这可能是我整个视频中唯一刻意使用的双关了
and that might be the only intentional pun in this whole video.
人们爱死这家伙了 大伙觉得它看起来是真的帅
People love this fucker.We thought he looked so cool.
他们把大白鲨唯一的天敌做成了毛绒玩偶 在Etsy上很快被一扫而空
They made plushies of the great white shark's only natural predator before they promptly sold out on Etsy.
人类会认为任何东西都很可爱 而无论它杀死他们的能力有多强
Humans will decide literally anything is cute,no matter how capable of killing them it is.
他们把祖国人做成了一个TMD黏土手办 除了我还有谁看过那部剧吗？
They made Homelander into a fucking Nendroid figure.Did anybody watch that show other than me?
好吧 做黏土人的肯定有人看过 因为他们给了他一桶他老母的奶喝
Well, somebody at Nendroid did because they gave him a bucket of his mom's milk to sip on,
所以这算个不错的小彩蛋
so that's a neat little reference.
说到近亲繁殖 虎鲸患白化病的几率要高得多
Speaking of incest,orcas have a much higher chance of albinism,
预计为千分之一 而哺乳动物的患病几率为万分之一
estimated at 1 in 1,000 odds,as opposed to 1 in 10,000 for mammals.
白化虎鲸相对较高的比例表明
This relatively high ratio of albino orcas suggests that
在本就有限且濒危的虎鲸种群中 近亲繁殖并不罕见
inbreeding is not super rare in the already limited and endangered orca population.
白化虎鲸虽然漂亮 但其往往寿命较短
As pretty as albino orcas are,they tend to die younger.
“冰山”显然是幸运儿之一 因为他已成年
Iceberg is apparently one of the lucky ones,as he's reached maturity
且在我们上次见它时情况良好
and was still doing well the last time we saw him.
冰山爆破是冰山研究领域早年间干过的事情之一
Blowing up icebergs is one of those things they did in the early days of the field of iceberg study,
因为难道这不好玩吗？至少我的理由会是那样
because wouldn't it be funny?At least that would have been my reason.
有一篇名为《冰山的物理特性及破坏方法》的旧论文
There's this old paper called Some Physical Properties of Icebergs and a Method for Their Destruction,
撰写这篇论文的物理学教授霍华德·巴恩斯
where the physics professor who wrote it,Howard Barnes,
组织了一些测试 揭示了很多如今我们讨论过的关于冰山的事实
ran tests that uncovered a lot of things about icebergs we've actually already gone over today.
其中一项是测试將高温作用于冰山的效果
One of these tests was effects of applying high-temperature heat to icebergs,
霍华德承认他们只是将铝热剂绑在冰上再炸了它
where Howard admits they just strapped thermite to the ice and just blew it up.
在他们测试过的最大冰山上
On the biggest iceberg they tested,
他们将一枚炸药埋入三英尺深的冰下
they buried a charge three feet deep into the ice
还说在引爆时 火柱向空中喷射了超100英尺
and said that setting it off made a plume of flame shoot over 100 feet in the air,
将冰块炸向四面八方
sending chunks of ice flying outward in all directions.
对冰山的结构性破坏导致它持续开裂了一整晚
The structural damage to the iceberg caused it to keep cracking throughout that night,
一声巨响吵醒了住在当地的居民
and a loud sound woke up folks in the area who lived there,
因为那座冰山在结构完整性受损后脱落了一大块
because the iceberg later had a huge part of it break off after losing its structural integrity.
他们拍下了冰山在被“理发”前后的照片
They took pictures of the icebergs before and after going to great clips pictured here,
如图所示 它被剃掉的可不仅仅是头顶那一点.
where they took a little more than just the top off.
这是爆炸前后的照片 这篇论文里还有好几张这样的
This is before and after the explosions,and there's a few of those in this paper.
虽然把炸弹放进冰里看起来好像很简单
As simple as putting a bomb in ice might seem,
但对我而言 在没能真正看到爆炸的情况下 观察它如何变化仍然很有趣
to me it's still interesting to see how it changed without getting to see the actual explosion.
而且 嘿 他们在尝试这个的时候是相当有远见的
And hey,it was pretty damn forward-thinking when they tried this.
事实证明 炸毁冰山实际上相当有用
It turns out blowing up icebergs can actually be pretty useful.
国际冰情巡逻队多年来一直在将这些家伙炸成碎片
The International Ice Patrol has been detonating these babies to smithereens for ages,
就像我对待真婴儿似的
much like I do to real babies.
尽管当年初始的测试方法并没那么科学
And despite the initial test methods back in the day not being that scientific,
但后来有一篇论文写到液氧是如何促使冰山爆炸的
Later,there was a paper written on how liquid oxygen could help cause icebergs to explode.
直到2020年 还有一篇论文在探讨如何间接地利用冰山抵御冰山
As recently as 2020,there was a paper on how to potentially use icebergs to ward off icebergs
以防它们摧毁像石油钻井平台、输油管道等基础设施及船只
from destroying infrastructure like oil rigs and pipelines,as well as ships.
然而最有趣的是
Most interestingly,however,
他们提到了利用爆破来有目的地引发可控的冰山崩解
is the potential they mentioned to shape an iceberg to our liking by causing a controlled ice calving event on purpose using explosions.
肯定会有哪个家伙会试图制造有史以来最大的斐济杯
Some dude is gonna try and make the biggest pocket pussy ever
这样他就可以名副其实地对着大地母亲起飞了
so he can literally fuck Mother Nature.
而说到比奇岛的坟墓
For the beachy island graves,
让我迅速地回顾一下之前提到过的约翰·富兰克林探险队
let me give a quick refresher on the John Franklin expedition from earlier.
这是英国在19世纪的一次失败的远航
It was a failed 19th century British voyage
两艘船都失踪了 船长死于探险初期
that lost both of its ships and whose captain died early in the expedition.
船员们被困北极多年 最终没有一人幸存并获救
The crewmen were stranded in the Arctic for years and ultimately none of them survived to be rescued.
而比奇岛就是他们几个的最终归宿
And Beachy Island is where several of them ended up.
当时 幸存者选择将他们逝去的同伴安葬于此
It's also where,at the time,survivors chose to put their fallen fellas who didn't make it
并在岛上为他们举行了正式的葬礼
to rest and gave them proper burials on the island.
搜寻富兰克林探险队幸存者的人们在1850年偶然发现了这些坟墓
Folks searching for Franklin expedition survivors stumbled upon the graves in 1850.
后来到1854年 另一位名叫托马斯·摩根的搜寻者在船航行至该地区时死亡
And later in 1854,another searcher named Thomas Morgan died on his ship while in the area.
他被葬在已经安息在那里的富兰克林探险队员旁
He was buried alongside the Franklin expedition members already resting there.
到了90年代 比奇岛被定为加拿大国家历史遗址
In the 90s,Beachy Island was designated a National Historic Site of Canada.
而那时 原本的坟墓已有将近150年的历史 且还在继续恶化
And being nearly 150 years old by then,the original graves were deteriorating.
所以这些墓碑得到了翻新 换上了精致的青铜纪念碑
So the headstones got a facelift with some fancy new bronze memorials.
人们不常在冰山中进行洞穴潜水
Cave diving in icebergs is something that people do not do a lot.
事实上我只找到了一条关于此事的详细记录
In fact, I only found one detailed account of it ever happening.
而且它是由经验丰富的洞穴潜水员吉尔·海纳斯完成的
And it was by the seasoned cave diver Jill Heinerth.
她是第一位在冰山内进行洞穴潜水的人
She was the first to ever cave dive inside an iceberg,
同行的还有她当时的丈夫保罗·海纳斯和一位水下摄影师韦斯·斯凯尔斯
alongside her now ex-husband Paul Heinerth and an underwater cameraman,Wes Skiles.
吉尔那时已经下过许多疯狂的裂隙了.
Jill has been in a ton of crazy crevices by then already.
但在2001年
But back in 2001,
她听说了我们那个有牙买加大的老朋友——B-15冰山
she heard about our old Jamaica-sized friend,Iceberg B-15,
它是当时地球上能够移动的最大物体
the biggest moving object on Earth at the time.
呃 当它从冰架上脱落时
Well,when it broke away from the ice shelf,
它发生了断裂 并在冰山中形成了深邃的隧洞
it had fractured and formed tunnels in the iceberg that went deep.
冰山下看似有隧道通向冰山所刮擦过的海底
Ostensibly,there were tunnels under the iceberg that fed into the seafloor where the iceberg had scraped it.
在潜到某个阶段时
At some point well into the dive,
吉尔说她听到了令人担忧的断裂声、呻吟声和丈夫唠叨的声音
Jill said she heard concerning cracks,groans,and nagging husband noises
直到她的团队折返回他们进来的地方时 她才认出这些声音
that she couldn't identify until after her team doubled back to swim out where they came in.
然而他们却发现入口被完全封死了
That is,only to find it completely sealed off.
在水面上 他们的冰山崩解了一大块 堵住了他们来时的路
Above water,a big chunk had calved off the iceberg they were in and closed off the way they came.
所以他们不得不当场走出一条新路
So they had to improvise a new way out of there on the spot.
有一部名为《冰岛》的纪录片记录了整个过程
There's a movie called Ice Island that documented the whole thing.
我还没有把它看完
I have not watched all of it yet,
但如果你想了解更多关于这个主题的内容的话 那我会推荐它
but I'd recommend it if you want to find more about this topic.
我在里面听到的一句台词让我毛骨悚然
There was just one line I heard from it that gave me straight chills,
就是：“在那天 洞穴试图把我们留下来
and it was,the caves tried to keep us that day.
这让我打寒颤 而且并不是因为冷
It makes me shiver,and not because it's cold.
我相信这对于那些觉得自己可能受困的潜水员来说非常可怕
I'm sure it was very scary for the divers who thought they might be trapped,
但他们当时听起来感觉并不像船上的人听着那样哈人
but it sounds like it didn't feel as immediately dramatic to them as it did to those on the boat.
当水上的船员看到潜水员们成功脱险并浮出水面时
When the crew on the surface saw the divers had made it out and surfaced,
显然在开香槟 因为在水上看冰山崩解要壮观得多
apparently they were celebrating,because the iceberg breaking away looked way nuttier upstairs,
而他们之前都以为潜水员们死定了
and they just assumed the divers were super dead.
后来 在回到船上后
Later on,after getting back on the boat,
团队正在用餐 吉尔说他们听到甲板上传来一声尖叫
the team was all having some grub when Jill said they heard a scream from the deck
上甲板一看 发现他们刚刚还在里面的那座冰山已经开裂并崩塌了
and came up to see that the iceberg they were just inside of had cracked and dissolved,
完全压碎了他们刚刚探索的洞穴
completely crushing the cave they were just exploring.
这是我听过最疯狂的事情之一
That is one of the craziest things I have ever heard,
可能也是我在这个冰山图上最喜欢的条目之一了
and probably one of my favorite entries on this iceberg.
但天啊 我们肯定只需要一个人去试一次就够了吧？
But good lord,certainly we only needed one person to try that ever,right?
既然已经有人做过 就不需要其他人再去做了 对吧对吧？
Now that someone has,no one else has to do it, right?Right?
海纳斯夫妇都把他们在下面看到的景象形容得美轮美奂
The Heiners both described what they saw down there as beautiful,
我想他们是所有活物中 唯一能亲眼目睹那番景象的
and I imagine they're some of the only eyes on any living thing who will get to see that sight in person.
我是很嫉妒他们 但还不至于要去尝试一下
And I am jealous of them, but not enough to give it a go.
这是我讲到为数不多的几个如假包换且让我大开眼界的条目之一
This is one of the few entries where I'm talking about something completely real that just blows my mind.
当我知道球状闪电真实存在时
When I found out that ball lightning exists,
我觉得就算没有上古卷轴或哈利波特里的魔法也没事儿
I decided that I'm fine without Skyrim or Harry Potter magic being around,
因为像缴税这样的现实问题已经够让我喝一壶了
because real shit like taxes scares me enough.
阿梅里冰架是南极第三大冰架
The Amery Ice Shelf is the third biggest ice shelf in Antarctica,
它上面有着一个巨大的湖泊
and one of the things on top of it is a giant lake.
或者说至少在2019年6月之前有
Or at least there was a giant lake there until June 2019,
当冰川学家罗兰·华纳使用卫星观测阿梅里冰架时
when the glaciologist Roland Warner was looking at the Amery Ice Shelf via satellite
发现整个湖在短短三天内完全消失了
and noticed that an entire lake completely vanished in just three days.
6月9日 湖中有210亿到260亿立方英尺的水
On June 9th,the lake had 21 to 26 billion cubic feet of water in there,
而到了6月11日 湖水便自行消失得无影无踪
and by June 11th,the lake controls it itself and was nowhere to be found.
华纳和他的同事们认为
Warner and some folks he was working with think
湖水的总重量超过了冰层的承受能力
the weight of all the water in the lake was more than the ice could handle,
进而导致水力压裂
causing a hydrofracture.
水力压裂是指当作为容器的冰层所承受的水超过其负荷时 冰层就会开裂
A hydrofracture is an opening cracked into ice when the weight of the water that it's a bowl for is more than it can handle.
而这个裂缝让水得以外漏 并尽数倾泻入海
And that crack allows water to escape through it and pour all out into the ocean.
阿梅里裂缝实际上是首次被详细观测到有如此规模的水力压裂
The Amery Crack was actually the first hydrofracture of its size to be observed in detail.
讽刺的是 这里本应是阿梅里冰架上相对坚固的区域
Ironically,this was meant to be a relatively sturdy area of the Amery Ice Shelf,
有将近一英里厚
being almost a mile thick.
不过这个湖有点像是为了恰流量而假死
The lake kind of faked its death for clout,though,
因为在第二年 也就是2020年夏
because the next year in summer 2020,
湖水又开始重新蓄积 而且速度很快
the lake started filling up again,and fast.
它在几天之内就恢复到了一年前的水平
Within a few days,it was back to where it was the year before,
所以我们成功地被大自然给耍了
so we got successfully baited by nature.
血瀑布是泰勒冰川上的一处长相怪异的水景
The Blood Falls are a crazy-looking water feature
但它与冰川相比还是相形见绌
at the much less interesting Taylor Glacier,
两者都坐落于南极洲
both located in Antarctica.
血瀑布的百科条目比孕育它的冰川还要长
The Falls have a bigger wiki article than the glacier that literally causes them,
因为好巧不巧 它看起来炫酷多了
because unfortunately,it is much doper-looking.
血瀑布是从泰勒冰川流出的一股水流
The Blood Falls is a rush of water coming out the Taylor Glacier
看起来就像人血从冰中无休止地喷涌而出
that looks like human blood endlessly gushing out of ice.
而这个瀑布被发现于一​​百多年前
The Falls were first discovered over a hundred years ago,
设想一下在地球上最后一片未知之地的深处发现这玩意
and imagine finding this in the middle of the last unexplored place on Earth.
我可能会把这当作一个预兆并掉头走人
I'd probably take that as a hint to turn around and never come back.
如果我在20世纪初是个上帝的虔信徒
If I was a God-fearing man in the early 20th century,
那这将是耶稣能给我的最清晰的信号 告诫我不要去那种地方
that would be the clearest sign Jesus could ever give me to not go somewhere.
这个瀑布看起来很疯狂 但它的解释却有点无聊
The Falls look insane,but the explanation is kind of boring.
可惜的是 这里并没有什么血祭
Unfortunately,there are no blood rituals or blood sacrifices here.
起初 人们认为是红藻将水染成了深红色
Originally,people thought that red algae turned the water maroon,
但真正的原因是 从那个缺口中流出的盐水被氧化铁污染了
but the real reason is that the salt water coming out of that bleeding gash has been tainted by iron oxides,
水中的铁含量非常高 以至于变成了深红色
and there was so much iron in that water that it turned crimson.
水源于冰下一个一千多英尺深的湖
The water itself comes from a subglacial pool that's more than a thousand feet under the ice,
所以这儿不仅有血瀑布 还有血湖
so there's not just the blood falls,there's also the blood lake.
但没有人能真正确定它有多大
But no one's really sure how big it is.
摩根·罗伯逊是《徒劳无功》一书的作者
Morgan Robertson is the author of a book called Futility,
这本书今天能被人铭记 说实话 是因为故事同泰坦尼克号的沉没高度雷同
a book people remember today because the story has a,quite frankly,stupid amount of coincidences to the Titanic sinking.
尽管它出版于泰坦尼克号沉没前近20年
This is despite coming out almost 20 years before the Titanic sank.
《徒劳无功》出版于1898年 是属于19世纪的文学作品
Futility was published in 1898.It is 19th century literature.
虽然只是勉勉强强 但也足以让我对此小题大作了
Just barely,but it's enough for me to be dramatic about it.
我不打算详细介绍情节 因为我还没读过
I'm not going to go over the plot in detail because I didn't read it,
但简单来说 书中有一艘名叫“泰坦号”的船
but basically,there's a ship in the book literally named the Titan
它被誉为是永不沉没的
that is touted as unsinkable.
然后它在四月的一个夜晚撞上冰山后沉沒了
It then proceeded to sink after hitting an iceberg in April,
地点就位于北大西洋的冰山巷
in the North Atlantic Ocean,in Iceberg Alley,
船上的救生艇不足以让所有乘客安全脱险
where there were not enough lifeboats for all the passengers aboard to be safe.
和泰坦尼克号一样
And like the Titanic,
人们说正泰坦号可以承受正面撞击
a head-on blow was said to be survivable by the Titan,
但船侧的剐蹭才是导致灾难性损伤的原因
but the scrape along its side was what led to the catastrophic damage.
在沉没前 它曾是海洋上最大的船
Before sinking,it was the biggest ship on the ocean,
尺寸几乎与后来的泰坦尼克号完全相同
and was nearly the exact same size as the Titanic ended up being,
两者之间仅差了80多英尺
with only a little over an 80-foot difference between them.
随着关于这些巧合的传闻四散开来
As word of these coincidences got around,
很多人相信摩根·罗伯逊能够未卜先知
a lot of people believed Morgan Robertson could see the future.
他总说那是纯扯犊子
He always said that was a crock of shit,
他只是非常了解自己所写的东西罢了
and that he just knew a lot about what he was writing about.
公平地讲 这种说法也得到了许多人的支持
And to be fair,that's backed up by multiple people.
学者们说 很多相似之处可能源于罗伯逊对他那个时代的造船业和航海总体趋势有着深入了解
Scholars say that a lot of the similarities could be a result of Robertson's deep knowledge of the shipbuilding and the general maritime trends of his era.
书中的雷同在很多作品中被引用过
The coincidences with the book have been referenced in a bunch of stuff.
《神秘博士》曾试着用它来编写一段时间旅行的情节
Doctor Who took a swing at using it for a time travel plot,
而在Chunsoft制作的一部游戏中也提到了它
and it's mentioned in a game made by Chunsoft.
巧合的是 他们也制作了《宝可梦之不可思议的迷宫》系列
They coincidentally made the Pokemon Mystery Dungeon games,
那也是我最喜欢的游戏之一
and that's one of my favorites.
我越来越相信 地球不是围着老太阳转的 而是围着老子转的
Every day I'm more convinced the world doesn't orbit the sun, and instead revolves around me.
“弗莱彻冰岛”是一个超特么大的平顶冰山
Fletcher's Ice Island was one of those big-ass tabular icebergs,
长约七英里，宽三英里
something like seven by three miles long
由美国首次发现
and was discovered by the United States.
它曾经被用作冰上科考站
It was used as an ice station
并且在历史上被多次废弃过
and abandoned multiple times throughout its history
从此，弗莱彻冰岛再也不愿相信人类了
which had to give it really bad trust issues
尤其是每次抛弃它的都是同一批人
especially since the same people kept ditching it
而且抛弃后又要回来找它，渣男属于是
and coming back over and over.
这是一块非常宽阔的浮冰
It was a really wide piece of ice
但它的顶端仅比周围冰层高出约十英尺（折合3米左右）
but apparently it only poked like 10 feet above the pack ice and ice flows that surrounded it
有效地将整座冰岛伪装其中
effectively camouflaging the island.
从远处看的话，几乎发现不了它的存在
It was really hard to spot the distance
掩盖了弗莱彻冰岛其实是一座超特么大的冰山的事实
which helped hide its existence as a big fuck off iceberg.
它在1952年首次被用作气象研究站
It was first used as a weather research station in 1952
1957年，人们在弗莱彻冰岛上修建了一整条飞机跑道
and they ended up building a whole ass runway on the thing in 1957.
这样就能把更多设备运上冰岛
This allowed them to do a whole lot of more complicated stuff on Fletcher's
以展开各项复杂的科考工作
now that they could get more equipment to it
当时在岛上设立的基地名为“Alpha”
and the station they set up on the island around that time was named Alpha.
它是西方国家在北极运营的首个长期科研基地
It was the first long-term scientific base in the Arctic that was run by a Western country.
但苏联在这方面依旧遥遥领先
But you know, the Soviets were already all over that shit
美国的第一座刚落成的时候，苏联人就已经有六座了
having six by the time America had its first.
在弗莱彻冰岛服役期间，还有不少其他科考站也陆续投入建设
There were multiple other stations set up while Fletcher's was in use.
它的科研价值取决于它这些年都漂流到了哪
How viable it was for science team purposes depended on where it drifted over the years.
不过，无论有没有美国人到来
Still, US occupation or no
这具活死人一般的冰山终究还是要老去的
this walking corpse of ice got old.
1982年，弗莱彻冰岛最后一次出现人们的视野中
The thing was last spotted in 1982
研究者们普遍认为，它沉没于1983年夏季的某一天
and was believed to have melted some time in summer 1983
这座冰岛至少存在了31年
meaning it was at least 31 at past.
“海洋怪声”是1997年捕捉到的一种声响
The Bloop was a sound heard in 1997
研究人员在监听水下火山活动时发现了它
that researchers found while listening for underwater volcanic activity.
听上去很诡异，而且奇响无比
It sounded weird as hell and was very loud.
这里有一段加速播放的水下怪声供你参考
Here's a sped up version for your viewing stressor.
人们非常好奇这声音到底是哪来的
There was a lot of interest to find out what the sound was
大伙提出了各种各样的可能性
with people speculating all types of things
比如大王鱿鱼啦，海怪啦，古神啥的
like giant squids or other unknown ocean monsters
直到2005年，在南极
until in 2005 where in Antarctica
一支麦克风，与当年首次录下海底怪声的那支同款
the same type of microphone that recorded the bloop
录下了一种极为相似的声响
recorded a very similar noise
原来那是冰震的声音
that was the sound of an icequake.
也就是冰川崩裂
AKA an ice calving
破案了，海底怪声原来只是冰川裂开的动静
and the bloop was concluded to likely have been an iceberg calving event.
我是觉得这个解释很合理
This explanation satisfied me personally
但有不少人并不认同
but a lot of people just weren't buying it.
很多人说这是歪理邪说，一派胡言
Some folks thought it was wrong, a lie
甚至说是有意掩盖什么而编出来的说法
or even an intentional cover up
海底怪声的来源肯定是什么资崩不想让我们知道的真相，怎么这么坏啊
because what the bloop actually is must be something they don't want us to know about.
我觉得纯胡扯了
I don't agree, like at all.
不过我是精英政治的坚定拥护者
But I still believe in meritocracy
所以爱咋咋地吧，非相信这个那也挺好的
so we've all got that thing we're done for still having faith in.
冰指，也称冰钟乳
A brinicle or ice stalactite
是一种会自行生长的水下冰刺
is legitimately an underwater ice spear that grows on its own
会冻死任何触及它的生物
and kills any living thing it touches.
如下图所示，简直跟《战神》里的卢恩符文攻击一样
I'll show you, it's straight up looks like a god of war runic attack.
这段视频是加速过的
This is sped up footage
看看这冰钟乳，把海星全冻死了
but watch this brinicle kill some starfish.
我可能解释的不大准确
I might flub this explanation.
为此我读了几篇文章
I had to read several articles several times
方才获得了解释这一现象的信心
before I was even kind of confident I understood it
如有错误欢迎指出
so feel free to correct me.
如果你看过《海绵宝宝》的话应该懂，虽然背景设定是在海底世界
But you know how in SpongeBob despite the show being underwater already
但依然存在诸如湖泊、海洋之类的水体
there are bodies of water like lakes and seas
甚至还有比奇堡
and bikini bottoms somehow.
以防你不知道，海底确实存在水体
Well, if you didn't know those are real things
学名叫做“盐池”
and they're called brine pools.
盐池中的水盐度高于普通海水
Brine is water that has a higher concentration of salt in it than normal salt water.
盐分低于0.05%的水称为淡水
Water is considered to be fresh if it's made up of less than 0.05% salt
3%至5%的水叫咸水
saline or salt water is 3 to 5%
超过5%则叫盐卤
and it's brine water if it's over 5% salt
盐卤的盐度可高达26%至28%
all the way up to like 26 to 28% salt.
跟你在新英格兰开车时候路过见到的防冻液山一个重量级
It's like those anti-freeze mountains you see when driving into England.
关键是，盐卤的盐度越高
The important part is that having more salt
重量就越重，冰点也比一般的海水更低
makes brine heavier and it's freezing temperature lower than salt water.
重量使得盐卤沉降到了海底
The weight causes the brine to sink to the bottom of the sea
在海底形成了盐池，有些甚至和湖泊差不多大
and potentially form brine pools that can be the size of lakes.
盐卤冰柱主要在极地海洋出现
And brine coles form specifically in polar oceans
因为海水冻结后就变成了淡水
because when water freezes it becomes fresh water.
使得盐分被析出到了冰层周围
This pushes the salt out of the ice and into the area around it.
这为冰指创造了一个盐水“容器”
This creates a kind of container of salinated water for the brineicle
它会持续向下冻结
where it will continue to freeze downwards
但冰指周围的水盐度更高，冰点更低
but since the water surrounding that brineicle is now saltier and has a lower freezing temperature
因此冰指无法向外扩展
the ice can't expand outward
它虽然低温，但不足以冻结盐度更高的水
as it isn't cold enough to freeze the saltier water.
盐卤持续下沉，将冰指困在它形成的管道内
The brine will continue sinking keeping the brineicle in that tube
直到它触及海底
until it touches the sea floor
冰指在此开始沿着海床扩散，冻结一切所及之物
where it then starts freezing along the sea floor and murking everything it touches.
我以前一直很好奇，为什么冰会和火、电之类特别异世界的元素
I used to always wonder why ice was considered a core magic element next to stuff
并列为核心魔法元素
is already otherworldly as fire and lightning
前者是超帅等离子体，后者代表原始能量
fucking plasma and raw energy respectively.
冰呢？冰不过是冻住的水而已
And when ice was just frozen water in my head
也太没意思了罢
it seemed so boring.
但做这期视频的时候我学到了一大堆奇奇怪怪的新知识
But while making this video I've learned about so much weird shit
冰的力量竟然如此强大，我被吓尿了
ice can do that it terrifies me.
现在我明白了，冰实至名归，值得敬畏
So I get it now, ice earned its spot, no complaints here.
科学家在融化的冰层下发现了古文化的人类遗骸
Human remains in relics of old cultures have been found under melting ice
虽说年代不比那些动物化石久远
and while they don't go nearly as far back as animal fossils
但不少还是有很高的研究价值的
tons of them are still very neat.
近期有考古人员在挪威兰德布林冰原取得了重大突破
Recently there is a big breakthrough under the lendbreen ice patch in Norway
中头彩了说是，发掘出约800件维京时代文物
where they found a jackpot of roughly 800 Viking artifacts
有些已被冰封了逾千年之久
some that had been locked in ice for over a thousand years.
他们还发现了马蹄铁、拐杖、餐具
Among other stuff they found horse shoes, walking sticks, tools people would eat with
以及我最爱的维京特产马粪
and my personal favorite, Viking horse poop.
如此规模的发现
This big of a discovery
引发了未来何处还可能出土此类文物的讨论
opened a discussion of where else artifacts like these might be found in the future.
同时，冰层中还会发掘出自然木乃伊化的人类遗骸
Old-ass human remains have been also found mummified in ice as well
比如“极地公主”
like the polar princess
被发掘时她已沉睡了900余年
who was 900 years dead when they found her.
以及“冰人奥茨”
There's also Ötzi the Iceman
bro生活在公元前3350至3105年
some dude who lived between 3350 and 3105 BCE
1991年在奥地利与意大利交界被发现
and was discovered in 1991 on the border of Austria and Italy
至少已有五千年历史
making him at least 5,000 years old.
他因自然条件被木乃伊化
He was naturally mummified
是欧洲迄今为止发现最古老的自然木乃伊
and is the oldest known natural human mummy ever found in Europe.
近年的新发现还有
There are some more recent things
“白色战争”的遗迹
like the relics of the White War
这场一战期间的战役发生在阿尔卑斯山区
a battle in the Alps they're in World War I
阿尔卑斯山懂伐，高耸入云
that was high in the sky on mountain tops
意大利人与奥匈帝国就在雪峰高地间作战
and was fought between the Italians and then Austrian Hungarians.
奥匈帝国工程部队在冰川中凿出隧道
The Austrian Corps of Engineers built a whole-ass ice city
建起了一座冰上城市
by digging out of a glacier.
这座城市被遗弃后，冰川还在持续移动
After being abandoned, these glaciers kept on moving
而隧道最终被冰层掩埋了起来
and eventually buried the tunnels that were scraped out of them.
不过，多亏了冰川考古学家们最忠诚的朋友
However, thanks to glacial archaeology's best friend
全球气候变暖
Global Warming
部分遗物得以被考古学家们发掘出来
an opportunity came up for some of the artifacts to resurface
就此重见天日
and be sure with the world once more.
他们发掘出了油灯和其他日用品
They had found oil lamps and other practical items
以及一些日用品
as well as personal effects
比如一面带有女性人像的小镜子
like a mirror with a woman's portrait in them.
或许这名女子是某位战士的爱人，他希冀着回家与她团聚
She was presumably some random soldier's broad that he hopefully got to go home to.
“美军推冰山”说的是上世纪六十年代
The US Navy pushing an iceberg refers to a time back in the 60s
新西兰基督城的三艘海军破冰船
where in Christchurch, New Zealand three Navy icebreaker ships
将一座体积达250万立方码的冰山
essentially bullied and pushed around a berg that was 2.5 million cubic yards in volume.
推离了麦克默多海峡半英里
They pushed it a half mile away to get it out of the McMurdo sound
以保持重要航道畅通
which was a shipping route
什么自然母亲，自然母亲也不能挡咱的路
they weren't going to let some bum like Mother Nature get in the way of.
其中一艘破冰船——我们的老朋友巨兽号
One of the ships, our friend, the USS Glacier
曾试图单独推移冰山
tried to push the sucker on its own
但冰山实在是太过庞大，于是不得不寻求其他破冰船的帮助
but the ice was just too big and it took the other ships coming into help before the job was done.
这个故事虽短，对我来说却很新鲜
This is a short one but it's novel to me
因为我仅在《纽约时报》档案中找到了这条旧闻的相关内容
because the only source I could find was an old section and an archive New York Times newspaper
让我对自己的研究能力颇感自豪
and it made me feel very good at researching
虽说维基百科也曾在社科研究时帮我不少
even though Wikipedia carried me through social studies.
而且不觉得很有意思吗
It's also just fun to think that
我们与大自然斗智斗勇了这么多年
we've been trying to smack these things around for a while now.
我们早在六十年代就本能地想教训冰山
Even in the 60s, we just had a natural human urge
让它们为那些曾被撞沉的船血债血偿
to get back at icebergs for sinking our ships.
对了，其实前面我说谎了
Also, I lied.
1965年已有一张大名鼎鼎的照片，记录了破冰船推动这座巨大冰山的场景
There's actually a very famous photo of these ships pushing that massive iceberg back in 1965.
这画面实在是太奇妙了
It's kind of a fantastical image
这些渺小的人造物，居然拥有能对抗自然中的庞然大物的力量
these tiny man-made creations exerting its will over these behemoths of nature.
一想到人类赢了，就更觉得奇妙了
Not to mention winning.
大冰山摧毁小钻井平台
Iceberg's destroying oil rigs
说的是冰山小巷之类的地区蕴藏大量可采集的石油资源
refers to how there's lots of oil to drill for in places like iceberg alley
尽管石油钻井平台由坚硬耐用的金属建成
and even though oil rigs are made of hard, durable metal
就如当年的泰坦尼克号一般
so as the Titanic
但就算冰山最快都只能以一英里的时速移动，对于钻井平台来说也是个大威胁
even an iceberg moving at like its peak speed of one mile per hour is a concern
因为当移动的是一股不可阻挡的力量时
because when the thing moving is an unstoppable force
钻井平台在自然的力量之下就成了软柿子
the oil rig is a comparatively movable object.
如果冰山体积够大，就能轻易撕裂钢铁
Ice can tear right through steel if the berg is big enough
这些钻井平台光是建设就耗资数十亿美刀
and these oil rigs had billions of dollars put into them
还肩负着开采价值数十亿美刀的石油的重任
and are expected to pump billions back out.
因此对那些可怜（迫真）的石油高管来说，冰山可千万不能撞上钻井平台
So an iceberg hitting one is a no-no to those poor struggling oil execs.
为了防范这样的灾难，“冰山牛仔”应运而生
To prevent this, there are these iceberg cowboys
其中就有杰罗姆·贝克这样的人物
like one Jerome Baker
在钻井平台周围六十英里范围内，专门侦测并驱逐潜在威胁
who hunt for danger ice within a 60 mile radius of these oil rigs.
冰山撞击事故在冰山小巷地带一向屡见不鲜
Iceberg's hitting stuff has been an ongoing issue in iceberg alley since forever
《华尔街日报》称他们为“牛仔”，还真没说错
and these cowboys, as the Wall Street Journal called them, is kind of literal.
但不开玩笑，他们用的是长达四千英尺的超大套索
They have unironic, gigantic 4,000-foot-long lassoes for rounding up icebergs
将冰山套牢，牵引至别的地方
that they're trying to herd somewhere else.
这还不是他们的全部伎俩
That's not their whole toolbox, though.
他们清除冰山威胁的手段五花八门
They have tried lots of things to get rid of ice.
一套基础的“冰山牛仔”装备
The standard iceberg cowboy kit, though
通常包括水炮，用于击碎小块冰屑
looks something like using water cannons for lasering smaller bergie bits
以及巨大的绳索，用于拖离冰山
in that big old rope to tow larger icebergs away.
话虽如此，仍有些冰山体积过于庞大，难以拦截
That being said, some are just too big to stop.
有一座名为“泰拉诺瓦”的浮式钻井平台
One of the oil rigs named the Terra Nova is a floating oil rig
可在紧急情况下停产并迅速撤离
that can stop production to get the hell out of dodge if it needs to.
而另一座名为“希伯尼亚”的平台则需要固定在海床上
But another one called Hibernia is glued to the ocean floor,
不过即便遭遇六百万吨的冰山撞击
though it can handle up to a 6 million ton iceberg hitting it
它也能修复并继续作业
and still be repairable.
研发人员称，“要是有超过六百万吨的冰山撞上来，就麻烦大了”
Anything bigger than 6 million tons hits us and will be in trouble is a literal quote.
确实啊
Basically, yeah,
比六百万吨大，咱就彻底寄了
bigger than that, we get the fuck up.
大自然，你赢了，，，
The ice earned this one.
2011年，日本经历了有记录以来最强烈的地震
In 2011, Japan underwent its most powerful earthquake ever recorded,
同时也是全球第四严重的地震
also being the fourth most powerful earthquake recorded in the whole world.
你大概听说过这个
I'm sure you know
至少是听说过这场大地震引发的海啸
at least the tsunami part of this
当时巨浪高达130英尺以上
where waves were peaking at over 130 feet tall
洗劫了日本沿岸数英里区域
and flooded for miles inland Japan,
那是一场彻头彻尾的人间惨剧，造成了数千人死亡
it was a genuine tragedy that left thousands dead
甚至还有更多人失踪，伤者也不计其数
and even more missing or injured
无数家庭被迫流离失所
and displacing countless people.
这场地震的能量太过巨大，甚至会对数百英里外的地区造成深远影响
The amount of power behind something like that can have huge effects on places even hundreds of miles away.
举个例子，人类发现的规模最大的冰山
Just look back at the biggest iceberg of our lifetime.
南极洲的B-15冰山
B-15 in Antarctica,
因阿拉斯加海域的一场风暴被摧毁
getting destroyed because of a storm in the little backwater of Alaska.
日本地震数月后
Well, several months after the Japan earthquake
欧洲航天局发布了一组卫星图像
the European Space Agency revealed satellite images
图像显示，南极的一座巨型冰山断裂而下
that showed a massive iceberg have been capped off in Antarctica.
那座冰山正是日本大地震余波的产物
And that iceberg was the result of that earthquake
震源离南极十万八千里
generating waves oceans apart from the South Pole
但地震波过于强大，传播到南极洲后已然具有能够崩裂冰山的强大能量
that were strong enough to create an ice-calving event when they got to the continent.
埃里伯斯山是南极洲最高的活火山
Mount Erebus is the tallest active volcano in Antarctica.
南极有火山听起来很奇怪，但其实南极有好几座呢
A volcano in the South Pole sounds wrong, but there's actually a few of them.
如果算上休眠的火山，埃里伯斯山只排名第二
Erebus is only the second tallest when you count the dormant magma mounts.
埃里伯斯山有一个熔岩湖，自70年代以来一直很活跃
Mount Erebus has a lava lake that's been there in active since at least the 70s
也有可能要更早一点
probably longer
它的名字来自HMS埃里伯斯号
and was named after the HMS Erebus,
也就是被约翰·富兰克林搞没的那艘船
the same ship John Franklin managed to lose.
它以其冰冻喷气孔而闻名
It's known for its cool and ice fumaroles.
一般的喷气孔都是在地表上的一个裂口
A normal fumarole is a vent in the
能喷出火山气体和蒸汽
Earth where volcanic gas and vapor leak out
而当这些蒸汽从低于水冰点的地面逸出时
and ice fumaroles are what happens when the places those vapors are coming from
就会形成冰冻喷气孔
is below water's freezing temperature
也就是这些天然的冰塔
creating these natural ice towers.
不过真正让埃里伯斯山声名大噪的，要属埃里伯斯山山难
But the most infamous thing Mount Erebus is known for is the Mount Erebus disaster
又名新西兰航空901号航班空难
aka Air New Zealand Flight 901.
这趟航班从1977年开始运营，主打南极观光游服务
This was a flight that has run Antarctic site seeing trips since 1977.
它的预定航线是早上从奥克兰机场出发
Its scheduled route was to leave Auckland Airport in the morning
在南极上空盘旋几个小时
spend several hours over Antarctica
然后经由基督城机场，晚上返回奥克兰
then come back to Auckland the evening by way of Christchurch Airport,
听上去是没啥问题
which shouldn't have been a problem.
但在1979年，901号航班一头撞上了埃里伯斯山
But in 1979, Flight 901 flew into the side of Mount Erebus
机上所有人员全部遇难
causing everybody on board to perish.
超过250名乘客和机组人员死亡，无一生还
Over 250 passengers and crew members died with no survivors.
早期调查认定是飞行员失误导致了坠机
Early investigations concluded that pilot error caused the crash
但公众的压力促使调查被重新启动
but pressure from the public led to it being looked into further
结果发现，这次可怕的空难是多种因素共同作用的结果
and it ended up being a mix of several things coming together that led to this terrible tragedy
首先，飞机本来的航线是飞越麦克默多海峡
Firstly, the original flight path for the plane was to fly over the McMurdo sound.
这条航线畅通无阻，没有任何可能撞上的障碍物
Clear of anything to crash into at the plane's planned altitude.
但就在空难前一晚，航线被改到了埃里伯斯山
But the night before, the flight path had been rerouted to head towards Mount Erebus
而飞行员们从头到尾都不知道航线已经更改了
and the pilots were never told that it had been changed.
所以他们以为自己还在沿着原定航线飞行
So they thought they were still taking the same path home as usual
然而导航设备早就被设置成了新的航线
while the navigation equipment was set to that new route.
有的小朋友可能要说了，“这飞行员又不是眼瞎
You might say that doesn't explain why they didn't notice the giant volcano
怎么可能看不到马上就要撞上的冰山呢”
there were two seconds for braving into.
乘客在坠机前拍的照片
Passengers photos taken right before the crash,
也显示当时天空万里无云
even show there being perfectly clear conditions in the sky.
但问题就在于
But here's the thing
在飞机到达埃里伯斯山一带时
specifically at Mount Erebus, at the time the plane was there
由于飞机当时的接近方式
with the way the plane was approaching the volcano
引发了所谓的“白曚天”或“平光”现象
the conditions for something called a white-out or flat-light phenomenon were in effect.
以防你不知道，这是一种天气现象
If you don't know it's a weather condition
它会让物体的边缘和轮廓——也就是区分物体、表示距离的东西
where edges and contours, the things that separate objects, or in other words, convey depth,
在雪地里变得完全无法辨认
become completely indistinguishable in snowy areas
几乎没办法感知到危险的存在
and near impossible to telepath.
就901号航班而言，埃里伯斯山就在飞机正前方
Specifically with Flight 901, Mount Erebus was directly in front of the plane
而太阳则从飞机正后方照射着山体
and the sun was shining onto the mountain from directly behind the plane.
无法估测距离，山体和地面又一样都是雪白色
Since with no depth perception, the mountain was the same snow white color as the ground,
这意味着这座山对飞行员来说几乎是隐形的
that meant the mountain was practically invisible to the pilot.
他们本来就不应该在南极洲的这一地带飞行
They were never supposed to fly near this part of Antarctica,
自然也从未接受过如何应对“白曚天”现象的培训
so they were never given training on how to deal with white-outs.
机组人员以为他们正飞过罗斯冰架那片又长又白、一望无际的区域
The crew thought they were meant to be over the long, white, single-color stretch of the Ross Ice Shelf
当他们看到眼前一片白茫茫时
and seeing nothing but endless white
他们可能就以为自己到了那片冰原
they probably assumed that was where they were.
他们开始下降，却不知道山就在眼前
They began to descend, not knowing the mountain was there
因为在他们看来，那里根本就没有山
because to them, it looked like there was no mountain at all
接下来发生的事也可想而知了
and you know the rest by now.
真是一场可怕的惨剧
It was a terrible tragedy
而调查也揭露了新西兰航空的导航失误，以及试图掩盖真相的行为
and the investigations of the crash, revealed Air New Zealand's navigational error and attempted cover-up,
最后，航司不得不支付数以亿计的赔偿金
which led to nine figures in court lawsuits.
新西兰航空最后一次运营南极观光线路是在1980年初
The last Air New Zealand Antarctic flyover was in early 1980
此后这条航线便被彻底停运了
before the route was discontinued entirely.
这场灾难遗留的部分残骸在夏天雪融化时仍清晰可见
Some of the debris from the disaster is still visible during the summer when enough snow melts.
阿卜杜拉·阿尔·谢希是一位阿联酋商人
Abdullah Al-Shehi is an Emirati businessman
他创办了一家名为“国家顾问局”的公司
who started this company called the National Advisor Bureau.
他们自称是一个为初创企业提供咨询，帮助它们成长
They're self-described as a group that consults with startups for general growth
并变得更环保的组织
and to help them be more eco-friendly.
据他自己网站上的介绍
According to his bio on his own website
阿卜杜拉对“填补空核”这个项目很感兴趣
Abdullah has a personal interest in the project of filling the empty core.
这个项目的目标是让阿联酋再次变成森林，以改善自然环境
That thing's whole goal is to turn the United Arab Emirates back into a forest in order to improve the environment
我是说，一整个国家
like the Whole Damn Country.
他有几个极其宏大的方案
He has got some big plans
比如通过种植大量植物来建立一条“绿色地带”，以阻止沙漠的扩张
like making a green belt by planting a bunch of plants to stop the desert from expanding.
他还畅谈了他建造多条从海岸一直延伸到内陆的人工河的设想，这些人工河还要彼此连接
He's talked about creating artificial rivers that go from the coast to halfway into the country in our all connected,
不过我们重点来说说他的其中一个设想
but the one we care about here is his plan
他计划将一座冰山从南极拖到阿联酋，作为饮用水资源
to tow in iceberg all the way from Antarctica to the UAE as a source of fresh drinking water.
哈哈，觉得眼熟？
Sound familiar?
嗯，据我所知这人好像是真打算把他的设想付诸实践
Well, this is the dude who seems to be the most serious about making it happen
至少根据我查到的资料来看是这样
at least from what I've found.
显然，这个想法50年前就在阿联酋被提出过
Apparently, this was also proposed some 50 years ago in the UAE
想必bro的灵感就是从这来的
and that's where the idea comes from.
国家顾问局计划利用卫星挑选出他们的梦中情冰山
The National Advisor Bureau plans to pick the Goldilocks iceberg of their dreams using satellites,
这座冰山可能长达一英里
and that iceberg could potentially be up to a mile long.
多年来，阿卜杜拉·阿尔·谢希的这个冰山计划
Abdullah Al-Shahi has gotten a lot of coverage over the years
比他的其他计划获得了更多的媒体关注
for this iceberg idea over all his other plans
可能这个计划对于全球人民来说都更容易理解
probably because it has the most easy to understand
也更容易让人大呼“什么勾吧”
what the fuck factor to an international audience.
说这个计划“雄心勃勃”都算轻描淡写了
The plan is ambitious if you're a fan of understatements.
为了实践这个计划的方案也是五花八门，比如把冰压碎以便于运输
Some methods proposed include crushing up the ice to make it easier to transport
然后装在船上运回家
before pying it on top of a boat to ship back home,
疑似有点刻意为泰坦尼克号复仇的意思了
just getting it back and blood for the Titanic
哈哈，看看现在是谁撞碎谁啊
because who's breaking up who now?
这也就让我感觉有那么点意思吧
All that stuff raised my eyebrows a little
目前最被看好的方法，听起来也可能是最逆天的
but the method in the lead right now is probably the craziest sounding
而且还有图片佐证，样样俱全
and it's got pictures and everything.
这个想法是使用国家顾问局将要开发的一项全新技术
The idea is to use this brand new technology that the NAB will develop
旨在阻止冰山在运输过程中解体
that is meant to stop the iceberg from breaking up into chunks
目标是冰山抵达阿拉伯海域时，只损失30%的质量
while in transit with the aim of the iceberg only losing 30% of its mass before getting to Arabian waters.
首次测试预计耗资6000万至8000万美元
The first test was predicted to cost 60 to 80 million dollars
整个项目将耗资1亿至1.5亿美元
and the full thing would cost 100 to 150 million.
看看看看，这才是值得我尊敬的牛比事
And you know, that's some shit I could respect.
这听起来可能并非痴人说梦
It sounds like this might not even be a pipe cream
因为就在去年，2022年
because last year in 2022
国家顾问局获得了一项英国专利，用于他们声称能够实现此计划的技术
a patent in the United Kingdom was granted to the National Advisor Bureau for the technology they say will pull this off.
当然，他们不是第一个获得拉冰山技术专利的人
Now, they aren't the first to patent iceberg towing technology.
该技术至少在2008年就有了书面记载
That's at least been in writing since 2008
但国家顾问局很懂怎么炒作自己，而且似乎有巨额资金支持
but this one's talking about itself a lot louder and seems to have dummy money behind it.
我查的资料越多，就越觉得这事能成
The more I read of this, the less crackpot it sounds.
事实证明这项技术有一定基础
It turns out there's some basis for the technology
阿卜杜拉也清楚并正视其可能存在的问题
and Abdullah doesn't seem unaware or delusional towards the problems it might have.
我支持这个愿景
I say the vision.
他希望为家乡带来新的淡水资源，这对于阿联酋来说绝对是件好事
He wants to get fresh sources of water to his home, which the UAE definitely could benefit from.
他说，这能减少他们对海水淡化的依赖
He says it'll lessen how much they have to dissalinate water
从而降低该过程对环境的负面影响
lowering the environmental impact from that process
而且冰山蒸发到大气中的水分还能增加降雨，他说道
and the extra water from icebergs going into the atmosphere could increase rain, he said.
我不知道他说的话里到底有多少真实性
I don't know how true that or any of this is
他可能完全正确，而我也无法证明
like he might be completely right and I wouldn't be able to prove it.
但这个确实听起来蛮好的
But it does sound good
咱就是喜欢听好听的，即便可能是被骗了
and I like the sound in nice things even if I'm being lied to.
哦对了
Oh, and of course,
就像世界上大部分价值数亿美元的大型项目一样
like most a hundred million dollar mega projects in that part of the world
这也是个旅游噱头
it's also a stunt for tourism.
我倒是觉得，如果项目现在就完成了，为了做这期视频我可能真会去一趟
And I mean, yeah, I probably would have gone there for this video if it was done by now.
坐在沙漠里，身后是一座冰山，想想就觉得很帅啊
Sitting on a desert with an iceberg in the background sounds pretty good.
当然，这件事能否实现还有待观察
Still, it remains to be seen if this will even pan out
但我愿意对它的成功持乐观态度
but I'm okay rooting for success
即便这听起来像是最不可能落成的解决方案
even if it sounds like the most impractical way to solve an issue.
你怎么能说给人们提供干净的饮用水不是好事呢
I think giving people drinking water is good.
我很勇敢，我知道
I'm very brave, I know.
接下来的名词我可能念的不对，多多包涵
Butchered name warning, you have been told.
毛利人与南极洲
The Maori in Antarctica
或者说乌伊.特.兰吉奥拉
or Ui-Te-Rangiora
特指一位备受尊敬的波利尼西亚航海家
specifically refers to the much revered Polynesian navigator
据说他早在公元七世纪就发现了南极洲
who was said to have discovered Antarctica in as early as the seventh century.
这比欧洲人第一次涉足这片极南之地还要早了一千多年
That's over a thousand years prior to Europe going on their first middle school field trip to the southern continent.
关于这个话题有很多争论
There's a lot of debate on this subjects
有人声称新西兰的毛利文化与南极洲有着长久的联系
some people claim that the Maori culture from New Zealand has long ties to Antarctica.
他们经常引用有关乌伊.特.兰吉奥拉的一则古老传说
They often cite that Ui-Te-Rangiora has a very old legend of him
传说中他说自己去过一个“多雾、朦胧、黑暗、不见天日
saying he visited a foggy, misty and dark place not seen by the sun,
天被刺穿，完全贫瘠、寸草不生的地方”
where some had pierced the skies and it was completely barren without vegetation.
很多人觉得这说的就是南极
A lot of people assumed this was referring to the South Pole
这描述简直跟南极的现实情况一模一样啊我看
because that is a decent description of the place.
但关于这个的争议也是有一打的
This has been disputed before though.
人们质疑这个翻译有缺陷
People have brought into question the translation being used as flawed
而且原始文献本身也因年代久远和欧洲殖民影响而受损
in that the source material itself has been damaged by time and European influence.
文本中，用“竹芋”这个词来描述兰吉奥拉看到的东西
In the text, the word arrow root was used to describe something that Rangiora saw.
竹芋是一种食物，看起来像面粉或者雪
Arrow root is food that looks kind of powdery and snow-like
所以有人认为他是在描述雪
so some thought he was describing snow
但也有人说，正确的翻译更像是描述
but others say the correct translation is more along the lines of describing
“像竹芋一样的海泡”
sea foam that's like arrow root.
我能找到的唯一其他确凿证据是
The only other solid evidence that I could find
恩德比岛，一座南极次大陆岛
is that on Enderby Island, a sub-antarctic island that's very far down south
在十三或十四世纪有毛利人活动的踪迹
there was proof of maori activity sometime in the 13th or 14th century
所以毛利人确实曾一度非常接近南极大陆
so at some point they did get relatively close to the continent
但没有任何证据表明他们到达了南极大陆本土
but nothing proving they made it all the way there for certain.
总之是个蛮有意思的话题
It's still an interesting discussion regardless.
冰层下隐藏的世界
The hidden world beneath the ice
兜兜转转又回到了之前关于冰川下湖泊中发现生命的话题
circles back to a brief chat about life-founded sub-glacial lakes
尤其是沃斯托克湖
and specifically in Lake Vostok.
就在去年，在南极洲地下1000多英尺处发现了一条巨大的地下河
Just last year, a big-ass underground river over 1,000 feet below Antarctica's service was discovered
里面不仅有生命，而且生机盎然
not to just have life but to be literally teeming with it.
有录像显示，镜头周围到处都是这种像小鱼虾一样的东西
There's footage of tons of these tiny fish rimp looking things swarming around where the camera is
人们给它起名为“隐藏的世界”，因为这条河流如此生机勃勃
and it was called a hidden world for being as active
却直到现在才为人所发现
as it is and only discovered now.
在一个可能从未见过光的地方
Having something down there as complex as actual animals
发现的不是什么单细胞虫豸，而是像真正的动物一样具有复杂构成的生命体
and not just single-celled microbial life in a place where light has probably never been seen
以及一个极其活跃的生态系统，不觉得很酷吗
as well as an incredibly active ecosystem to boot
很符合我对地底世界的想象，要是外太空鱼也是真的就好了
is insanely cool and god I want space fish to be real.
在南极犯罪，就是字面意思啦
Crime in Antarctica is exactly what it sounds like
这也是不大常见的
and it's also really rare.
我们知道，至少在南极
We know that at least the crimes of fighting,
打架、暴力袭击、猥亵
violent assault, and decent exposure
超屌的派对，也就是溜冰（意味深）
first-degree park popping, aka drug use
纵火和谋杀未遂等罪行
arson and attempted murder have for sure
都确确实实的发生过
happened in the South Pole.
还有一些未确认的罪行
There are also a few unconfirmed crimes
有的比已确认的情节轻一点，有的就要恶劣得多了
some better and some worse than what's on the confirmed list.
这些罪行大多数被认为是人们在南极自闭太久而精神失常
Because of most of these crimes is said to usually be a mix between the isolation getting to people and wearing at their brains,
典中典之醉酒犯罪
classic alcoholism
（南极人就爱这么嗯造自己的肝功能）
they're big on liver failure in Antarctica
甚至还有纯无聊导致的
and even just from general boredom.
我想最后两个原因之间是有联系的
I imagine those last two are connected somehow.
咱前面也说过，南极洲很少有人犯罪
Like I said, down that far South, crimes don't happen much
有些罪行，光是考虑要不要做都蠢得冒泡了
and some would just be stupid to even consider doing.
维基百科明确指出不会发生抢劫
The wiki page is very explicit on robberies not happening
抢劫有啥意义我能问问吗
because what would be the point?
钱根本没用，南极也没有什么地方供你消费
Money is useless when there's nothing to buy.
关于在南极犯罪适用哪些法律，也一直存在不少争议
There's also been a decent amount of debate over what laws even apply to crimes committed in Antarctica.
《南极条约》规定
That big Antarctic treaty said
当一个人被指控在南极做了坏事，他将受到本国法律的惩罚
that when a person is accused of prohibited South Pole shenanigans that they are subject to punishment by their home country
可能已经是他们能想出来的最不麻烦的处理方式了
which is probably the least messy way to do it.
我这个冰山图上有一些特定罪行的独立条目
Some specific crimes committed have their own entries on my iceberg chart
不过鉴于南极犯罪已经很罕见了
but since crime is as rare as it is in the South Pole
我想利用这一部分，分享一些我最喜欢、也最啥比的
I wanted to use this section to share some of my favorite and silliest
不会在后面提到的南极犯罪
illegal things done in Antarctica that we won't be covering later.
1959年，在沃斯托克科考站
In 1959, at Vostok Station,
两名俄罗斯科学家正在下棋
two Russian scientists were playing a game of chess.
一个人输了，在竞技游戏中再常见不过了
One of them lost as often happens on competitive games
但bro输了之后直接勃然大怒
and that dude also lost his shit.
这是我见过输了游戏之后最能发火的人
In the worst game of rage I've ever seen
他试图用一把冰镐攻击自己的对手
he tried to attack a guy who beat him with an ice axe.
一些消息来源说他在棋盘外把那人击败了
Some sources say he killed the guy
我是觉得有点扯淡，当然我很懂你们XBox玩家有多想真人快打让你输了游戏的人
but I'd think most of the accounts agree that he didn't get an Xbox user's greatest wish
但无论结局如何
but either way it ended
苏联因此而规定，所有的科考站全面禁止下棋
it somehow led to a complete ban of playing chess at every Soviet research station
肯定是爱玩游戏导致他们这样的，绝对不是因为工作人员都闲出屁来了
because the game was definitely the issue here, not the lack of things to do.
禁止最能让大伙津津乐道消遣，当然不会让情况变得更糟
Removing one of their most stimulating pastime certainly won't make this worse.
我想说的另一件事也和俄罗斯人有关
The other one I want to mention was also Russian
这件事发生在2018年10月
and was in October 2018
谢尔盖·萨维茨基刺伤了奥列格·巴拉格扎姆
where Sergei Savitsky stabbed one Oleg Balagazam
这还不是南极洲发生的第一起持刀伤人事件
and what is somehow not the first stab wound given in the South Pole.
这件事的有趣之处在于，根据不同人的说法
What makes it funny is all the different ways the camel's back
压垮骆驼的最后一根稻草各不相同
is said to have brokendepending on who you ask.
这两个人在一起工作了大约六个月
These guys worked together for around six months straight
萨维茨基持刀伤人的时候喝大了，情绪有点鸡冻
and Savitsky was definitely drunk in having an emotional breakdown
据说他情绪失控的原因
at the time of attempted puncture wound.
要么是因为奥列格拿他打趣，让他像脱衣舞娘一样在桌子上跳舞赚钱
It said he either snapped because of Oleg teasing and telling him to dance on top of the table for money like a stripper
这笑话是有点蠢，毕竟你在南极洲要钱有啥用呢
which is a dumb suggestion because money's useless down there.
但更有趣的说法是，奥列格似乎一直在剧透
But the funnier one is that Oleg apparently kept spoiling
萨维茨基从科考站图书馆借来的书
the endings of books that Savitsky was reading from the station library
这才是他被捅的原因
and that's what got him shanked.
我说白了，要是有人提前告诉我蟑螂的《UTOPIA》都有谁feat了
Listen, I would have done the same thing to someone
那我也会不吝对他们痛下杀手的
if they spoiled the features on Utopia for me.
不过故事的结局相当的正能量啊
This case did have a relatively happy ending though.
萨维茨基毫不反抗地飞回俄罗斯，认罪认罚
Savitsky flew back to Russia without resistance where he accepted guilt
并接受了刑事处罚而非康复治疗
and to take criminal punishment over rehabilitation.
他显然对此感到很懊悔
He apparently felt pretty bad about it.
奥列格可能也体会到了冰雪侵蚀大脑的感觉
Oleg must have empathized with the feeling of ice rotting his mind too
他的态度就是
because he was like
“哥们你都这样了那我还说啥了，直接给你捅不完了”
man, shit happens, it's whatever.
由于奥列格选择不再追究，所以这起案件被撤销了
In the case was dropped because Oleg chose not to press charges any further.
我想他的想法可能是：“要是换个日子
I imagine his thought process was something like out of different day.
被插插的可能就是他了”
I could have been stabbing him.
you can lick the iceberg's toes here on layer 4
这层啊，这层是冰山图的玉足
down here it's a cold cold world
这里的词条，全都冰冷而小众
Rodney Marks was an Australian astrophysicist
有个天体物理学家，叫罗德尼·马克斯
who died in Antarctica in may 2000
2000年5月，他死在南极洲
and what is potentially the South Pole's first and only case of murder
这可能是迄今为止，南极洲唯一的谋杀案
mosquito net because I don't want to die again
这头套帅吧，我怕被蚊子杀害
阿拉斯加的蚊子贼大贼凶，会吃人，是当地的州鸟
he started feeling sick on may 11
最开始，是在5月11日
at the Admusen-Scott South Pole station
在阿蒙森-斯科特南极站
while walking between the observatory and base
从观测站回来的路上，他觉得有点难受
while getting sicker and sicker over the next 36 hours
接下来，他的症状越来越恶化
until dying the day after
然后一天半就死了
there wasn't a great way to get Mark's body off of Antarctica
当时是冬天，没办法把他运出南极洲
until the end of the winter
so they legit just stuffed his body in the freezer for 6 months
大伙都没招了，只能把尸体塞进冰箱，冻了6个月
until he could be flown to New Zealand to get his body autopsied
开春后，才把尸体空运到新西兰，去做尸检
the examination found that Mark died of methanol poisoning
结果表明，马克斯死于甲醇中毒
but the issue was no one knew if he did it to himself
但问题是，他到底是自己喝了假酒
or if someone else had done it to him
还是被别人下了毒?
and in either case if he had been killed on purpose
还有就是，这到底是不是意外?
suicide was considered the least likely option
自杀的可能性，首先就被排除了
hence the first South Pole murder title
毕竟标题里都说了，这是谋杀
most don't think he ingested methanol on purpose
大家都觉得，他不会自己喝甲醇
since he was not believed to be suicidal
因为他没有自杀倾向
and actively sought treatment for how ill he was feeling before passing
而且觉得不舒服后，他还主动去找了医生
they had plenty of booze on the station already
要是想喝醉，营地里存了很多酒
if the idea was to get a high
没必要整这玩意
the Christchurch police cited Raytheon and the National Science Foundation
基督城警方指出，雷神公司和美国国家科学基金会（NSF）
as being uncooperative
不主动配合调查
with DSS Wormald saying
沃莫尔德警官说
I suspect there have been people
我怀疑，有些人害怕影响自己的前途
who have thought twice about making contact with us
on the basis of their future employment position
不敢主动跟警方联系
reportedly the US Department of justice
据说就连美国司法部，也被这两家机构无视
didn't get any answers from the two groups either
which made it seem like they'd just been denied jurisdiction
他们直接拒绝了司法部的管辖权
there's probably some important info missing
现在流出的信息很少
but with what we have
但据我所知
these are the main ways
关于马克斯的死因
people think Rodney may have been poisoned
大家目前有如下猜测
methanol can enter the body in a number of ways
甲醇进入人体的途径有很多
and there was methanol in the solvent
马克斯用来擦望远镜的洗液里，确实有甲醇成分
that Rodney was using to clean telescopes
but in Mark's case
但事实是
a pathologist said that he almost definitely ingested the poison
一位法医说，从体内查出的甲醇浓度来看
because of how much was in his system
他肯定是直接喝下去的
the four common sense possibilities are
于是就有了四种推测
he took it on purpose to get high
他故意喝假酒，想灌醉自己
he took it on purpose to end his life
他故意喝假酒，想弄死自己
He took it accidentally and died
他不小心喝了假酒，死了
or someone gave it to him on purpose
要么是有人让他喝假酒
either as some kind of prank
可能是个神人，要么是想逗他一下
to get him sick for whatever reason
or intending to kill him from the very start
要么就是本来就想害死他
these are mostly self explanatory
这些理论都很好理解
but there's context for the self inflicted accident theory
不过，关于"意外自伤"理论，要补充一点背景
despite alcohol being pretty accessible in the South Hole
虽然说在南鸡，酒不是什么稀罕东西
folks in Antarctica love liver failure
但当地人 都想速通肝衰竭
they were still known to mix their own concoctions together
他们会自己动手，把酒水混起来喝
in what was called Toast Juice
这种自制酒，叫"吐司汁"
Rodney may have used methanol in a mixture on accident
马克斯在调酒时，可能误用了甲醇
because of a mislabeled bottle
也许是标签贴错了
or just not checking it too thoroughly
要么就是他本人太马虎
and if there was a mislabeled bottle
但如果标签贴错了
the question is whose screw up was it
那我要问，标签是谁贴错的?
again apparently the investigation was
情况依然很复杂，雷神公司和NSF不愿配合调查
very rocky with the NSF and Raytheon
as well as the crew at the station
科考站里的其他人，都是那两家机构的员工
employed by those two groups mind you
supposedly not working very openly with the police either
他们也不愿向警方透露太多信息
as it stands a lot of people say Rodney wasn't suicidal
于是很多人觉得，罗德尼不可能自杀
and was smart enough to know better than  to make his own alcohol
脑子也没那么笨，不会自己去酿酒喝
leaving murder as the most likely option for some
那剩下的可能，就只有谋杀了
his death was never solved
他的死因至今不明
and remains as a classic Unsolved Mysteries podcast episode topic
这事情成了悬案，成了那种"未解之谜"播客的话题
The USS Nautilus was the first operational nuclear powered submarine
USS鹦鹉螺号，是世界上第一艘核潜艇
and also the first sub to swim under the North Pole
也是第一艘抵达北极点的潜艇
managing to swim across the whole thing from beneath it
它从水下，跨越了整个北极
imagine being on that sub
想象一下那个场景
and that's how you find out The North Pole is actually
你发现，北极根本没有陆地
just a floating chunk of ice and not a solid landmass
只有那种全是冰的冰块
oh my god I can see the bottom I didn't know it had one
哎我草，北极居然有底盖，以前没听说啊
the Nautilus was commissioned in 1951
鹦鹉螺号 立项于1951年
began construction the year after
第二年开始建造，并于1954年下水
and was first launched in 1954
but it didn't give the North Pole a scratch on its Tate until 1958
不过直到1958年，“阳光行动”正式启动后
when Operation Sunshine first took place
鹦鹉螺号才窜访北极
after the Soviet satellite Sputnik was launched
苏联发射第一颗人造卫星后
there was a lot of fear
美国人担心，苏联能通过人造卫星，协调洲际弹道导弹
that Sputnik might be able to reach the mainland with ICBMs
or intercontinental ballistic missiles
打击美国本土
so in response
作为回应
President Eisenhower with his weird alien looking face
埃森豪威尔总统，就顶着那张比脸
ordered the Navy to give a go at sliding under the North Pole
命令美国海军，从水下穿越北极
as a sort of proof of concept
以此来验证项目的可行性，项目名叫SLBM
for the then in development SLBM program
submarine launched ballistic missiles
全称"潜射弹道导弹“
they gave it a go in June that year
当年六月，潜艇首次出发
but the ice was too thick in shallower waters
但当时，浅水区的冰层太厚
where they couldn't just dive deeper to avoid the ice
潜艇的潜深不够，没法绕过冰层
so the Nautilus went back to Pearl Harbor
于是只好耻辱返航，回珍珠港，等七月再出发
with its tail tucked between its legs to shamefully wait until July
you know like a loser
没办法，只能忍辱负重，等冰层化冻
until the ice conditions were better
it became the first watercraft to reach the North Pole on August 3
8月3日，鹦鹉螺号成功抵达北极点
but four days after first going under
它在水下待了4天
and over 1800 miles later spent entirely under the ice
还在冰层下面，潜航了将近3000公里
like I wish I could be right now
我都有点羡慕它了
all made possible by new navigation tech
得益于全新的导航技术
the Nautilus had the balls to show her face again after what she did
鹦鹉螺号才能从下面，看光了北极的底裤，然后抵达格陵兰岛
and made it to Greenland
at which point it became the first sub
于是，它成了有史以来
to swim all the way under the ice of the North Pole
第一艘完全从冰层下穿越北极的潜航器
to get out the other side
Project Cold Feet was a CIA operation in 1962
"冰冷玉足"行动，始于1962年，是个CIA秘密行动
its aim was to lift some secret info
由于冰层情况变动
off an abandoned Soviet Arctic ice station
苏联遗弃了一座北极科考站
that had been left behind because of unstable ice
CIA想去那里，搜索情报
America had recently developed tech
当时，美国发明了一项技术
that let them track Soviet submarines
可以追踪苏联的潜艇
and they were paranoid that the Soviets had made similar tech
他们怀疑，苏联可能也有类似的技术
but they had no proof
但他们没有证据
so they wanted to see if this now empty station
所以，他们想去那个废弃站点
had the Lego studs they were looking for
看看苏联人，有没有留下小零食
it was a pain in the ass to pull off
我只能说，那次行动很困难
I would know I was there
当时我就在现场
the station itself was near impossible to get to
那座站点，本身就非常难以抵达
the ice itself was already rickety as a seesaw
冰层七扭八歪，就像拼图一样
the ice was too deep into an ice pack
而且站点建在冰盖深处
for an icebreaker ship to reach
破冰船难以抵达现场
and it was outside of helicopter range
直升机的航程也不够
because all of these options were like not options at all
既然以上选项，都完全不可行
this was the first time the Fulton surface to air recovery system
美国人搬出了新东西：富尔顿地对空回收系统
was used on an operation
it had been entirely theoretical
这是一种试验技术，从来没实际运用过
and only used in trials up till then
in less big words that I only Learned just now
我刚查了一下，这玩意其实没那么复杂
it's a fucking skyhook
这就是个"天钩"
it's the shit Christian Bale escaped Hong Kong with in The Dark Knight
《黑暗骑士》里，蝙蝠侠就是用它逃出香港的
that was based off a real thing
其实，这类电影里的道具
like most gadgets in those movies were
大多都是有现实原型的
and the first time they actually used this
这种炫酷的科技，第一次实际运用
incredible piece of human ingenuity
was to get to an ice shack
是去钩一个冰上小屋
not very glamorous
听着是不太光彩
it sounds nuts in concept
虽然看起来很疯狂
but the operation itself was a complete success
但行动本身，其实大获成功
a few operatives parachuted down to the drift station
通过空降，两位特工抵达了站点
found the equipment and information they were looking for
找到了相关的机密材料和情报
and got pulled out of there on a skyhook
然后用天钩，顺利进行了三次回收
over the course of three trips
one for the info
先回收资料
and one for each of the operatives who went in initially
然后分两次，回收了两位特工
everything went close to plan from what I understand
在我看来，一切都是按计划进行的
and they found the exact evidence they were looking for
他们也确实找到了关键的证据
and yeah it turns out the Soviets were developing  means
没错，苏联的确在研发相关技术
to detect Us submarines under the ice
用于探测美国的冰下潜艇
The Arctic Harvester is a concept proposed for a floating structure
"北极收割机"是一种概念性的浮动结构
that can house a community of some 800 people
其间可以容纳大约800人居住
it was designed to float in open waters near Greenland for its functionality
根据构想，这个东西要在格陵兰岛附近漂浮
like over there or some shit
就我背后这个鬼地方
it won the innovation in architecture for the sea award
在2013年，雅克·鲁热里国际建筑设计竞赛中
in the Jacques Rougerie Foundation
International Architecture Competition in 2013
这玩意得了个“海洋建筑创新奖”
you see Greenland is very reliant on imports for their agricultural needs
大家知道，格陵兰农业不发达，农产品全靠进口
and the Arctic Harvester was trying to cover those needs
而"北极收割机"，希望以能被复制的方式
in a way that could be hopefully replicated at scale
满足格陵兰的农产品需求
the images they used as concept photos look like dogshit
这个项目的概念渲染图，就是纯纯的狗屎
even by dogshit concept photo standards
而且是狗屎中的极品狗屎
but the device itself is pretty neat
但设计本身，却还算精巧
the harvester is built in a circular shape that open on the inside
这东西是个环形结构，内部是开放的
where there's a central bay
外面有个入口，冰山从这里运进去
where icebergs are meant to be delivered
for freshwater harvesting and as a reusable resource
然后融化成淡水，供其中居民使用
it goes fairly deep underwater
它的水下结构很庞大
and looks like under the surface
而水下的部分，正是"北极收割机"的居民区
is where a decent part of the inhabitants would actually be staying
which is kind of like an iceberg
就有点像冰山，大部分都在水下嘛
since they're mostly underwater
I hope I don't get obliterated by the ones they pull into the city
希望我不会被拖进来的冰山创死吧
Pobeda Ice Island is an ice island and
胜利岛是一座冰山岛屿
kind of a tabular iceberg off the coast of East Antarctica
也可以说是平顶冰山吧，它位于南极东岸
that only exists when it feels like it
而且它经常会消失
it's a weird mix of things so let me try to explain
听起来是有点怪，但且听我解释
Pablo was first discovered by the United States in February 1840
1840年2月，美国探险队发现了胜利岛
because it was blocking an expedition  by Charles Wilkes
它挡住了查尔斯·威克斯的船队
he called the place Termination Land
因为它挡住了航道，查尔斯管它叫"终末地"
because it stopped his journey short
and that's what the name should have stayed as
本来，这名字就这么定了
though this dude Douglas Mawson changed it
但后来，有个叫道格拉斯的哥们
to Termination Ice Tongue
给它改名"终焉冰舌"
which is at least equally as sick as Termination Land
不是哥们，名字都这么狠的吗?
but a Soviet expedition on the island over 100 years later
结果呢，100多年后，来了个苏联探险队
gave it its current name
改称它为"胜利岛"
and was the site of one of those temporary research stations
他们还在当地，建立了一座临时科考站
that we went over earlier
weirdly this thing only exists sometimes before straight up vanishing
奇怪的是，这座岛会周期性地消失
it's a cycle that's repeated since we first realized
直到今天，这个循环都在反复上演
it was happening at all
it shows up when a new iceberg
附近的登曼冰川，会不定期地崩解
splits off from the nearby Denman Glacier
where eventually this big white brick
崩下来一大块又白又纯的冰
that somehow isn't cocaine
真冰，大家别乱猜啊
Pusha T botz on Twitter eat your heart out
不是 Pusha T 那种冰
drips along until it beaches on a shoal
然后这块大冰，搁浅在冰川北面的浅滩上
that is north of the ice shelf
an iceberg big enough to do this
这种规模的冰盖
apparently only comes around every 40 to 50 years
每隔四五十年，才会崩落一次
the iceberg can get stuck there for a decade or even longer
这块冰会在浅滩上，停留十多年
until it's been worn away enough to unload from where it ran aground
慢慢地融化，最后重新滑进海里
according to the first link on Google the dimensions vary
谷歌上面说，胜利岛的尺寸会变化
but it's usually 43 by 22 miles
最长大约70公里，最宽大约35公里
at its longest and widest points
with an area of around 579 square miles
总面积大约有1500平方公里
it's a shame it's not called Terminator Land today
真可惜，它现在不叫"终末地"了
like I could make a lot of AI jokes here
虽然有股AI味，但这名字真潮的呀
but it just sounds cooler
Oumuamua was the first interstellar object
奥陌陌是第一颗闯入太阳系的星际天体
or a thing in space not attached to the gravity of a star
它在宇宙中漂浮，没有被任何天体捕获
that passed through our solar system
只是路过了太阳系
when it first showed up
它出现时，大家都在猜这是什么东西
there was a lot of speculation on what it was
things from a special kind of comet
从特殊的彗星，一直猜到外星人飞行器
to advanced alien technology
which I actually understand for once
其实这也算有情可原
cause it was moving in a way that  gravity would not have caused
因为只靠天体引力，无法解释它独特的轨道
so some folks started thinking that something with intention
所以有人猜测，它会这样运动
forced that rock to blast off the way it did
是受了什么东西的操控
based on where it was and how fast it was moving among other things
依据这颗天体的位置，以及它的超高速度
scientists determined that this big rock was
科学家推测，它应该是某种物质冻成的冰
a solid mass of frozen something
and the only kind of ice they said explained its properties was hydrogen
根据其特质，其唯一可能的成分，就是固态氢
raw hydrogen only freezes into ice
只有在绝对零度附近，氢才会凝结成固态
when temperatures are slightly above absolute zero
and it doesn't give off or reflect light when burning up
而且它受热时，既不发光，也不反光
so there would be no streak for a telescope to catch while viewing it
所以只靠望远镜，很难捕捉到这颗天体
and since we've seen one dark hydrogen iceberg
既然我们发现了一颗"暗氢冰山"
that is what they're actually called
这玩意真叫这名字
that means there are likely tons of these things
这意味着，宇宙里有无数这种东西
all over the place in space
listen Darryl Seligman from the university of Chicago
听好，芝加哥大学有个达里尔教授
called these things dark hydrogen icebergs before I did
是他先管这玩意叫"暗氢冰山"的
it wasn't like an ass pull I did
真不是我为了节目效果，把它硬凑进图里的
for some in universe game lore okay
the name is really metal and has iceberg in it
毕竟名字这么潮酷，还是个"冰山"
which is enough of a reason to get it on the chart by itself
这谁能忍住，不把它放进冰山图啊
but apparently the conditions for these big phantom black space
需要满足非常严苛的条件，才会产生这种黯淡的巨大天体
breaks to form are also incredibly rare
at least the type specifically that we thought was
它就像那种宇宙里的冰山美人，漂亮得过分
pretty from across the cosmos
but we're too scared to talk to
但大家都不敢去搭话
they're formed in nebulae
它诞生于星云中
the cores of these clouds in space where stars are born
这种星际尘埃，也是恒星的发源地
think that pillars of creation photo
大家知道"创生之柱"吗?
yeah yeah that's where a star will probably get made eventually
对，恒星就是在这种地方诞生的
and that's also where these shadow realm
那颗黯淡的宇宙冰山，也是从星云飘来的
spacebergs probably come from
a type of iceberg that gets made when a star is born
想想吧，这种冰山是与恒星一起诞生的
man I'm sorry
哎哟我，不赖
but my iceberg chart was foretold in the stars yours wasn't
我的冰山图里有宇宙天体，你的没有
Operation Iceberg was the codename for the battle of Okinawa
冲绳岛战役，代号叫“冰山行动”
between the United States and Imperial Japan
这是二战期间，美日两军的最后一场大型战役
towards the end of World War II
the name's a little dumb to me personally like
我个人觉得，这个代号是有点蠢
this is the wrong ocean and battlefront of the war for that name
毕竟你俩打架的地方，也不会有冰山啊
it sounds like some shit they would have come up with
光听这个代号，你都会觉得这场战役
if they were trying to run up on
I don't know Greenland for some reason
是要入侵格陵兰岛呢
which they did at some point
格陵兰还真参战了
and I mean we have tried to buy that
其实，买格陵兰岛这事儿
place from Denmark multiple times
美国动过好几次念头
including recently
最近都有一次呢
so it's not like there isn't historical precedent for invasion
美国入侵格陵兰，也算自古以来了
it just depends how goofy the Pentagon's feeling on a given day
至于今天动不动手，全凭五角大楼心情
Kaffeklubben or Coffee Club Island
科斐克拉本，意思是"咖啡俱乐部"
is an uninhabited piece of land
是一座位于格陵兰北端的无人小岛
on the northern tip of Greenland
it was discovered in 1900 by an American explorer
该岛被美国探险家于1900年首次发现
but no one set foot there until Danish explorer Lauge Koch
但第一次登岛的是个丹麦人，叫达·刁
or large cock stood up on the island
这位达刁哥，狂暴轰入了小岛
it's a little under 450 miles from the North Pole
这座岛距北极点大约700公里
and is the farthest northern point of land
经过一番争议，大家一致认定
outside of the North Pole that is undisputed
这座岛是地球上最北端的陆地
stealing the title in 1969 from Cape Morris Jesup
1969年之前，最北陆地还是“莫里斯杰塞普”角
the reason it's the undisputed most northern point
之所以会有这种争议
is because there's a big argument
是因为大家不清楚
about what even counts as a piece of land in this case
到底怎样，才能算得上是"陆地"
the wiki page for that type barely explains it
维基词条里，也写得含糊其辞
because there's no clear consensus
直到目前都没有共识
they just have a chart of what might be
所以维基上列了个表，里面是各种有争议的最北陆地
the most northern points in the world
a lot of these issues come from not knowing
其中大部分争议点，在于人们不知道这些"陆地"
if the places cited as farthest north
are permanent plots of land
到底是永久存在的，还是会随时消失
or will disintegrate any day now
like banks that are currently visible can be destroyed
就好比，河岸随时有可能变道
ice sheets might move
冰盖会移动
oceans and storms can shift these things around
洋流和风暴，会带着海冰漂浮
the point is places that are thought to be the newest most northern point
正因如此，那些比咖啡俱乐部岛，更靠北的"陆地"
have a lot of argument if those actually count as land
在很多人眼里，其实算不上陆地
whereas Coffee Club Island is
而咖啡俱乐部岛，最起码是个公认的永久性陆地
at least confirmed to be a permanent landmass
in the farthest north of any of the places
而且在所有陆地中，它还是最靠北的
that are confirmed to be so so
it's undisputed
没有争议哈
the US CGC Eastwind was an icebreaker ship
美国海警东风号，是一艘破冰船
built for the US  Coast Guard
隶属于海岸警卫队
it was built in time to be drafted into the military
最开始，它是要投入军事行动的
and saw service around the Second World War
二战期间，它参与了冰山巷的任务
where she got active in Iceberg Alley
remember what I said
还记得吧，二战时我们打过格陵兰
we ran up on Greenland in World War II
well this was when
就是它这次
the Eastwind ferried some 200 US ships to victory
当时，东风号搭载200名美军士兵
taking over the last German weather station in Greenland
攻下了格陵兰最后一座德军气象站
after the war
二战后
the ship was used in Antarctic exploration in the 50s
东风号参与了50年代的"深冻行动"
as part of Operation Deep Freeze
前往南极探险
which again is the name for American operations in the South Pole
这个"深冻行动"，就是之前提到的美国南极项目
as part part of this research
为了科研行动
the East Wind set sail from Boston in October 1960
1960年10月，东风号离开了波士顿
which I definitely understand
我能理解它这么做
I'd try to get as far away from there as possible too
波士顿那种鬼地方，谁愿待啊
but then she sailed through the Panama Canal
但随后，它穿越巴拿马运河
across the Pacific
横渡太平洋
visited New Zealand and the Mcmurdo Sound
窜访了新西兰和麦克摩多湾
sailed across the Indian Ocean
然后横跨印度洋
passed through the Suez Canal
穿越苏伊士运河
crossed the Mediterranean Sea
然后穿越地中海
and then finally sailed across the Atlantic Ocean after all of that
最后，再简简单单横渡个大西洋
making it home in 1961
1961年荣归故里
no idea why you try that hard to go back to Boston
不是，你费那么大劲儿，回波士顿干嘛
this made her the first cutter ship
于是，它成了第一艘环球航行的执法船
meaning government vessel in this case
to circumnavigate the globe
因为它属于海警嘛
two mountains in Antarctica
南极有两座山
were named after the captains who helmed the journey
是以当时的东风号船长命名的
Mountain Naab and Mount Schmidtman
纳布山和施密特山
where Schmidtman is one of the easiest things to make fun
看过《刀剑神域》吐槽版的，听到"施密特"
《刀剑神域》吐槽版是个抽象二创，施密特是其中的谐星人物
著名台词是“可我还有老婆孩子啊！”
of for SAO Abridged watchers
可能就开始笑了
the Eastwind did some more work for Operation Deep Freeze after that
此次行动后，东风号继续参与"深冻行动"
until she was decommissioned in 1968
它一直服役到1968年
nuclear fallout in glaciers is pretty straight forward
冰川里的核辐射，顾名思义
some very special and lucky waters out there
有一些福运当头的冰川水
got irradiated before freezing into ice
在冻成冰前，先吸收了核辐射
radiation was found not just in the poles
不光是南北极有辐射冰川
but in at least 17 different glaciers
2011年的检测发现，至少有17座冰川
that were being tested for it in 2011
where they all had higher levels of radiation
会释放出超过常规的辐射量
than they should have
the radioactive waste mostly came from early days
这种辐射的来源，大多是早年的核武器试验
nuclear weapons testing
when setting off bombs
那时候，丢个核弹
and dumping radioactive waste into open water like dry spaghetti
或者往海洋里，倾倒点核废料啥的
was a national pastime
是很平常的事情
nuclear weapons testing can slingshot
核武器试验后，放射性物质
radioactive material up to 50 miles in the air
可以覆盖到周边80公里远
and the less heavy lighter materials will over time
随着时间推移，那些较轻的颗粒
settle back down on Earth's surface from rain
会融进雨水，降落到地表
and some of that water will freeze over while contaminated
这些核污染水，随后冻成了冰川
part of the radiation was attributed to Chernobyl
核污染的来源，包括切尔诺贝利和福岛事故
and the Fukushima disasters
but most was from weapons testing
但主要来源，还是武器试验
for instance in 1963
比如，在1963年
there was a very noticeable spike in nuclear activity
冰川辐射有一个明显峰值
which lines up with a period of time
而恰恰就在这一时期
where nuke testing was ramping up again
全球进行了密集的核试验
to quote a scientist
有一位科学家说
they are some of the highest radiation levels
这是在自然环境里，最高级别的辐射
you see in the environment
outside nuclear exclusion zones
其辐射剂量，仅次于核禁区
very comforting
哎哟我
the main concern for us is that
大家都在担心的是
with glaciers speed running their melt records
现在冰川都在光速融化
the radioactivity in them
那么，我们的淡水和海洋，会不会被污染？
might leak back into our water supplies and our oceans
could poison ocean life
万一海水有辐射
meaning our source of food
那海鲜还能吃吗?
or at the very least the source of food for our food
整条海洋食物链，是不是都要被污染?
down the line it will probably work its way back into
如果这样，那人类肯定也是会吃掉辐射的
human consumption somewhere
that's if we don't just get exposed to it directly
我们还会暴露在更多辐射中
because there will just now
毕竟，水体的放射性正在不断提高
be more nuclear waste than water from now on
but there's good news
但咱先别慌
it'll probably mostly happen in the global south
因为先遭殃的，是全球南方国家
and bad stuff is okay
众所周知，南方的事
as long as it happens below the equator
跟我们发达国家无关
the flies can smell the sarcasm
哎呦这堆苍蝇啊，它们知道我在说垃圾话
that's why they're running around me
diseases in glaciers are exactly that
冰川病毒，也是同样的道理
viruses pathogens and other slimy words
病毒啦，病原体啦，那些坏东西
that were frozen in ice millennia ago
被冻在万年冰川里，封存至今
and remain there today
the main fear is again that
同样，大家担心冰川融化后
with more and more ice melting
some of these diseases that are thousands of years old
那些有数千年历史的，我们尚未免疫的远古疾病
that we have no direct immunity for
and have shown the ability to survive for ages while in ice
会从万古沉睡中破冰归来，给人类带来灾难
could potentially come back and be the catalyst
or the next pandemic
造成下一场叮咚鸡
or at the very least
或者给人类带来另一种疾病
infect people they wouldn't have otherwise
there's precedent for this too
还真发生过这种事情
in just 2016
就在2016年
there was an anthrax outbreak in Siberia
西伯利亚的冻土融化，导致了一场炭疽疫情
due to permafrost melting
and exposing an infected deer corpse to the open air
当地的鹿尸解冻后，释放了炭疽孢子
the last outbreak of the disease in that area was
该地区上一次爆发炭疽，还是在1941年
all the way back in 1941
but to be fair
尽管如此
at least a little bit of the whole
有一些古代疾病爆发，是人类自己造成的
reviving ancient disease thing is our fault
scientists found what they called an untouched giant virus
科学家在3万年前的古代冰层中
that was 30000 years old
发现了一种"未接触巨病毒"
when discovered under the ice
it was one of the largest viruses ever found
这种病毒非常巨大
and researchers say that it is surprisingly complex
而且据研究，它的结构也相当复杂
HIV for instance only has 12 genes
HIV病毒，只有12个基因
where this thing had 500 genes
而这玩意有500个基因
other even bigger giant viruses
也有更大的巨病毒，有多达2050个基因
have been found with up to 2050 genes
and of course one of the first things scientists did
不出所料，那些科学家们
was bring the virus back to life
马上把这玩意复活了
something that is well known for going smoothly every time
哎呀梅事的，不会疣问题的好吧
okay I'm fear mongering here
好吧，是我危言耸听了
these guys aren't idiots
科学家不是傻逼
and they did do it in a controlled setting
他们知道要做实验防护
in fact they were very specific
其实他们很谨慎
that they tested in a closed environment on an Obama as bait
只在封闭环境中，在阿米巴虫上做了实验
and immediately verified that it couldn't infect
结果立刻发现，这种病毒感染不了人或动物
animal or human cells
it's not supposed to be dangerous to us
所以，它应该没有危险
but I'm sure I had you going for at least a second there
刚刚我是不是把大家唬住了?
we'll see if I can have you going any further
走着瞧吧，这视频还长
as this research progresses and becomes scarier
后面还有更多更哈人的内容
icebergs in Lake Michigan refers to pictures of striped
密歇根湖冰山，是一张条纹冰山的照片
multi colored icebergs
said to be taken at Lake Michigan
据说拍摄于密歇根湖
this picture is real and very cool
这张炫酷的照片不是P的
but it was actually taken near Antarctica
只不过它拍摄于南极附近
that on its own would make this a very short entry
这词条就这样，没什么特别的
but I kept it in because it is relevant to icebergs
但它毕竟是冰山，所以我保留了它
but also as an excuse
还有一个原因就是
well searching I found multiple ice slash cold stuff related stories
我查资料时发现，有许多跟冰相关的潮酷故事
that were coincidentally all from Michigan
不知为啥，全都发生在密歇根
so you get to hear about a few of these as bonuses
所以我要讲个关于密歇根的故事
The Great Michigan Pizza Funeral
伟大的密歇根披萨葬礼
is one of the funniest names for something ever thought of
能想出这个名字，真的是有点神人了
in 1973
在1973年
pizza manufacturer Mario Fabriani was told by the FDA
有个叫马里奥的披萨商，接到FDA通知
he had to murder metric shit tons of his frozen pizza
说他有几吨冷冻披萨，必须得销毁掉
because they detect did botulism causing bacteria
因为他使用的一批蘑菇罐头
and a batch of canned mushrooms that he had used on his pies
被FDA检测出了肉毒杆菌
botulism is the stuff used in Botox but
就是肉毒针里的那个杆菌
unrefined and unregulated
只不过未经提纯处理
it's like one of the most potent neurotoxins known to man
是最危险的蛋白质神经毒素之一
and it can paralyze your whole body
甚至会导致全身瘫痪
on March 1973
1973年3月
Mario held a funeral where he very dramatically buried
马里奥选了个良辰吉日，举办了风光大葬
29 188 frozen cheese and mushroom pizzas
埋下了29188个奶酪芝士披萨
the hole was 18 feet deep
墓坑深达5.5米
so it was like having a funeral for three of your loved ones
相当于你家亲戚，同时死了三个
who died at the same time
才会挖这么大坑
there was a live audience at the service
葬礼现场，来了很多观众
and the fucking governor of Michigan spoke at the event
连你妈密歇根的领导，都来发表讲话
like whose side is the government on
不是领导，你支持哪边啊?
well states rights I suppose
扶持小微企业是吧
all that just for the FDA to find out
葬礼后，FDA才发现
those shrooms didn't even have botulism
那批蘑菇罐头里，根本就没有肉毒杆菌
causing bacteria in them
so Forbrini sued his suppliers getting 211 thousand dollars  out of it
于是马里奥起诉了供应商，结果获赔21.1万美元
in 1979 money
是1979年的美元哦
if he wasn't set from then on
要是这样还没缓过来，那就是他自己的原因了
it's kind of his own fault at that point
unless he had outside circumstances affect him
除非他也是大环境不好
in which case I'm empathetic to his hardships
如果这样，那我也只能表示同情
the 2008 housing crisis was hard on us all
大家都经历过2008年
I lost millions in the stock market at the age of 8
我当年8岁，股票亏了大几百万
the Little Traverse Bay Crucifix is very specifically
小特拉弗湾十字架，是唯一沉在淡水湖中的十字架
the only known underwater freshwater crucifix
and it's at the bottom of Traverse Bay in Michigan
位于小特拉弗斯湾湖底
not for long bitch watch me do one too
这有啥好唯一的，我请问呢
it's also a tourist attraction
它还是个热门景点呢
I know why it is
这倒也合理
but the circumstances for that reason
但我想不明白，到底是什么样的神人
to even exist and make sense
is the confusing part to me
才会构思出这种景点
if you're wondering why it's there at all
想必大家也很疑惑
the story is about as scuffed and somehow
但其实，它背后是个既抽象
at the same time tragic as you'd expect
同时又有点悲伤的故事
in 1956 Gerald Schnappinsky a 15 year old boy
1956年，有个叫杰洛特的15岁小孩哥
was accidentally killed by a shotgun
在自家农场里，被霰弹枪误杀了
on his family's farm
this crucifix was commissioned and crafted in Italy
于是他家人从意大利，订购了这座十字架
in memory of Gerald
来悼念杰洛特
but they didn't write fragile
但可惜快递时，包裹上没写"小心轻放"
this side up on the shipping container
and it broke when it was in transit across  the Atlantic
结果运输过程中，十字架摔碎了
so the family turned it down for that damage
于是，那家人拒签了快递
it was sold at an insurance sale after that
后来，在一次保险拍卖会上
and picked up by a diving club
它被一个潜水团体买下了
who thought let's put this at the bottom of a lake
那帮人说，我们把它沉湖里吧
that seems like a good idea
这肯定是个好主意
and yeah it was they were right
结果呢，这主意确实不错
the crucifix was a big draw
十字架沉入湖底后，马上就成了热门景点
even when it first got put down there
the Drowning Jesus ceremony
这个溺水的耶稣，引来了大批游客
brought onlookers from the very start
and has had frequent seasonal tourist trips to view the crucifix
一到冬天，都会有游客来参观十字架
and every year since
年年如此
after some time of being submerged
十字架沉入湖底几年后
it was taken out of the lake
人们又把它捞出来
to try and salvage the parts of the original
经过一番修复，补好了当初损坏的地方
withering and damaged statue
the cross was repaired
十字架修好了
and then the new Frankenstein crucifix
那个打着补丁的耶稣，重新沉入湖底
was put in the bag
unfortunately
可惜的是
the site hasn't been visited since before the pandemic
叮咚鸡之后，就没人来这里观光了
as the tour relies on the lake ice
因为要去看水下十字架
to freeze thickly enough to stand on
冰面必须能站住人
where the crucifix can then be seen
这样游客才能踩冰走过去，看水下的耶稣
under that layer of ice
obviously they couldn't run tours during the pandemic
在叮咚鸡时期，旅游业停摆了
and it hasn't been cold enough to do so again
随后几年，冬天又不够冷
in the past few years either
冰上站不住人
though it is still a popular diving spot
不过听说，去那里潜水的人还是挺多的
from what I hear
the pole of inaccessibility is the point of land
所谓"难极"，指的是地球上各个大陆
said to be the most difficult to reach on a landmass
依据某种标准，最难抵达的地点
by a given standard or criteria
usually that standard is
一般来说，这种地方
是距离所有海岸线最远的点
the farthest away point on a body of land
from any of its coastlines
如果海岸线模棱两可
if a coastline is a little ambiguous though
"难极"的位置，也就很难确定
its pole of inaccessibility probably will be too
在南极洲的语境下
specifically in Antarctica though
这个词一般指俄罗斯难极考察站
this term usually refers to the Russian
Pole of Inaccessibility Research Station
which was built in Kempenland in 1958
1958年，该站设立在肯普兰
the pole was thought to be at the time
那里是当年的"南极难极"
it was only really used for like a week and a half
这个站点就用了一个半礼拜
built on December 14th and abandoned right after Christmas
12月14号建好，圣诞节过后就废弃了
but during further Antarctic expeditions
但在后续的南极科考中
both in the Soviet and modern era
无论是苏联时期，还是在今天
Russian crews would sometimes go to the abandoned station
俄罗斯探险队，还是会路过这个废弃站点
and hunker down there for a few days before moving on
修整个两三天，然后再继续上路
now to be fair
我说实话啊
I feel like they should have seen it coming
我觉得他们在当年
that this station was gonna be a pain in the ass to use
肯定也知道，这个站点根本用不了
it's almost like
就想想吧
they put it on top of the hardest place to reach
那里是整个南极，最难抵达的地方
in the South Pole
but the station building itself
然而，那座科考站屋顶
has a bust of Vladimir Lenin that faces towards Moscow
还有个列宁的半身像，面向莫斯科
and it's almost entirely covered in snow by now
今天，建筑本身完全被雪掩埋了
so you can only really see Lenin's little head and beard
你只能看到列宁的小脑袋和胡子
sticking out of the white powder mountains these days
从无边的大冰里，探出头来视察
it's like Lenin fell asleep at the beach
就好像列宁在沙滩上睡着了
and his boys just left him like that as a prank
然后，他的好兄弟决定整整他
ooh Trotsky is such a funny guy now help me out of here
托洛茨基，你真够意思的，快把我挖出来
Trotski you there
托洛茨基，你在哪?
Stalin
斯大林?
the skeleton in the iceberg is a viral photo from 2007
冰山里的骷髅，是一张2007年爆火的图片
of what looks like a big ass animal corpse
就是一个巨他妈大的动物骸骨，挂在冰川上
jutting out the side of an iceberg
it was found in Iceberg Alley
照片摄于冰山巷
and stumped scientists both in Canada where it was found
无论是加拿大，还是其他国家的科学家
as well as abroad
都感到很困惑
plenty of smarter folk than me were saying
那些比我聪明得多的人
they'd never seen anything like this before
也说从没见过这样的东西
and that they'd love to get their hands on a sample
很想找来样本，检验一番
but the bone in the picture was unfortunately never identified
但很可惜，现在也没查出那是什么的骨头
the family who took the photo
拍下照片的那家人
also didn't say much about it
也同样缄默不语
after forwarding it to a fishery to try and identify the bones
他们把照片发给一家渔场，想辨认那是什么
some say that they're not answering questions
有人说，他们之所以回避，是因为照片是P的
because it was faked
and were embarrassed to get caught
他们不想再出丑
but it's more likely that they just did want the extra notoriety
但其实，我觉得他们只是不想被过多关注
they weren't even the ones who put out that picture publicly first
毕竟这张照片最开始，也不是他们公布的
and I definitely understand not wanting to bring more attention
我很理解那种感觉，图片不是你发的
to pictures you didn't post
恶评却要冲着你来
this photo could of course still be faked
当然了，这图确实可能是P的
but some of the scientists interested in the find
不过，关注此事的科学家说
said that it would have to be a really good Photoshop job
这么真的图，其实是很难P出来的
like this quote the way that it's laying there
就比如这个: "它趴在那里
with what looks like to be part of it underwater looks authentic
半截浸没在水下的样子，看着挺真的"
so remember when I mentioned how back in 1915
我之前说过，当初在1915年
Ernest Shackleton lost his ship the endurance at sea
沙克尔顿被浮冰困住，只好丢下"坚忍号"
when it got crunched up by sea ice and sank
well in 2022 over 100 years later
2022年，也就是一百多年后
they actually found the site of the wreck
人们找到了这艘沉船
and got 4k HD footage of what it looks like today
还拍下了4K画质的照片
and at least to me
要让我说
it's looking pretty good for 107 years of retirement
哥们保养的真不赖啊，都107年了
not a wrinkle in sight on that boat's Okie skin
看那木头上面，一个褶子都没有
the fact it's a wooden shipwreck
一个木头沉船，居然保存的这么好
and still this clean is nuts
even when my wood's at full mast it's still wrinkly boo
毕竟我胯下的巨轮，都已经磨损不堪了
fuck you but
哎我操，反正
the entire thing is almost still completely intact
这艘船几乎是完好无损的
for Christ sake
真牛逼啊
the name of the ship is still legible on the front
连船头上的名字，都清晰可辨
in the century since it fell off the Billboard charts
沉入海中这一百年以来
the endurance became a makeshift habitat for sea life
坚忍号变成了海洋生物的栖息地
a lot like other shipwrecks end up being
这也是大部分船骸的归宿
with all sorts of ocean critters living inside it now
成为海洋生物的摇篮
the William Brown
威廉·布朗号
was an American ship that sank
是一艘美国船，于1841年撞冰山沉没
after it struck an iceberg in 1841
there were 17 seamen and 65 passengers aboard
当时穿上有17名海员，65名乘客
82 total where 31 passengers died in the wreck
总共82人中，有31名乘客没能活下来
it's pretty mundane as far as iceberg sinking ships goes
船被冰山撞沉，其实没有什么稀奇的
but there is a lot of hoopla
它之所以榜上有名
because of what happened on one of the lifeboats after the fact
完全是因为一艘救生艇上的事故
those who lived escaped on two separate lifeboats
活下来的人，分别乘坐了两艘救生艇
the captain eight of the crew
船长和八名海员
and one passenger escaped on a jolly boat
外加一名乘客，搭乘了工作艇
which is a short fella
其长度很短
while nine crew and 32 passengers
另外九名海员，32名乘客
including the first mate of the ship is
包括船上的大副
escaped on a longboat which is a long fellow
搭乘了一条更大的长艇
the longboat about a day after the William Brown sank
短短一天半后，这艘长艇就开始漏水了
was already leaking
the winds were picking up
而且海上起风了
water was getting over the brim of the ship
船里灌进来很多海水
and it was pissing down a storm
而且雨下的天昏地暗
the boat was in a precarious position and already overcrowded
逃生艇的处境很危急，而且还超载了
so the first mate's solution
于是大副决定
was to start throwing passengers overboard
挑几个乘客，扔到海里去
he told his crew to get to it and it took some convincing
他花了几番口舌，让海员动手丢人
but they ended up Chuck and 12 dudes into the sea
最终，他们扔下去12个男性乘客
and two women took a dive as well
还有2名女性乘客
I don't think I need to tell you that that's like really shitty
我就不多骂了，你是人啊
your job as a crew member
你是个海员啊，本来就该保护乘客性命
is to ensure a passenger's safety no matter what
that's like what you signed up for
职业操守这块
and these dickheads just started killing them
这帮吊人呢，没等暴风雨来，为了自己活命
before the storm could
so that they could live
先把乘客杀了
several passengers filed a complaint
几名乘客上岸后
with the district attorney in Philadelphia
向宾夕法尼亚州的法院，发起了投诉
when they reached land
a guy named Alexander Holmes
当时在城里的，只有个叫霍姆斯的海员
was the only crewman still in the city
making him the only one who ever got charged
于是，他成了唯一被起诉的人
and he was found guilty of manslaughter
最终被判处杀人罪
all the other crew
所有其他海员
including the first mate who ordered them to do it Francis Rhodes
包括那个下达命令的大副，弗朗西斯·罗德
got away Scott Free
全都逃之夭夭了
the Titanic iceberg was sentient
泰坦尼克冰山是活的
refers to a few different things
指的是好几个东西
all of which you should be laughing at
每一个都无比抽象
one is in the movie Titanic 2
有个电影叫《泰坦尼克2》
which is one of those cheesy on purpose disaster movies
它是那种狗屎B级灾难片
that had not literally
没搞标题诈骗
but essentially a sentient iceberg as the enemy
它里面的反派，真就是座活冰山
an iceberg that was looking to destroy the Titanic 2
它出现在泰坦尼克号沉没100周年
specifically on the 100th anniversary of the first one sinking
故意要撞沉泰坦尼克2号
there's even a second movie in the franchise
这片子还出了续集呢
because Titanic 2 is not related to the James Cameron one
因为《泰坦尼克2》跟梅导那部没关系
but yeah the sequel's called Titanic 666
它续集叫做《泰坦尼克666》
who else would fund that thing other than Tubi
这种烂片，还是留着快播上看吧
if you don't know what that streaming service is
哦你不知道快播啊
that is exactly my point
这事儿不赖你
there's also the idea that
不过还真有人觉得
if the iceberg that hit the Titanic was sentient
如果那座撞沉泰坦尼克的冰山是活的
it's arguably just as tragic for the iceberg
那么，那座冰山其实也很惨
because truthfully the ship hit the ice
毕竟，是船撞上了冰山
not the other way around
冰山没招惹它
the Berg probably didn't feel good about
我估计那座冰山，应该不愿意害死那么多人吧
being forced to kill that many people
and of the last straggler theories is a reversal
还有个非主流理论，非常邪门
where in the cars universe
在汽车总动员宇宙里
the Titanic was presumably alive
泰坦尼克号，应该也是活的
the argument is over whether there were car passengers on board
既然如此，是泰坦尼克号搭载汽车乘客沉没呢
or the Titanic sinking was just one really big dude
还是说泰坦尼克号本身大吼一声迎来沉没？
dying in a really loud way
but the real sentient Titanic iceberg is SCP 5245
但真正的泰坦尼克活冰山，是SCP 5245
this big lunk of ice is an iceberg that's 90 by 390 feet wide
这块大冰哥，长达120米，宽达30米
and it's got built in ominous fog on its VR chat model
而且它还内置了不祥的雾气特效
in that it's shrouded in mist at all times
始终笼罩在一片浓雾中
also did I mention that it's alive and can talk
然后，这玩意是活的，还会说话
specifically it's very fond of taking credit
他尤其喜欢吹嘘，说自己撞沉了泰坦尼克
for sinking the Titanic
this Berg would have been very proud
我觉得要是这个冰山能飞
if it was the one who did 911
那9·11肯定是它干的
if ice was the reason the North Tower collapsed
如果冰山撞塌了世贸大厦
we would be sure hearing about it
那可真就有意思了
here's an excerpt from an interview with the Berg
以下是对大冰哥的采访
are you aware of the many casualties you've caused
你知道自己杀死了很多人吗
yes and I'm proud
是的，我很自豪
if it weren't for me the Titanic wouldn't be as popular
要是没我，泰坦尼克就是路边
I beg your pardon
啊？你说啥？
I sunk the Titanic
泰坦尼克我撞的
you sunk the Titanic yes
- 你撞的？ - 对
SCP 5245 is basically a teleporting iceberg
SCP 5245还会瞬移呢
that likes to pop in near ships
它喜欢出现在船附近
where the chances of it appearing in the wild
而且在特定情况下，它的出现几率会变高
increase under certain conditions
you're shiny hunting this iceberg
如果你想邂逅大冰哥
encounter chances generally go up when it's raining
最好的时间，是在下雨或者风暴时
or there's a storm
odds may also improve
还有额外加分项
if 75 percent of a ship's passengers are tourists
就是船员里有超过75%是游客
20% are in a relationship
超过20%处于恋爱关系
or if 5 to 10% of the passengers have thalassophobia
或者5%到10%的乘客有深海恐惧症
this berg is ruthless
大冰哥很绝情
it's not only a sadistic killer
它不光是个虐待狂杀手
but it likes to kill
而且它杀人是有品味的
not just as many people as it can
within the niche it's found
不是见人就杀
but it also wants to make sure that the people it kills
它最喜欢杀的，是那种有老婆孩子的人
have loved ones to leave behind
and that it's killing people who are the most scared
而且它要确保，自己的冰下亡魂
of the specific type of hell it can put them through
在临死前，体验到无尽的恐惧
people who are already stressed out
他喜欢杀那种 被坏天气吓懵了的人
on a ship in bad weather
and also seeking out ships
或者是那种，对深海怀着巨大恐惧的人
with people who have a fear of the ocean's depths in general
ones who despite their fear
那些人克服了恐惧
still had the courage to get on a cruise
好不容易才登船旅行
and try and better themselves as a person
还觉得自己战胜了心魔呢
only for this dick to around to show them
结果这大冰哥传送过来，直接给他们弄死了
they never should have tried
Project Habakkuk was a plan in World War II
"哈巴谷"计划，是二战期间的一种构想
to make an aircraft carrier out of a
那帮神人想用冰和木屑，搓一个航母出来
fucking iceberg in sawdust for some reason
well it was more like they were gonna use ice
冰和木屑可以制成一种
and wood as a resource to make pykrete
名叫"派克瑞特"的复合材料
that way they could make a ship out of pykrete
于是，他们就想用这材料造船
if you want me to say it in the boring historically correct way
好了，这就是个无聊的军事历史概念
Pykrete is a composite developed
"派克瑞特"发明于二战
by Geoffrey Pyke in World War II
发明人叫杰佛里·派克
that's roughly 14 percent wood and
按重量，成分大约是14%的木屑，加上86%的冰
86 percent ice by weight
and it's weirder than my taste in men
比我对男人的品味还怪
解释笑话：Wood在俚语中指男性生殖器
Ice在嘻哈文化中指珠宝、纯纯的冰，以及谋杀
意思是筑波是个BBC Thug爱好者，令人会心一笑
it melts slowly due to low Thermal conductivity
因为导热率低，所以它融化得很慢
and as solid as concrete if kept frozen
在冰冻状态，它硬得像混凝土
apparently you could also repair and maintain pykrete with seawater
还有就是，"派克瑞特"可以用海水来修复
and it could also be molded into any shape
还能塑造成任意的形状
folks were trying to build ship
"派特里克"发明之前，就有人想用冰做船了
out of ice long before pykrete came along
but ice itself was just too brittle
但冰本身却太脆了
and pykrete was developed specifically
于是，"派特里克"被发明出来
with the idea of making a supersized aircraft carrier out of it
专门用于建造巨型的冰山航母
making a ship was the plan from the start for this
这个抽象计划，从一开始就是冲着冰航母去的
crackpot adjacent plan
and to demonstrate how strong this shit was
为了展示这种材料的强大特性
one of Pykrete's proponents Lord Mountbatten
"派特里克"的推广人，蒙巴顿勋爵
his real name is too long to call him anything else but that
这人的名字非常长，我们就不叫全名了
brought a block of ice and a block of pykrete with him
他怀里揣着一块冰砖，一块"派特里克"
to a meeting that had both Winston Churchill
去觐见英国首相丘吉尔
and Franklin Delano Roosevelt present
以及美国总统罗斯福
he placed both on the ground
他把两块冰放在地上
and then pulled out his pistol before shooting the ice
然后掏出手枪，对着冰砖就是一枪
of course the ice split apart
当然，冰应声碎裂成一地碎片
splintered and all that stuff
that happens when you shoot something that isn't bulletproof
毕竟这只是冰，不是什么防弹材料
then he shot the pykrete block
然后，他掏枪射"派特里克"
where the bullet bounced off it
结果子弹被弹开
and hit one of the admirals there in the fucking leg
射向了美国海军司令的大腿
it was just his pants I guess not the meat
幸好，子弹只是擦破了裤子
but the point stands
大家被说服了
Churchill was really jazzed about the whole piecrete thing
丘吉尔非常喜欢这个"派克里特"
and wanted a 2000 foot long
于是下令，建一个全长600米
40 foot thick Pykrete carrier
拥有12米厚的冰装甲
that was theoretically self repairing
有能力自我修复的冰航母
which sounds insane even today
这想法真是有够癫的
a prototype pykrete ship did eventually get made
结果，还真造了个试验型冰航母
it was designed to be 60 feet long and 30 feet wide
其长度大约20米，宽度大约10米
weighing close to 1,000 tons
排水量近1000吨
and the test was mainly to see
大家想看看，这玩意能不能浮起来
if it even stayed afloat
and it actually did
结果还真能
shit never got any farther than that prototype though
不过随后，冰航母项目就没有下文了
as the war had no need for it past a certain point
因为战况很顺利，没必要整花活了
but the potential for the pykrete ship idea applied at scale
但用"派特里克"造船，说不定还真行得通
might have actually worked
the Mythbusters also made a scuffed ship
流言终结者，按当年的构想
following the original plans
造了一艘小冰船
but they're theirs was thinner
他们的船没那么厚
and there was no cooling measures implemented
船上也没有冷却系统
to stop the pykrete from melting
无法减缓冰块的融化
still their version sailed at decent speeds for a while
尽管如此，他们的冰船还是顺利航行了一阵子
after they made it
the mythbusters said that
流言终结者说
the original idea for the aircraft carrier might be plausible
最初的冰航母计划，尽管看似是可行的
but is still very stupid
但却很愚蠢
especially considering there's more already reliable ways
因为在当时，正常造船的流程已经很成熟了
to build them these days
melting icebergs will cause an ice age
融化的冰山会导致冰河世纪
refers to how the earth naturally goes through
指的是地球数千年来，自然经历的冰河周期
ice age cycles over thousands of years
which affects how much solar energy makes it to us on earth
这会影响地球从太阳接收的能量
according to researchers
据研究人员说
when Earth's orbit around the sun
当地球的公转轨道，处于某个窗口期的时候
is in just the right pocket
Antarctic icebergs will melt more and more
从南极向北漂移的冰山，会融化得更快
as they get further away from Antarctica
this moves a lot of fresh water
由此一来，大量的淡水
away from the Antarctic Ocean and into the Atlantic
便从南极洲附近，涌入大西洋
making the Antarctic's water saltier
导致南极海水的盐分更高
and the North Atlantic's water fresher
北大西洋海水的盐度更低
over time
长此以往
this pulls carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere
这会减少大气中的二氧化碳
and reduces the greenhouse effect
从而降低温室效应
which then kicks starts another ice age
于是，地球就陷入了冰河世纪
and this whole process happens over a long long time
这个过程，需要耗费漫长的时间
it's been observed as the basis for every ice age
过去的160万年里，每个冰河世纪
in the last 1.6 million years
都是这样开始的
and the concern is that nowadays
但今天的问题是
the Antarctic Ocean is too warm for icebergs
南极周围的海水太暖了，那里的冰山
from the South Pole to get far enough north
没法漂到更远的北方
meaning it can't trigger those needed changes in salt levels
由此一来，盐度的交换就中断了
打游戏输了后口吐莲花，在英语里也叫“salty”（高盐度）
that you usually only get from cod lobbies
负能量的交换就爆发了
我真心盼你得绝症好吧
傻逼玩意打成这样
and this might hamper the Ice Age from starting
这样以来，下一次冰河期更新
when it was originally supposed to
可能就要跳票了
the Ice Age devs just need more time man
哎，让开发团队多花点时间吧
I'd rather wait and get a finished Ice Age when it's ready
我宁愿多等等，换来成品版的冰期体验
instead of rushed out the door
也不想打开新版本
and filled with super viruses and bad net code
发现全是超级病毒和烂网络代码
man proposes god disposes
《谋事在人，成事在天》
is an oil painting from 1864
这是埃德温·兰西尔，在1864年创作的油画
by artist Edwin Landseer
that depicts polar bears
画中，两只北极熊
tearing shit up at the wreck site of a ship
在船骸中间，撕扯啃食
other than looking just sick as hell
这玩意不光看着瘆人
it was directly inspired by John Franklin's lost expedition
它还影射了之前提到的"富兰克林远征队"
from earlier in this chart
there's more history and details behind this painting's creation
这副画背后，有不少值得一聊的故事
but the modern day urban myth is more fun
其中最有趣的，是一个现代都市传说
today the painting sits in the university of London
如今，这幅画收藏于伦敦大学
and since the 1920s all the way till the 60s
从1920年代，一直到1960年代
it was a genuine legend
一直都有传闻说
that sitting in front of the painting during an exam
无论是谁，只要坐在这幅画前
would instantly lobotomize you and make you fail it
立刻就会大脑降级，考试挂科
ever since the 70s
从70年代开始
it's become a tradition during exams
每年一到期末考试
to cover the painting with a Union Jack
这幅画就会被国旗盖住
because it won't stop looking at you like that
把那双瘆人的鬼眼给挡住
an unnamed student back then
当年考试期间
apparently wouldn't take the exam with it given off weird vibes
有个学生无论如何，也不愿坐在这幅画面前
and it was covered with the first thing they could find
监考老师找来一面巨大的国旗，勉强把油画盖住
that was big enough to obscure the whole image
so that exams could get started
然后考试才正常进行
there was also a rumor that the painting
关于这幅画，还有流言说
convinced a student in exam season to kill themselves
曾有一个学生因为它，在期末周自杀了
writing the Polar Bears made me do it on their test
那个学生的试卷上，写着"是北极熊逼我的"
which as far as suicide notes go is pretty weak
不是哥们，这就是你的遗言啊
and there's literally no trace of this ever happening
但这个自杀事件，完全无迹可查
making it another one of those fan favorite crocks of shit
可能是热心网友现编的故事吧
Jupi Nakoolak is a 17 year old Canadian
朱皮·纳库拉克，是个17岁的因纽特人
or at least he was when this stuff happened
反正他遇难时是这个岁数
he got stuck drifting on an ice floe
在一片浮冰上，他被困了整整三天
for almost 3 days straight
he got stranded while hunting with his uncle
当时，他正和叔叔一起打猎
when an ice floe he was standing on broke away
结果，他脚下的浮冰突然崩裂了
and also on the ice with him were two polar bear cubs
同一片浮冰上，还有两只小北极熊
whose mom Jupi just marked right in front of them in self defense
朱皮为了保护自己，开枪打死了它们的母亲
the only food he had was some chocolate bars
他唯一的食物，是飞机空投的几条巧克力棒
that a small plane dropped to him
which is like really unhelpful I'm not gonna lie
这玩意是填不饱肚子的
if he brought the chocolate bars himself
如果是他自己，出门只带了巧克力棒
and they were the only food he had
then you know you work with what you got
那他挨饿属于活该
but if you're air dropping him supplies
但你都安排空投了啊
all you're gonna give him is Mr Beast Feastables
结果你就给他丢点巧克力棒?
they probably taste decent
这玩意是挺好吃的
but that still feels disrespectful when the dude's like starving
但人家快饿死了啊，你就让人家吃这点破东西?
get him his Chipotle order or something man
起码给人家吃个猪脚饭吧
at least like beef jerky
实在不行牛肉干呢
he suffered enough down there without you bullying him
他已经够辛苦了，还要被你们霸凌
I'm sure there's practical and logistic reasons
我知道，当时只送巧克力棒
why he got chocolate bars only
是因为物资运输很困难
but just let me be funny please
不过就让我幽默一下吧
the truth is hard for people like me
真相对我来说太沉重了
after Nakoolak was found
纳库拉克被人发现后
two crew members parachuted down to an ice floe nearby
两位救援人员，跳伞到了旁边的浮冰上
and crawled call of duty prone style to get to him
然后像COD那样，匍匐爬过去
where they were all picked up via boat
把他救上船，顺利脱险
he was alone and in temperatures below negative 15 degrees Celsius
他孤身一人，困在零下15度的冰天雪地里
but was somehow in good condition
获救时居然没啥大碍
other than slight hypothermia
只不过轻微脱水
and just a little love chomp of frostbite
外加一点点冻伤罢了
Antarctic Google Maps alien sightings
谷歌地图里的南极外星人
is this weird category of thing
这是我在查资料时
I kept running into while researching
多次看到的一个怪东西
where more than one person has gone viral
就是有很多人，在网上到处宣扬
for thinking they found
说自己有大发现
or lying about finding
也可能是装的
not only aliens or extraterrestrial spaceships
反正就是发现了外星人和地外飞行器
but that they made these earth shattering discoveries on
更离谱的是，他们做出这些大发现的地方
Google Maps of all possible places
居然是谷歌地图
here are some I found a bit silly
我挑几个蠢的讲讲吧
we have this alien face on Google Earth
这是谷歌地图上的外星人脸
where the dude who posted it
发帖人说，这是外星人留下的遗迹
claims that it was left behind by aliens
quote from a conspiracy theory channel reads
有个阴谋论频道里说
it appears to be a massive ancient structure
"这是一种象征脸部的巨大物体"
of some kind of face
that is being revealed for the first time on Google Earth
"首次被发现在谷歌地球上"
I would have to concur that whatever we're looking at
我赞同，无论这玩意是什么
resembles some sort of mega structure
它的体积一定很巨大
no doubt
但这玩意长得，像被闪瞎了一样
it looks like someone who couldn't handle a blinker
to me this is just an example of blatant pareidolia
我觉得，这是一种幻想性视错觉
like those icebergs we saw earlier that looked like penises
就像之前那些冰山，还看着像极霸呢
it's unironically the same thing
这两者背后，其实是同一种大脑机制
making both of those happen in your brain
this other dude Scott C Warring
还有个斯科特·C.沃林
said he had 100% proof
说自己有远古外星人窜访地球的铁证
of ancient aliens on earth
because he found this thing that is
铁证就是，他在谷歌上找到的这些三角形
kind of triangle shaped on Google
he then concluded yeah that's from space
然后他就说，这太空来的
the only one of these I'll admit is kinda cool
唯一让我觉得真有点潮酷的
is someone who found a supposedly
是有人在谷歌地图上，发现了120米长的"冰船"
400 foot long ice ship on Google Maps
100 miles off the coast of Antarctica
位于南极洲100英里外
it definitely looks the most like a ship
跟其他"发现"相比，这玩意还真挺像船的
out of all the things we've been looking at
but if a world order is dumb enough
如果外星人这么蠢
to let this shit be found on public access stuff like Google Maps
真的会让我们在谷歌地图上找到端倪
to me personally they just don't seem smart enough
那么以它们的智商，肯定也藏不住其他东西
to hide the rest of the ship
there's theories saying the ship is anything
有人说这是外星飞船
from aliens to some secret Nazi base
还有人说是南极纳粹基地
and I don't about any of them
随便咋说，我不在乎
the moon controls the release of methane in the Arctic Ocean
北冰洋释放甲烷是受月球影响
is what's on the tip
就是字面意思
I could probably get away with reading this entry name
本来我读完这句话，就可以直接进入下一层了
and immediately doing the next layer
but if you don't know because I didn't before this
不过，还是简单给大家科普一下
the Arctic Ocean releases a lot of methane
长期以来，北冰洋一直在释放大量甲烷
and has been doing so for ages
so naturally
可以理解
folks are worried about the consequences of this
大家都担心，这样会加剧海洋变暖
with already warming oceans
the basics are that the moon controls the tides
其原理是，月亮会控制潮汐
which is such a sick character description
这能力其实有点OP了
and tides have a big impact on how intense methane
而潮汐的强度，会影响北冰洋的甲烷释放
emissions from the Arctic Ocean are
higher tides seem to keep emissions lower in height and volume
涨潮时，甲烷释放更少，气泡柱高度也更低
while low tides are when they seem to be stronger
退潮时，甲烷释放会加剧
this discovery could lead to a method of counteracting ocean temperatures
基于此，我们可以发明一种方法
from getting even warmer
控制海洋暖化
if researchers can find a way
如果能控制甲烷释放，我们就能缓解全球变暖
to keep these emissions down manually
then there might be some good we can do with that
如果能控制甲烷释放，我们就能缓解全球变暖
现在是第五层，我已经看不到船了
It's layer 5 now, and I can't see ship.
我们身处伟大的未知之中
We are in the great unknown.
“冰虫计划”简直牛的批爆
Project Iceworm was batshit insane,
这是冷战时期美国陆军的一项秘密计划
and a secret US Army plan during the Cold War
打算在格陵兰岛的冰盖下建设一个大型核导弹发射阵列
to build a big array of nuclear missile launch sites under Greenland's ice sheet.
当然这事肯定不会事先和他们打招呼
Very much without telling them.
这东西如果完成的话，预期规模简直疯狂
The intended scale this thing, if finished, was nuts.
整个设施本来应该覆盖大约 134679 平方公里，并且位于地下 8.5 米深处
The full facility was supposed to cover some 52,000 square miles and be 28 feet underground.
这些狗日的打算从冰层中挖出 4023 公里长的隧道
These fuckers were going to try and dig 2,500 miles of tunnel out of the ice
因此，如果发生核战争，他们可以发射出 600 枚能够抵达苏联的核弹头
so they could shoot out 600 nuclear missiles capable of reaching the USSR if there was ever a nuclear war.
世纪营地是他们在格陵兰建立的基地，是给冰虫计划打掩护的
Camp Century was the base that was constructed in Greenland as a public front for Iceworm,
用来解释美国军方为什么要在那里设立基地
in order to explain why, about why the US military was setting up shop.
据我所知，世纪营地这一计划是美方唯一与丹麦和格陵兰讨论过的部分
From what I know, this Camp Century front was the only part of the plan that US discussed with Denmark and Greenland,
当时这两方某种程度上相当于他们的人才基地
who were kind of like their talent management agency at the time.
希望不该听到这话的人没有听到
I hope the wrong person didn't hear me say that,
美国人当时是这么和丹麦人说的，这是为了验证在冰盖上建立廉价军事前哨的可行性
but the US basically told the Danes it was meant as a proof of concept for making inexpensive military outposts at ice caps,
这话可能有一定道理
which might have also been true,
但并非主要原因
but was not the main reason.
他们甚至为自己为什么必须要在冰盖基地搞一座核反应堆找好了不在场证明
They even had an alibi for why they definitely needed to have a nuclear reactor with them at their ice cap base.
绝对只是为了测试半移动核反应堆可能会遇到的实际问题
It was definitely just to test practical issues that a semi-mobile nuclear reactor might have.
绝无非分之想哦
As you do.
令人惊讶的是，那座核反应堆其实并不完全是谎言
Surprisingly, the nuclear reactor wasn't actually a lie.
这是史上同类装置中的首例，在实践中掌握其运作原理或许也不赖
It was the first of its kind, and learning how it worked in practice was probably not a bad idea.
冰虫计划被终止，并不是因为冷战紧张局势缓和或美国的良心发现
Practic Iceworm was discontinued, not because of Cold War tensions lowering or the goodness of America's heart,
而是因为他们挖掘的冰川不稳定，头顶上的马上要塌了
but because the glacier they were digging in was unstable and collapsing on top of them.
1962 年，基地上的人们一度以为他们长个儿了
In 1962, folks on the base must have thought they had gotten taller,
之后才意识到只是反应堆房间的顶棚变矮罢了
before they realized the ceiling of the reactor room was just shorter.
事实证明，冰川就像跑步机一样持续移动，即使你身处其中也无法阻止
Turns out, glaciers stay on the treadmill and keep moving even when you're inside them,
而这座冰川的移动速度比他们预期的要快
and this one was moving faster than they anticipated.
他们不得不把反应室的屋顶再抬高 1.5 米
They had to lift the reactor room's roof back up by five feet,
而这很可能让有人想
and that probably had someone going,
嗯，也许这里并不是放核反应堆的好地方
hmm, maybe this isn't a great place to keep a nuclear reactor.
尽管他们为此经历了种种折腾，事情就是行不通
It was just not going to work out, despite all the hoops they'd gone through to get there,
并且预计隧道将在两年内坍塌
and the tunnels were predicted to collapse in two years' time.
当基地在 1965 年撤离时，他们至少记得把核武器带回了国内
They at least remembered to bring the nuke back home with them when the base was evacuated in 1965,
该项目于 1966 年被正式取消
and the project was officially canned in 1966.
小行星 2022 EB-5 是有史以来第五颗在撞入地球前被发现的小行星
Asteroid 2022 EB-5 was only the fifth ever asteroid that was discovered before it crashed into Earth.
在去年的三月，也就是 2022 年，匈牙利的一位天文学家克里斯蒂安·萨尔涅茨基
In March last year, 2022, an astronomer in Hungary named Christian Sarnetsky
在通过望远镜观测时看到天空中有一个又大又亮的物体
saw something big and bright in the sky while looking through a telescope.
他在接下来的短时间里继续观察
He kept on observing it for the next little while,
在第一次看到该物体不到 15 分钟后，就向小行星中心报告了此事
and in less than 15 minutes of first seeing the object, reported it to the Minor Planet Center,
那是负责追踪彗星和其他比行星小的天体的一群人
who were the group of dudes that tracked comets and other space falls smaller than a planet.
他说他所看到的东西真不能假设是一架飞机
He said that what he saw he couldn't just pretend was an airplane,
而是在夜空中真实存在的一样东西，一颗流星
and that it was a real deal in the night sky, a shooting star.
当克里斯蒂安的发现首次被公布时
When Christian's find was first published,
没有人想到它会来跟行星的地壳亲密接触
no one thought it was coming to suck face with the planet's crust.
小行星撞击地球的概率被定在不到百分之一
The chances of the asteroid hitting Earth were set at less than one percent.
消息传开了，更多该领域的专家开始观察这个天体
Word got around, and more experts in the field started observing the object,
克里斯蒂安也开始继续观察它
and as Christian continued observing it,
他们收集到的数据越多，预测变化越频繁
the more the data that they collected changed the prediction.
只是一点点证据
Just a little bit.
就把撞击的概率从千分之几提升到了——
It brought the chance of impact up from a fraction of a percent to,
没座，那东西肯定会撞上我们，而且很快
yeah, that shit's definitely hitting us, and, like, soon.
这颗小行星会在我们意识到它将撞击我们后不到一小时内，就我们到家门口
The asteroid would be knocking on our front door in less than an hour from when we realized it was going to hit us at all.
预测它会在冰岛北部登陆，会在一个较少有人居住的地方形成撞坑
It was predicted to land off of Northern Iceland, where it would crater somewhere not so inhabited,
而且雷声大雨点小，没啥致命性
and would just be really loud instead of really deadly.
幸运的是，这颗小行星足够小，大部分在大气层中燃烧殆尽
Luckily, the asteroid was small enough that most of it burned up in the atmosphere,
尽管没有人记录到它坠落的瞬间
and while nobody recorded it touching down,
但雷达确实记录到了撞击，威力相当于一次里氏 4.0 级的地震
the impact sure showed up on the radar with the power of a 4.0 magnitude earthquake.
EB-5 最终长眠于偏远之地，它在瓦特纳冰川的冰丘间划出波纹，随后便失去了踪迹
EB-5's final resting place was in a remote area where it motorboated the icy mounds of the Vatnajökull Glacier before passing out.
斯凯达拉是我刚用碎木机绞过的一个词，也是冰岛一条相当短的冰川河
Skeiðará is a word I just ran through a wood chipper, and a rather short glacial river in Iceland.
它因为过去的危险而声名狼藉
It's got a bad reputation because of how dangerous it's been in the past,
因为那里的冰川洪水相当常见，历史上曾经死过几个人
as glacial flooding there is pretty common and has been known to kill a few fellas in its time.
比如，这里的桥梁纪念碑就是 1996 年火山爆发后
For example, the bridge monument here is all that's left of a bridge
那座被炸得稀巴烂的桥梁仅存的遗迹
that was blown the fuck out after a volcano blew up in 1996.
那次喷发融化了斯凯达拉冰川流出部分的冰
The eruption melted parts of the glacier that the Skeiðará flows from,
巨大的冰块横冲直撞穿过桥梁，把它撕得粉碎
sending giant chunks of ice careening through the structure, just tearing it apart.
它还是存在时是冰岛最大的桥梁
It was the biggest bridge in Iceland when it was still around,
并且是该国环岛公路的一部分
and was a part of that country's ring road.
以防你不知道，那基本上就是他们的州际高速公路
If you don't know, that's basically their interstate highway.
它绕着整个国家盘旋，并通过油老虎大车把一切连在一起
It circles around the whole country and connects everything via gas guzzling vehicles.
不过，桥梁工程师们并不全是煞笔
Now, the bridge engineers weren't just stupid.
他们不会上 r/Batman Arkham
They don't go on r/Batman Arkham.
这座桥的建造考虑到了洪水的情况
The bridge was built with flooding in mind,
但它并不是专门为承受像复式房屋那样大的冰山撞击而造的
but it wasn't really made to take hits from icebergs the size of duplex houses.
这些扭曲的金属和钢梁就是所剩下的一切
These twisted metals and girders are all that's left,
它被放置在取代那座桥梁的新道路旁
and it's placed next to the road that went on to replace the bridge.
我听说现在它附近也能看到河流的好景致
I've heard it has a nice view of the river nearby now, too.
好，冰火山本质上是在地球上的湖面上形成的锥形冰堆
Okay, so ice volcanoes are essentially cone-shaped ice mounds that form on lakes specifically on Earth.
它们有点像冰上的喷气口，也有点像铁板烧店里那种分层的洋葱火山
They're similar to ice fumaroles, and they're kind of like the layered onion volcanoes at a hibachi place.
它们由水和雪泥冲破冰架喷出形成
They form from water and slush getting erupted through an ice shelf,
由于外面温度很低，当这些物质落回地面时会立即冻结
and since it's cold outside, when they fall back to the ground, they freeze.
这会重复发生几次，水落回到最后那层冰上
This will happen a few more times with the water falling back down on that last frozen layer,
在其上方再次结冰，使冰火山变得更大
freezing on top of it, and making the ice volcano bigger.
这与美国在某一区域分层浇水并让其结冰的过程类似
It's a similar process to how the U.S. would layer water and let it freeze in a certain area,
然后冲洗并重复该过程，建造我在几层之前提到的那些冰墩
then rinse and repeat to build those ice piers I spoke about a few layers ago.
冰火山和冰冻火山的区别在于冰冻火山是在太空中的
Now, the difference between an ice volcano and a cryovolcano is that a cryovolcano is in space.
它们存在于行星和你所在的“太空球体”上
It's on planets and space balls that you are in.
这些东西除了喷出氨和甲烷等物质外，也会喷出水
These things also spit out water, in addition to ammonia and methane and other stuff,
再强调一次，这玩意处在等于或低于喷出物冰点的环境中
again, into an environment that is at or below the freezing temperature
无论冰火山喷出的是什么，结果其实都差不多
of whatever the cryovolcano is coughing up, and they essentially do the same thing.
这些物质落回去并凝固在它们被喷出的喷口上
The materials fall back down and freeze to the orifice they got spit out of.
它们最常出现在那些极其寒冷的地方，比如冰冷的卫星
They're most known to happen on really cold-ass places like icy moons,
并且已经在矮行星上被观测到，比如土卫六、谷神星
and have been seen on dwarf planets like Titan, Ceres,
以及我心爱的、曾经被欺负过的——冥王星
and my beloved, who has done dirty, Pluto.
对我来说它们是行星
They are a planet to me.
当我们这些矮个子得知冥王星被踢出行星行列时，我们每个人都感到被针对了
Every short person felt personally attacked when we found out Pluto had been kicked out of the club.
当我学习太阳系时，那里还是有九大行星的，九大！
When I learned about the solar system, there were nine planets. Nine.
格利泽 436 b 是一颗类海王星大小的行星，环绕红矮星格利泽 436 运转
Gliese 436 b is a planet the size of Neptune orbiting the Gliese 436 red dwarf star.
那是首个被确认无误的类海王星行星
It was the first Neptune-looking planet that was confirmed to be, without a doubt,
真他妈的火热，跟我一样
really fucking hot. Almost as hot as me.
这里值得注意的是，那颗遥远的火球不知怎的竟然有冰
It's noteworthy here because that far away ball of fire somehow has ice on it.
能达到 1000 度的冰，我不是在开玩笑
Ice that runs up to a thousand degrees Fahrenheit. I'm not joking.
区别在于，在地球上，冰在寒冷时会保持固态
What makes the difference is that here on Earth, ice stays solid when it's cold,
因为水分子会紧密排列，使水呈固态
because the molecules will huddle in, making water solid.
它们之所以凝结，是因为温度足够低，热能不足以让分子四处碰撞
They compress because the temperature is low enough that there isn't enough heat energy
因此它们减速到足以互相吸附并固化的程度
for the molecules to bounce around, so they slow down enough to grab onto each other and solidify.
相反，当温度足够高时，分子热运动变得更快并彼此分离
The reverse is when it's warm enough, the molecules become faster and let go of each other,
融化成液体
melting into liquid.
如果听起来像是在居高临下地说话，我为此道歉
Sorry if it sounds like I'm talking down to you.
当然那不可能，因为你比我高
That's impossible because you're taller than me.
但尴尬的是我自己也得复习这些知识，就当小贴士听了
But I embarrassingly had to brush up on this stuff myself, so I just wanted to be considerate.
话说回来，在格利泽 436b 上，冰在该烧起来的温度时仍能保持凝结的唯一原因
Regardless, on Gliese 436b, the only reason the ice stays frozen together while on fire
并非严寒，而是极大的压强
isn't because it's so cold, it's because of sheer pressure.
燃烧的冰之所以仍然是冰，是因为那颗行星的大气层非常沉重
The burning ice keeps being ice because of how heavy the atmosphere on the planet is.
牛逼到能把水压缩成固体
It's so strong that it will compress water into being solid.
水分子无法解开或移动，因为它们承受着极大的压力
The H2O molecules cannot unhook or move anywhere because of just how much stress they're under.
所以即使它们被加热到极高温度并想快速移动，也无济于事
So it doesn't matter if they're super heated and want to move super fast,
它们没有足够的空间可以弹开并融化
there is no room for them to bounce off and melt.
据我所知，在足够的压力下，水会变成一种比冰和液态水都更致密的固体
From what I've read, under enough pressure, water becomes a solid denser than ice and liquid water,
就像碳如果在你两颊之间放得足够久，会变成钻石一样
the same way carbon becomes diamonds if you keep it between your cheeks for long enough.
说到这里，钻石冰山是一种可能存在于海王星和你肛门里的冰山
Speaking of, diamond icebergs are a type of iceberg that potentially exists on Neptune and your anus.
天王星 Uranus 的谐音梗
你懂的，因为屎夹得很紧
You know, because shit is tight.
那些行星是冰巨星，所以和地球有点不同
Those planets are ice giants, so a bit different from Earth.
它们有冰冷的海洋表面和超过 3728 公里的深度
They have icy oceans and over 6,000 miles under the surface.
那里的压力甚至超过你第一次参与飞叶子时的感受
There's more pressure than even your first time in a blunt rotation,
曾有人推测，在那里有一段时间可能是会下钻石雨的
where for a while it's been speculated that it might rain diamonds down there.
与此同时，也有人推测这些行星上的海洋可能由液态钻石组成
Alongside this, it's also been speculated that the oceans on these planets might be made up of liquid diamond.
最近在地球上进行的实验表明，这实际上可能是真事儿
And experiments done recently here at home show that this might actually be possible.
我不知道在地球上具体要如何做到这一点
I don't know how on Earth specifically you do this,
但科学家们用激光在超过地球大气压四千万倍的压力下对钻石进行猛烈轰击
but scientists beat the life out of a diamond with a laser at pressures over 40 million times Earth's atmosphere.
在缓慢降低温度和压力后
After slowly lowering the temperature and pressure,
他们发现钻石在凝固和融化时的行为像水
they discovered that diamond behaves like water when it's freezing and melting.
固体钻石块会浮到液体表面，形成钻石冰山
Chunks of solid diamond will float to the top of the liquid, making diamond icebergs.
海王星和天王星的海洋由液态钻石构成也可以解释其他现象
The oceans on Neptune and Uranus being made of liquid diamond would also explain other stuff,
比如它们的磁场严重偏离南北轴线，以及两颗行星的组成中大约有 10% 是碳
like their magnetic fields being tilted way off their north-south axes, and both planets being about 10% carbon in their makeup,
而钻石并不完全由碳构成
which is what diamonds aren't made of entirely.
现实中的冰墙是冰架的边缘，但在地平论中
A real-life ice wall is the edge of an ice shelf, but in flat Earth theory,
冰墙这一概念是指南极并不是真正的一个大陆
the ice wall is the idea that Antarctica is not actually a continent.
在当前的平地球模型中，南极反而是世界的边缘
In the current model of the flat Earth, the South Pole is instead the edges of the world
把它们封闭起来
that keep it closed in.
它就像大洋的一个碗
It's like a bowl for the oceans.
它们把外面的东西挡在外面，也阻止我们离开
They keep what's out there, out, and us from getting out.
一些地平论者声称，NASA 守护着南极冰墙，因为他们不希望人们看到真相
Some flat Earthers claim that NASA guards Antarctic ice because they don't want people to see the truth,
并且冰墙之外可能有什么他们不想让我们知道的东西
and that there's perhaps something beyond the ice that they don't want us to know about.
这与那些推测南极神秘真相的阴谋论倒是呼应上了——
This ties into other conspiracy theories speculating what's really going on in Antarctica,
或许只有政府人员、科学家和野兽先生被允许前往那里，背后藏着某种不可告人的原因
that maybe there's some kind of sinister reason only government personnel, scientists, and Mr. Beast are allowed to go there.
多名平地论者曾多次计划航行到地球的边缘
Several flat Earthers over time have planned to sail to the edge of the Earth,
或者冰墙，终结性地证明地球是平的
or the ice wall, to prove once and for all that the Earth is flat.
有些人在 2019 年制定了计划，定在 2020 年某个时候行动
Some folks made plans in 2019, setting a date of sometime in 2020,
但随后叮咚鸡爆发，阻止了他们
but then COVID came up and stopped them.
这也情有可原，但我没想到他们会让叮咚鸡给拦住
Which is fair, but I didn't think these were the type of people who let COVID stop them.
不过很幸运，为了我们的娱乐消遣
Luckily, for the sake of our entertainment,
一对意大利夫妇接过了这一重任，计划航行至兰佩杜萨岛
an Italian couple took up the mantle and planned to sail to Lampedusa,
一个位于意大利海岸外的小岛，他们相信那里就是世界尽头
an island off the coast of Italy that they believed was the end of the world.
若你认为世界尽头不过是乘船离家不远的地中海一隅，那你的眼界未免太过狭隘
You must not think very big if you believe the world ends a boat ride away from your house, a boat ride that's in the Mediterranean Sea.
他们没能成功，但别担心
They never made it, but don't worry.
这是本冰山图上少数几次无人遇难的失败探险之一
This is one of the only failed expeditions on this chart where nobody died.
这对夫妇阴差阳错去了错误的岛屿，被隔离后试图逃跑未果
Instead, the couple went to the wrong island by accident, got put in quarantine, tried to escape, failed,
再次遭到隔离，最终选择了放弃
got put back in quarantine, and finally gave up.
之后，他们只能搭乘一艘简陋的客船回家，因为他们的船在中途丢失了
After that, they just took a measly passenger ship back home because they lost their boat in the middle of the whole thing.
里格是一只据称在泰坦尼克号沉没时登船的狗，在灾难中帮助拯救了多条生命
Rigel is a dog who was allegedly on the Titanic when it sank, that helped save multiple lives during the disaster.
故事称里格是泰坦尼克号的大副威廉·麦克马斯特·默多克养的
The story goes that Rigel was owned by first officer of the Titanic, William McMaster Murdoch,
他倒确实是船上的一位真实存在的人
who was actually a verified real person on the ship.
据说在威廉在沉船中身亡后
Supposedly after William died in the wreck,
据一些记载，里格用狗刨式游出了自己的路线
Rigel doggy paddled his own path but stuck close to the lifeboats,
但始终紧贴救生艇，特别是四号救生艇
specifically lifeboat number four, according to some accounts.
当喀尔巴阡号前来搜寻幸存者时
When the Carpathia showed up looking for survivors,
显然是里格的吠叫引起了他们的注意
it was apparently Rigel barking that got their attention
因为救生艇正位于喀尔巴阡号的船头下方
as the lifeboat was under the Carpathia's bow
若非如此，邮轮很可能会在毫无察觉的情况下碾过他们
and it might have run them over without realizing it.
实际上也就是说，我狗哥通过吠叫救了乘客们一命
So effectively, the dogs saved the lives of those passengers by barking.
想象一下死在救生艇上，那可真是够尴尬的
Imagine dying on a lifeboat. That's gotta be embarrassing.
这玩意儿名字就叫救生艇啊，蠢货
It's literally named a lifeboat, dipshit.
里格体型太大无法上船，船员们不得不用帆布吊索把他从水里拉上来
Rigel himself was too big to get on the boat, so some crewmen had to hoist him out of the water with a canvas sling.
可惜这很可能又是那种典中典的航海吹比小故事
Unfortunately, there is a good chance this is another one of those trademarked crocks of ship.
有人说这个故事主要来自乔纳斯·布里格斯，他后来收养了这只狗
Some say the story mostly came from Jonas Briggs, who later adopted the dog,
而这位乔纳斯·布里格斯显然也是将里格从水中救起的船员之一
the same Jonas Briggs who apparently was also the crew member who lifted Rigel out of the water.
不过当时并没有任何名为乔纳斯·布里格斯的人在喀尔巴阡号上工作
This despite there being no Jonas Briggs that worked in the Carpathia at the time,
而且四号救生艇上的幸存者也对救生艇的故事提出了质疑
as well as the lifeboat story being disputed by the people on lifeboat four.
无人为这一说法的任何部分作证
None of them vouched for any part of the story,
而喀尔巴阡号在接到这艘救生艇之前就已熄灭了引擎
and the Carpathia had stopped its engines well before it picked up said lifeboat.
还有一点，没有证据表明威廉·默多克或他的妻子曾养过狗
There was also no evidence William Murdoch or his wife had a dog ever,
也没有任何在世的官员提到泰坦尼克号上有狗
and no surviving officer mentioned a dog being on the Titanic.
这个故事漏洞百出，很可能是编造的
There's a ton of other holes in this story, and it's probably made up,
但想到一只狗狗在那里竭尽全力，还是挺暖心的
but it's nice to think that a pooch did his best out there,
尽管它可能根本没在那里
even though it probably wasn't even there.
斯瓦尔巴群岛本身是北冰洋中的挪威群岛
Svalbard on its own is a Norwegian archipelago in the Arctic Ocean.
这里作为北极观光的热门旅游地而闻名，海岸附近常有大量壮观的冰山漂浮
It's popular as a tourist destination for Arctic sightseeing, and it gets a healthy amount of icebergs off its coast.
而斯瓦尔巴的全球种子库是世界农作物多样性的备份储存库
And the Svalbard Global Seed Vault is a backup storage for the world's crop diversity.
该设施保存着来自全球各地基因库的种子副本
It holds duplicates of seeds from gene banks,
这些基因库用于储存遗传物质，为世界粮食供应提供备选方案
which are banks for holding genetic material, from across the globe to provide a plan B for the world food supply.
防止种子因战争、蓄意破坏、疾病或其他令人忧心的全球饥荒问题而流失
This is in the case the seeds are lost through any number of means, be it war, sabotage, disease, or other cringe world hunger stuff.
它完全由挪威政府，这也是它建在这的原因
It was entirely funded by Norway's government, which is why it's there,
但我想，选择斯瓦尔巴群岛的一个额外优势是它靠近北极，在气候变暖的未来
but I imagine that the proximity to the Arctic, where temperatures will likely remain livable the farthest into a warming future,
那里的温度可能仍然宜居
was a bonus of picking Svalbard to host.
马可·埃瓦里斯蒂是一位智利艺术家，自里根时代（80 年代）起便旅居丹麦
Marco Evaristti is a Chilean artist by way of in living in Denmark since the Reagan era, the 80s.
他手头有多个引发广泛关注的项目，还拥有正儿八经的建筑学学位
He has multiple projects that have gotten mass attention and a genuine degree in architecture
——虽然搞那些疯狂事儿时基本用不上这文凭
that he's used when getting up to crazy shit,
毕竟大多和建筑毫无关系
most of it having nothing to do with architecture.
有一次他举办晚宴，主菜是意大利饺子
One time he threw a dinner party where the entree served was agnolotti pasta
上面点缀着用马可当年早些时候抽脂手术中取出的自身脂肪制成的肉丸
topped with meatballs made of Marco's own fat from a liposuction he had earlier that year.
2000 年，他在丹麦举办了一个展览，展出了 10 台内有金鱼的搅拌机
In 2000, he hosted a gallery in Denmark of 10 functioning blenders that had goldfish in them,
他邀请参观者去开启搅拌机
where he invited visitors to turn the blenders on.
正如你所料
Like I'm sure you guessed,
最终有人这么做了
somebody eventually did it
把金鱼弄死了
and it killed the goldfish.
它把金鱼搅得稀烂，你应该能想象得到那个场景吧
It blended it alive, kind of what you expect from a blender with a live goldfish in it.
画廊馆长被控虐待动物
The gallery director got charged with animal cruelty,
但后来被宣判无罪
but was later acquitted.
马可曾用像精液和血液这样的奇怪材料来创作吸睛作品
Marco has used weird ass materials like semen in blood to make statement pieces.
而且我说的不是那款血液精液联名的 Supreme 设计——
And somehow I'm not talking about the blood and sperm supreme design.
他真用那俩玩意创作的
This is real.
对不起喵
Sorry.
不过马可的一个拿手把戏是他不停重复的笑话，他称之为“粉红国度”
One of Marco's staples though is his ongoing gag that he calls the pink state.
我直接引用维基上关于粉红国度的简介吧，因为我实在搞不懂这个
I'm just going to quote the wiki blurb for the pink state because I can't even begin to decipher this.
如果你讨厌这种措辞，我很抱歉
I'm sorry if you hate the wording.
我实在找不到更好的说法了
I got nothing better.
埃瓦里斯蒂将粉红国度描述为他自己的独立国家
Evaristti describes the pink state as his own independent state,
一个拥有护照和宪法却不受政府管控的精神领地
a state of mind with passport and constitution, but without government control.
尽管是虚构概念，他仍会通过转瞬即逝的景观艺术作品将其具象化
Although imaginary, he will materialize it from time to time in this transitory landscape works.
“粉红国度”属于埃瓦里斯蒂，却没有被控制或控制他人的边界
Pink state is Evaristti's, but without controlled or controlling borders.
我分享这些只是为了铺垫他的一项作品——那个涉及“粉红国度”的“冰立方”项目
Me sharing all of that was just context for one of the things he made involving the pink state called the ice cube project
是他在格陵兰岛沿海完成的
that he did off the coast of Greenland.
2004 年，马可在冰山上模拟了一次月经，将整座冰山染成了血红色
In 2004, Marco had some simulated menstruation on an iceberg where he painted the whole thing blood red.
真疯狂，带血的冰竟然不止一次出现过在这个视频里
It's crazy that bloody ice has come up more than once in this video.
他和 20 人的团队花了不少时间精心寻找合适的冰山
He and a 20-man crew spent time carefully searching for the right iceberg
因为我猜马可对符合他构想的冰山相当挑剔
because Marco was picky on what fit his vision, I guess.
他们找到合适样本后
After they had their specimen,
突发艺术灵感，用消防软管将约 780 加仑红色颜料喷洒在选定的冰山画布上
they used fire hoses to spray some 780 gallons of red paint on a fitting iceberg canvas, apparently on a creative whim.
他们花了两个小时把颜料喷得到处都是，弄得一团糟
It took two hours to splooge squib blood all over the damn thing,
结果就是眼前这个样子
which left us with the result in front of you now.
宁根是一种水生生物，外形似鲸鱼，长着两条腿和蛋形脸
The Ningen is an aquatic, whale-looking, two-legged, egg-faced loser
据称能在陆地上行走，栖息于南冰洋
that allegedly walks on land and lives in the Antarctic Ocean.
它于 2002 年在日本的 2ch 论坛上出现
It was made in 2002 on Japan's two-channel forums,
人们一开始声称一艘鲸类研究船的船员在南极海岸附近看到这头丑陋到极点的怪物
where people started claiming that the crew of a whale research ship saw this fuck-ugly monstrosity off the  Antarctic coast,
他们起初以为那是潜艇，后来才意识到它是活的
and they originally thought it was a submarine, before realizing it was alive.
多年来曾有多张据称是宁根的照片
There have been multiple supposed pictures of the Ningen,
比如 2005 年那次，当时有一块冰山被误认为是海怪
like in 2005, where an iceberg was mistaken for a sea monster,
以及其他模糊不清的视频，大多拍的是我们已经熟知的其他动物
and other unclear videos that are mostly of other animals that we already know about,
但绝对没有两条腿、蛋形模样的生物
but definitely aren't of two-legged, egg-looking creatures.
所有关于宁根的艺术描绘中，我最喜欢的一点就是他们清一色全在用那张呆萌精子 PNG
What I love about all the artist renditions of the Ningen is that they all use the same exact dopey-looking sperm png.
它们用的腿部剪影和维基百科页面上的一模一样，放在现实背景里简直烂得出奇
They use the same leg cutouts that are on the wiki page, and it looks so shit on real-life backgrounds.
这太棒了，我希望他们永远别改
It's great. I never want it to change.
接下来谈谈幻视的话题
Calling back to the pareidolia stuff,
根据 NASA 的说法，B-17B 冰山看起来有点像卡通鲸鱼
Iceberg B-17B was a berg that looked kind of like a cartoon whale, according to NASA.
偏偏是他们作出这种比喻，真是让人哭笑不得。我挺乐在其中的
Of all the places that comparison could originate from. I'm glad to have fun over there.
这块冰山也超级大
It was also  a very large iceberg,
大概有曼哈顿的两倍大
at twice the size of Manhattan.
到了 2009 年 12 月前后，它已经漂到离澳大利亚挺近的地方了
Around December 2009, it was drifting close enough to Australia
甚至政府还专门发了警告，说可能会影响航道，航行也有危险
that a warning was issued by the government about possible disruption of shipping lanes and danger in the area.
我知道这在物理上是不可能的
I know it's, like, physically impossible,
但想象一下要是堵住巴拿马运河的不是船，而是一大块冰山
but imagine if a big iceberg clogged up the Panama Canal instead of a ship.
那画面肯定很搞笑
That'd be funny.
就想象一大块冰山，偏偏待在热得要命的地方
Just a big iceberg at a place that's hot as sin,
硬是死活不融化，好像硬要跟物理定律对着干
but won't melt because it's stubborn with a personal drudge against the idea of physics.
我知道底下藏着一只像货船那么大的螃蟹，比前面两种情况都酷，所以我选这个
I know there's a crab the size of a cargo ship under there, which is cooler than both the previous options, so I'll take it.
海华沙冰川位于格陵兰岛西北部
The Hiawatha Glacier is located in northwest Greenland.
该冰川于 1922 年首次被测绘
It was first mapped in 1922
2018 年在其下方发现巨型冰下陨石坑后引发了广泛关注
and got people taking a closer look at it when a massive crater was discovered underneath the glacier in 2018.
那个坑大得要命
It was big as hell,
位于地下一千米处
a kilometer underground,
横跨 31 公里，年龄约为 17.4 亿到 19.85 亿年
19 miles across, and some 1.74 to 1.985 billion with a B years old.
NASA 制作了这个精致的小型立体模型，他们将冰盖像包皮一样剥离
NASA made this nice little diorama where they peeled the ice sheet off like a foreskin to show what the bedrock
展示出冰川及其周边区域下方基岩的真实样貌
in and around the glacier looked like under everything.
没有人能完全确定这个陨坑是如何形成的
No one is entirely sure how the crater got there,
但对该地区岩石的研究以及撞击成因的分析表明
but research of the rocks in the area and the impact that caused it
这个陨石坑可能来自一颗直径略小于 1.6 公里的金属小行星
show that the crater might have been from a metallic asteroid a little less than a mile wide.
如果这是一个撞击坑
If this is an impact crater,
它将位列我们已知的前 25 大撞击坑之中
it would be on the top 25 biggest ones that we know of.
2016 年，西伯利亚奥贝湾沿岸绵延 18 公里的海滩上
The Siberian beach snowballs were near perfect, naturally ball-shaped clumps of snow that in 2016
出现了近乎完美的天然雪球奇观——这些西伯利亚海滩雪球由自然滚圆的雪块形成
covered the Gulf of Obe in Siberia for a stretch of 11 miles.
这些东西大小从棒球大小到近 0.9 米不等
These things were as little as baseball-sized to almost three feet across.
它们是由一种罕见的自然过程形成的，冰的小碎片在风和水的作用下被来回滚动
They're formed by a rare natural process where little bits of ice that have formed get rolled around by wind and water
最终滚成非常圆的球状，看起来像胸部假体
until they ball up into something very round that looked like boob implants.
结果这对当地人来说也是新鲜事
It turned out this was a new thing even for the locals
他们说以前从未见过这样的东西
who said they had never seen anything like them before.
无独有偶，虽然不是很相同，但在芬兰也自然出现过类似的冰球
It's not the exact same, but similar ice balls have naturally popped up in Finland
在那边，这类现象稍微常见一些
where it seems like it's a little more common.
你们知道吗？密歇根湖上也出现了冰球
And hey, what do you know? Ice balls have also popped up in Lake Michigan.
但与底特律相关的一切事物一样，它们看起来比欧洲版本要破旧得多
But like everything associated with Detroit, they look a lot more scuffed than Europe's version.
冰山融化导致局部海平面下降，这种有趣的现象在于：虽然冰山融化会抬升全球海平面
Icebergs melting, lowering sea levels locally is the kind of fun fact that melting icebergs will raise sea levels globally,
但在它们实际融化的区域
but wherever they actually melt,
海平面反而会降低
sea levels will go down in the area.
这是因为冰的消融会从物理上改变冰盖的引力作用
This is because the loss of ice physically alters the gravitational pull of an ice sheet,
这种现象早在 1880 年代就有人注意并开始研究了
and this is something that's been noticed and investigated since at least the 1880s.
冰山融化导致局部海平面下降的原理显然比我能搞懂的数学要复杂得多
There's obviously more to how that lowered sea level comes about that I could not hope to track the math on,
但还是挺有意思的——严格说，更像个冷知识，而不是冰山图里的必要条目
but it's still interesting though more of a fun fact than a full entry in the context of this chart
因为有一说一，这个机制搞得我有点猪脑过载了
because the mechanics kind of go over my head if I'm being honest.
古佛罗里达冰山是说几千年前
Icebergs in ancient Florida refers to how thousands of years ago
huge icebergs are believed to have gotten from iceberg alley to as far south as Florida.
据说有巨大的冰山从冰山走廊一路漂到了佛罗里达那么南的地方
而且可不是快融化的垂死冰山哦，是那种比埃菲尔铁塔还高的大冰山
Not on their deathbed icebergs either, like ones taller than the Eiffel Tower.
说冰山曾经在远古的佛罗里达海域游荡，本身就挺好笑的——
It's mostly just funny to say icebergs roamed the seas of ancient primordial Florida,
那时候连第一个佛罗里达人都还没踏上这片土地，更别提去改造大沼泽地了
long before the first Florida man ever set foot on its shores and terraformed the Everglades.
这个理论是根据冰山在海底留下的痕迹来的——
The theory is based on seabed gouging by ice,
它们移动的时候，会在海底划出切痕，好像留下了自己的旅行日志
where cuts on the seafloor as icebergs move left a trail of their adventures,
据说，那时候的冰山漂得比现在可远多了
which are believed to have gotten much farther away from their home than icebergs do today.
据说冰块从加拿大一路漂了 8000 公里向南，不只是漂到佛罗里达那么远
Ice was said to have drifted 5000 miles south from Canada, and it wouldn't just make it as far down as Florida,
but would more generally ferry down the entire United States east coast before giving into the warmer waters near the equator.
实际上大概会沿着整个美国东海岸慢慢向下，直到快到赤道附近遇到暖水才融化
冰山能漂这么远，部分原因是冰川融水的作用——
Part of icebergs making it this far is believed to be from glacial meltwater,
这些融水让冰山像在水面上冲浪一样，漂得比单靠自己更远
which allowed icebergs to surf on them farther along than they would on their own.
而且虽然是融化的冰水，但冰川融水还是比中大西洋的海水冷
And even though it's melted water, glacial melt is still colder than the water usually in the mid Atlantic,
所以冰山大概也能靠这点多漂一段路
so icebergs probably get a little extra mileage out of that too.
“纳粹南极秘密基地”指的是一种阴谋论，毕竟纳粹确实对南极探险很感兴趣
Secret Nazi Antarctic bases refers to the conspiracy stemming from the Nazis' genuine interest in exploring Antarctica,
由此衍生出他们可能在那儿发现了某些秘密或超自然事物的说法
with the idea that they may have discovered something secret and supernatural there,
或者至少建立了我们还未发现的隐藏基地
or at least had established hidden bases that we haven't found yet somehow.
德国人在 30 年代末确实进行了南极探险，比如 1938 到 1939 年
The Germans did run expeditions to Antarctica in the late 30s, like 1938 to 39,
他们声称占领了一些土地，拍了些照片
where they claimed some land, took some pictures,
也试图找点有用的东西
and tried to find anything useful,
但他们从未建立过永久定居点
but they never established a permanent settlement.
这些传闻比我在更衣室里被人传得还快——都是 1947 年
The rumors got passed around more than I did in the locker room by this random Hungarian bum, Ladislas Szabo,
可参考图书：Nazi Antarctic Exploration: Hitler's Escape to South America and Secret Bases in Antarctica
一个叫拉迪斯拉斯·萨博的匈牙利流浪汉提出来的
who brought it up in 1947.
不过，唯一可靠的证据只是显示
But the only reliable evidence we have
纳粹党卫军在 30 年代末短暂到过南极，其他说法都没被证实
shows that the SS were in Antarctica for a time in the late 30s where everything else is unproven.
接下来的这一个世纪
In the centuries since,
我们在南北两极都驻扎过，但没有出现什么新发现，至少没有公开的消息
we've posted up on both of the polls, and nothing new has come to light, at least nothing public.
就我个人来说，如果要猜的话，纳粹可能根本没在南极建立基地
Personally, if I had to guess, the Nazis might have never set up a base in the South Pole,
不仅因为那儿没什么好东西，还因为南极本身就是个鸟不拉屎的地方，根本不适合待着
not just because there was nothing there, but Antarctica is just a dogshit place to hang out.
而且他们是一群超级怂蛋
Also, they're massive fucking cowards.
我们早就知道他们承受不了寒冷，问问俄罗斯人就知道了
We already know they can't handle the cold, just ask the Russians.
负责这次探险的人大概是这样想的
Dude in charge of the trip was like,
嗯，什么都没有，哎卧槽，希儿肯定会非常生气的！
well, nothing's here. Oh man, Hitler's gonna be so bad!
我寻思还是赶紧走吧，免得他在那儿干等着
Guess we should, like, leave right now so he's not waiting.
我也同意，因为我现在几乎和讨厌那个神秘的 Julia 噪音一样讨厌南极了
Works for me, because I hate the South Pole now almost as much as I hate the mysterious Julia noise.
Julia 是 1999 年 3 月 1 日美国国家海洋和大气管理局（NOAA）利用赤道太平洋自主水听器阵列记录到的超低频声音
对，我就是这么讨厌它
Yeah, that's what I hate,
因为这是我最不喜欢、内容也最简单的一条，我却还是决定把它放进来了
because this is one of my least favorite and most bare-bones entries that I still chose to include.
几乎没有什么信息，也不是那种可以用疯狂理论去推测、还能讲得通的神秘事件
It has little to no info on it, not in a mystery-to-be-solved-with-nut-job-but-feasible-theories kind of way,
倒不如说它无聊透了，因为我们基本上早就知道它是什么了
rather in that it's fucking boring, since we basically already know what it is.
但不知怎么的，每次我看到极地谜团或者冰山图，它还是老是被提起
Yet somehow, it still keeps getting brought up in every arctic mystery or iceberg-iceberg chart that I see.
话说回来，Julia 是 1999 年在太平洋录到的一种声音，持续了 2 分 43 秒
Either way, Julia was a noise recorded in 1999 in the Pacific Ocean that lasted 2 minutes and 43 seconds.
如果你想听的话，这里有个加速版录音
Here's a sped up recording if you want it.
后来判断，这最有可能是一块在南极海岸某处搁浅的大冰山发出的声音
It was determined to most likely be a big iceberg that beached somewhere off the coast of Antarctica.
它具体搁浅的位置不清楚，但大概是在布兰斯菲尔德海峡和阿代尔角之间
It's unknown exactly where it landed, but it was narrowed down to be between the Branfield Straits and Cape Adair.
有些人和油管短视频还说这是未解之谜，但其实不对，早就有解释了
People and YouTube shorts will still say it's unexplained, but no, they explained it.
你只是不信他们的解释，总觉得那是海怪，也不知道为啥
You just don't believe them and think it's a sea monster for some reason.
不过仔细想想，冰山某种程度上也算是海怪，也算是埋了个伏笔
Icebergs kind of are sea monsters, though, if you think about it. That's foreshadowing.
你真信了短视频也无所谓其实
If you believe that, it's fine,
反正我们在南极已经听过好几次了，每次的声音都跟冰山崩裂和撞击的声响一模一样
even though we've literally heard this multiple times in the Antarctic and it matches the noise of iceberg calving and crashing events every time,
但你就是信偏方啊，兄弟
but you do, yo.
这让我有点烦，因为下一条其实是个更有趣的神秘未解之声
It just frustrates me because the next entry is literally a more interesting version of a mysterious, unexplained sound.
那我们干脆直接关注那个不就行了？
Why don't we just hone in on that one?
北加拿大的“砰”，或者简称“砰”，是那个迷子乐队的吉他手，哎呀嘴瓢了
The Northern Canada ping, or just the ping, is MyGo!!!. Whoops, my bad.
这是北加拿大弗里与赫克拉海峡附近的当地人几个月里多次报告听到的一种声音
It was a noise that locals near the Fury and Hecla Strait in Northern Canada reported hearing multiple times over the course of months,
这个倒是真的挺酷的
and this one is actually cool.
它之所以叫“砰”，是因为听起来像“砰”的一声，同时人们也形容它像是一种哔声或嗡鸣
It got its name from sounding like a ping, but was also described as a kind of beep or hum.
2016 年整个夏天，加拿大伊格卢利克的多位居民都听到了这种声音
It was heard through the summer of 2016 by multiple residents of Igloolik, Canada,
据说这声音是从海底传出来的
and supposedly originated from the seafloor.
当地的猎人认为，这声音是那一年猎物稀少的原因
Hunters in the area blamed it for the relative lack of game to hunt in that area for the year.
因为这件事后来闹挺大，加拿大军方最终也派人去调查了
A big enough fuss got made about it that the Canadian military eventually took a look.
他们在该地区进行了空中巡航，还用各种多传感器设备进行搜索
They ran flyovers and different multi-sensor searches in the area,
但最终什么也没发现，也没能解释这到底是怎么回事
but came up empty-handed and couldn't explain what the deal was.
他们说，无论水面上还是水下，都没发现什么引人注意的东西
They said there was nothing they saw above or below the surface that caught their eye.
援引报道“船员们唯一观察到的，是在关注区域里有两群鲸鱼和六只海象”
The only thing the crew did observe were two pods of whales and six walruses in the area of interest.
刻意写上这句话，就好像官方的说法是：是啊，我和那个人之前看到了一些鲸鱼
The explicit inclusion of that seems like the official government way of saying, yeah, me and the  guy saw some whales earlier.
真的很棒
It was awesome.
当然有一说一确实挺不错的
Which, to be fair, that does sound awesome.
流传的理论有好几种，比如可能是某矿业公司在用声纳调查
A few of the theories touted have been things like sonar surveys from a potential mining company,
绿色和平组织播放声音吓跑猎物，或者最无聊的一种——军事潜艇
Greenpeace playing the noise to scare wildlife away from the hunting ground, or somehow, the most boring one, military submarines.
2017 年初次空中巡航几个月后
A few months after the initial flyovers in 2017,
加拿大政府派了道格·布朗和军方的声学专家去伊格卢利克地区进一步调查
the Canadian government sent Doug Brown and acoustic experts in the Canadian military to the Igloolik area to do more sleuthing.
他在伊格利利克的时间大多用来与当地人交谈，
He spent the time in Iglilic mostly talking to locals,
他报告说，在镇上根本没碰到一个人听说过或相信“砰”的
where he reported that he didn't meet a single person in the town who had heard or believed in the ping,
再者整件事很可能只是最初那篇报道在传到网上时被误解了
and that the whole thing may have actually been a misunderstanding in the article that broke the story to the wider internet.
但事情并没有就此结束
But, that's not a wrap though.
村子里的人主要担心的，好像从来就不是那个“砰”
The main concern in the village didn't seem to have ever been the ping.
不管那个声音到底是真是假
Whether the sound itself was real or not,
确实有东西让动物没像往年一样出现在他们的狩猎场
something was genuinely making animals not come to their yearly hunting grounds like they usually did,
而搞清楚这件事原因才是真正的问题所在
and getting to the bottom of that was the heart of the issue.
当然，也有一些自然原因能解释这些动物为什么突然改变习性
There are natural explanations for why these animals broke with their habits,
但如果你真想在这件事里找点能打牙祭的悬念，那这个谜团到现在还是没解开
but that specific mystery still remains unsolved if you actually were looking for meat to chew on in one of these.
所谓的神秘坑洞，或者叫神秘大洞——不是你想的那种，别想歪了
Mystery craters, or mystery holes, is not a sex thing.
它指的是一系列地面上出现的大坑
It's a range of different divots in the earth
奇怪的是它们都有个共同点——没人知道这些坑到底哪儿来的
that are all tied together in that we don't know how they got there.
这些坑可能就是在人没注意的时候突然冒出来的
They may have randomly appeared while someone wasn't looking,
或者它们有些特别的特征，看起来像是背后还有我们没搞明白的东西在作祟
or have unique properties to them that suggest there's something we don't yet understand at work.
我这段说得比较笼统，不过举个例子
I'm speaking very generally in this entry, but for instance,
西伯利亚那边就冒出来过一堆突然出现的巨坑
there have been these series of craters that have just been opening up all of a sudden in Siberia.
这些大坑能有 30 米深
These things can get like a hundred feet deep,
而自从 2013 年起，光在那片区域就已经冒出来至少九个这样的“突然现身”的巨洞
and there have been at least nine like this that randomly showed  up in the region since 2013.
科学家们在同一时间内能够进行的研究数量有限
Scientists are limited on the amount of research they can do at one time,
因为他们必须携带设备亲自爬入陨坑内部进行查看
because they have to physically climb down into the crater with their equipment to take a look,
但这些大坑在两年内就会变成湖
but the craters also turn into lakes after only two years,
也就是说留给研究的时间窗口其实挺短的
which is a relatively small window of time to work with.
这种坑一般是由积聚的甲烷气体突然释放形成的
This type of hole specifically is believed to come from built-up methane gas,
最后就像点着了导火线一样爆开，周围温度升高
finally having its fuse pop, which then increases the temperature of the local area,
环境变得更热，还可能引发其他可燃物反应
making it warmer and potentially setting off more combustible stuff.
没人能肯定知道，
No one knows for sure,
因为人们都是在这些坑出现之后才发现它们的
because people have only been finding these things after they happened,
而且大多数都是偶然看到的，比如猎人或者随便飞过去的直升机发现的
usually by chance too, like a hunter or random helicopter seeing it went out and about.
南极的另一个神秘坑洞至少从 1989 年就为人所知了
Another mystery orifice in Antarctica has actually been known about since at least 1989,
当时人们认为那是一次古老陨石撞击形成的
and was thought to be an old meteor impact site.
但后来发现，那其实是一个塌陷的湖泊——
But that thing turned out to be a collapsed lake
冰层在某个时候裂开，湖水全部流走
where the ice cracked open at some point and all the water flowed out of the lake,
只留下了这个大坑
leaving just the crater.
这就意味着，它不仅不是古老的陨石遗迹
This meant it wasn't just some old space relic landmark
还实在显示了该地区冰层大量融化的迹象
but actually a sign of strong melting in the area.
而且这些融化发生的时间比我们原本以为的要早得多
Melting that happened much earlier than we originally thought,
所以情况不太妙
so not good.
“洛夫克拉夫特式冰山”是指亲眼见过冰山的人通常用来形容它们的方式——
Lovecraftian icebergs is in reference to the general way people who have seen icebergs in person describe them
看起来超凡脱俗、难以理解
as otherworldly or incomprehensible,
更像城市或水晶建筑，而不是地球上的普通自然景观，比如...
as more like cities or like crystalline buildings than any other natural feature on earth, which like
我现在就能看见
yeah I can see it,
再加上在寒冷环境下那些奇怪的现象
as well as like the nutty phenomenon in cold conditions
如果你不知道是怎么回事，那看起来简直像巫术或者恶魔在捉弄你一样
that would seem like straight witchcraft or demons playing tricks on you if you weren't aware of how these things happen.
我们之前也讨论过不少，但冰山翻转时释放的能量，轻松能跟核弹相比
We've touched on a lot of this already, but bergs flipping can easily release the energy of a nuke.
它们是由数十万年的古冰构成，经历了漫长时间和巨大力量的作用
They are made of ice that is hundreds of thousands of years old, they are products of time scales and forces we can barely just now comprehend in this century,
我们直到现在也只能大概理解它们
and only in general terms.
它们的规模可以比国家还要大，可以移动数十公里摧毁人类建造的任何东西
They can be bigger than countries and move for miles to destroy anything that man has built,
有时我们根本无能为力去反抗
sometimes with nothing we can do to fight back.
冰山一旦长得太大，人类就根本没法管得住
If icebergs get too big, they are essentially unmanageable forces of nature that no current human effort can stimmy,
它们的变化和力量，几乎像全能的超自然力量一样无法阻挡
and they are functionally as unstoppable in their whims as all-powerful supernatural forces.
不过，这也拦不住人们试着在冰川破裂时冲浪——这其实也不算新鲜事
This hasn't stopped people from trying to surf on glaciers as they break though, but that's not anything new either.
尽管我们对北极和虚空生物知之甚少
Despite how much we don't understand about the arctic or beings from the aether,
这也没阻止我们伸手去掘冰，想挖出点可以用的东西，仿佛那是神秘的肉体销钉一样
that didn't stop us from sticking our claws into the ice and trying to dig up some goo we could use like it's the mystery flesh pin.
说白了，“冰山一角”这句话就是提醒我们
Hell, the tip of the iceberg saying is literally about how much there is we
冰山大部分都藏在海面下，根本看不到，也很难了解
can't know about or understand about any given iceberg
because most of it is in the dark depths under the ocean.
它凝视着你，而我们永远无法彻底看透它
In a bish we can't fully ever know, it's staring back at you.
无数泰坦尼克号的幸存者在经历那场难以言喻的灾难后
There are numerous accounts of titanic survivors coming off the back of surviving an unfathomable disaster,
都以带着敬畏与警惕的目光描述了那些冰山
all describing  the icebergs there with a kind of awe and healthy amount of fear.
他们常说自己被巍峨的冰墙包围、困在其中，不过难免带有些许夸张
They often recount being all encompassed and boxed in by ice that towered above them, though they may be a bit biased.
劳拉·梅布尔·弗朗卡特利回忆道，在她的救生艇上，他们像疯了一样驶过高耸如山的冰山
Laura Mabel Francatelli said that on her lifeboat they passed icebergs like mountains
只为避开与之相撞的必死命运
and rode like mad to avoid the certain death of hitting them.
休·沃尔纳说：“天亮时，我们看到无数色彩各异的冰山，阳光洒下
Hugh Wollner said, At daylight we saw a great many icebergs of different colors. As the sun struck them,
有的白如雪，有的蓝如海，有的带着淡紫，还有的深灰如墨
some looked white, some looked blue, some looked mauve, and others were dark gray.
有一座‘双峰’冰山，看起来体型相当庞大，估计高约百尺。”
There was one double-toothed one that looked to be of good size. It must have been about 100 feet high.
W·T·斯洛珀说，在黑暗中，一艘巨大的船只从他的救生艇旁擦过，仅相隔几十米
W.T. Sloper said, A large ship passed within a few hundred feet of his lifeboat during darkness.
其他幸存者也经历了同样的情景，黑暗中他们尚未察觉
The same experience during darkness was similarly experienced by others,
直到黎明才发现，那竟是一座冰山
only at dawn did they realize it was an iceberg,
还有许多人同样有如此经历
plus a whole lot others liked that.
在冰山翻转的视频评论里，人们纷纷分享亲身经历
On videos of icebergs flipping, the comments are full of first-hand accounts
描述看到如此巨大的冰块翻动时那种难以言喻的敬畏感
of the sort of reverence a person feels when seeing something that big move so much.
我曾在智利的一座冰川亲眼见过这一幕
I saw this first-hand in a glacier in Chile.
出乎意料，那情景带着一股阴森的气息
I wasn't expecting it and it was rather sinister.
那是一幕令人震撼、令人警觉的景象
It was an intimidating and alarming spectacle,
尤其当时我正坐在一艘橡皮艇上
particularly as I was in a zodiac inflatable boat at the time.
我们尽快往后退了一段，因为这些冰山足以引发海啸
We moved a ways back as quickly as we could because these things can generate tsunamis.
这是另一段视频的评论
On another video,
当冰山从水面升起时，它竟有一瞬间像极了哥特式大教堂
as it rises out of the water, it looks like a gothic cathedral for a while.
宛如行走的诗篇
Poetry in motion.
即便远不及亲眼所见，透过视频我们仍能略感冰山崩裂的气势
We can get a glimpse of what a calving iceberg feels like based on footage, even if it's nothing compared to it in person.
然而，请看这令人震撼的景象——这正是我此刻眼前的冰山翻转
Still, peep the horror. This is an iceberg flipping where I am now.
看起来就像海底的行星吞噬者正要站起来似的，真是吓人
It looks like Galactus could be standing up from under the water or some shit.
行星吞噬者（英语：Galactus），又译加拉图斯，是一名出现在漫威漫画中的宇宙神明
我对那般巨量水流的景象只能有个大概的想象，因为我们平时看到的都是电脑特效
I only have an idea what that amount of water moving is supposed to look like because it's in CGI all the time.
就在此刻，它真实地翻动着
And here it is, just happening.
早前提到的吉尔·艾纳斯回忆，当她在冰山洞穴潜水时
Jill Einarth from earlier recalled that when cave diving in the iceberg,
外面的船员看到冰山翻转
the crew who saw it flip while she was still inside
以为她和其他潜水员肯定完了——从水面上看，那冰山的翻动几乎不可逾越
thought her and the other divers were for sure dead because of how insurmountable it looks from the surface.
在一条询问海员们见过的最离奇海上景象的讨论串中，有位海员说道
On a thread asking mariners what the weirdest thing they've seen at sea was, this dude said,
有些冰山看起来仿佛高百万尺
或悬浮于空中，甚至颠倒——宛如海市蜃楼
我实在无法理解早期的水手们如何保持理智
因为在那种景象面前，你根本无法信任自己的双眼
这是个匿名的 Reddit 账号，所以我无法核实真实性
This is an anonymous reddit account so I can't verify it,
但我见过的类似经历可不止这一条
but it's not the only one like it I've seen.
帖子里说的“海市蜃楼”，是一种幻象，会让远处的物体位置或形状完全变得扭曲
The Fata Morgana thing mentioned in the post is a mirage where distant objects can have their location or shape completely distorted.
这种现象在麦克默多湾以及整个极地地区都很常见
They happen a lot in the McMurdo Sound and polar regions in general,
有理论认为，它或许能解释历史上多次关于“幽灵岛”或失落之岛的目击报道
and it's theorized to account for several reports of ghost or lost islands that have been reported throughout history.
比如说，1821年12月，威廉·埃利奥特船长曾报告过一座“幻影翡翠岛”
For instance, the Phantom Emerald Island reported by Captain William Elliott in December 1821,
57°30′S 162°12′E
但那座岛从未被找到，也没有被证实存在
but that was never actually found or confirmed to be real.
你也知道，南极的孤寂和极端环境长期以来曾让许多人精神崩溃
As you know by now, there's also a long history of people going nuts from the isolation and conditions of Antarctica.
有记录显示，人们在这种环境下会变得缄默无言，也有人因孤独和无聊而行为暴力
Reports of people going non-verbal from the conditions, folks acting violently from their boredom of isolation,
还有各种其他心理反应
among other psychological reactions.
这些现象并非不可理解，也并非只在南极才会出现
That's nothing unexplainable or that doesn't happen in other places,
但按人均计算，极地的发生率确实稍高一些
but it also definitely happens a little more often per capita at the polls.
综上所述，人们会相信冰层下正发生着某种灾难般的秘密，我也就不觉得怪了
With all that said, it's not really surprising to me anymore that people think some secret stuff of cataclysmic proportions is going on under the ice.
南极是一片寂静、荒凉、充满敌意的冰雪荒原，除了冰和企鹅一无所有
The South Pole is a silent, desolate, and hostile wasteland of nothing but ice and penguins
仿佛随时可能有未知之物从冰层下迸发而出
that seems ripe for something unseen to burst out from under.
一个随时可能发生的事件，将彻底改变我们对世界的根本认知与看法
An event just waiting to happen that would change our fundamental understanding and view of the world.
无论是某种东西、飞碟、或是纳粹早已发现却未公开的秘密……
The thing, UFOs, something the Nazis already found and didn't share.
人们的想象力总是让各种恐怖潜伏在这片冰冷之地
People's imagination think there is all kinds of horror lurking in the cold.
我理解人们的这些想象与动机
And I understand the motivation for all of that,
但对我而言，那种宇宙般的恐怖并不在冰层之中，也不藏于其下
but to me, the cosmic horror isn't anything in the ice or a threat lurking beneath it.
对我而言，真正的恐怖是冰本身——
To me, the horror is the ice.
那些从相当于欧洲大小的母体中崩裂而出的巨型冰块，横扫千里，带来惊骇与混乱
Big-ass giants that break off their Europe-sized origin to terrorize and cause  issues thousands of miles away from where they started.
它们横扫过一切人类建造的结构，却丝毫不知自己所为
They tear through every human structure it wants without having any concept of that being what it's doing.
这一切，最终只为了融化
All of it to just melt later on,
慢慢地可能促成那场最具存在威胁、最具破坏力、却又不可见的灾难
to slowly contribute to potentially the most existential, most devastating, and somehow unseeable disaster.
它虽进程缓慢，却更具破坏力，前所未有，人类从未面对过这样的威胁
One that, while it's a slow burn, is more destructive and unlike any threat humanity has withstood before.
你大概能看出来，这都是我自己即兴写下的
You can probably tell this is something I've shit out on my own.
将冰山想象成某种无法理解的洛氏力量的触手
The idea of icebergs being the arm of some incomprehensible lovecraftian force,
再加上那些真实目睹它们的人所描述的震撼场景，总能让我脑洞大开
along with the accounts of just how shocking these things are to see for real just get my brain going.
我喜爱那种源自未知的深深恐惧
I love the fear of the unknown type of thing.
没座，冰山冰山图堂堂完结
And yeah, that was my iceberg iceberg chart explained.
希望大家喜欢，我已经有一阵子没做视频了，这算是我回归后的第一条
I hope y'all enjoyed it. Uh, this is my first video back in a while now.
并非每条视频都会如此，但还是希望你们能告诉我你们的看法
They aren't all going to be like this, but please let me know what y'all think.
其实我早在停更前就已经开始一点点打磨这个视频了
I've been chipping away at this video since even before my break.
我是从去年就开始筹备这个视频的，所以真心希望它能让大家满意
Like I started this last year, so I really hope that it came together for y'all.
感谢那些少数而勇敢的先行者——那些在我之前制作冰山冰山图的人
Thank you to the few, the proud, the brave, the dudes who made iceberg iceberg charts before me,
尽管我在这条视频里没有直接使用他们的成果
even though I didn't end up directly covering any of them in this video.
但正是他们让寻找精彩素材轻松了许多
Some of these made finding cool stuff so much easier.
接下来是 Reddit 用户致谢名单
Get ready for some butchered reddit usernames.
致那些在我之前就制作过冰山图的前辈们
For the iceberg charts that you made before me.
同时要向 GanStarr4Life 致以最诚挚的谢意，他的“北极奇观冰山图”真是宏大而精彩
And a massive, huge thank you to GanStarr4Life for their gigantic arctic obscurities iceberg.
上面还有许多我没有在视频里涉及的内容
There's lots of stuff on there I didn't feel fit in this video
如果你对北极或南极的未解之谜感兴趣，非常值得去探一探
that might be worth checking out if you're interested in arctic or antarctic mysteries.
其实我以前几乎没尝试过这种形式，所以非常希望能收到大家的反馈
I haven't done something like this ever really, so feedback is appreciated.
想听听大家觉得哪些地方没抓到点子，哪些地方还算成功之类的
What fell flat, what worked, that kind of thing,
因为我确实希望能多做几条这样的内容
because I definitely want to make more of this.
呃，总之，回来真好，这里虽然一片寂静，但呃，我可是死不了的
Uh, yeah, anyways, it's good to be back. This has been quite, and uh, you can't kill me.